<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title xml:lang="eng">
	      Acts of John
      </title>
      <author>
	      Anonymous
      </author>
      <funder>
        University of Virginia
      </funder>
      <respStmt>
        <resp>Published original versions of the electronic texts</resp>
        <orgName ref="https://www.opengreekandlatin.org">Open Greek and Latin</orgName>
        <persName role="principal">Gregory Crane</persName>
        <persName role="principal">Leonard Muellner</persName>
        <persName role="principal">Bruce Robertson</persName>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <resp>proofreader</resp>
        <persName>
          <forename>Ann</forename>
          <surname>Burns</surname>
        </persName>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <resp>CTS conversion</resp>
        <orgName>
		Mount Allison University
        </orgName>
        <persName>
          Bruce Robertson
        </persName>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Open Greek and Latin</publisher>
      <idno type="filename">tlg2038.tlg001.1st1K-eng2.xml</idno>
      <pubPlace />
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Available under a Creative Commons
        Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License</licence>
      </availability>
      <date when="2020-10-13" />
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <biblStruct>
        <monogr>
          <author>
            <persName>James, M. R.</persName>
          </author>
          <!--Short version of title; no period; lang attribute-->
          <title xml:lang="eng">The Apocryphal New Testament, being the Apocryphal Gospels, Acts, Epistles, and Apocalypses</title>
          <editor />
          <imprint>
            <pubPlace>
              Oxford
            </pubPlace>
	    <publisher>Clarendon Press</publisher>
            <date>1924</date>
          </imprint>
        </monogr>
	<ref target="https://archive.org/details/JAMESApocryphalNewTestament1924/page/n254/mode/1up">
		Internet Archive
        </ref>
      </biblStruct>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <editorialDecl>
      <correction>
        <p>Lace v. 0.6.14 copyright 2013-2020, Bruce Robertson, Dept. of Classics, Mount Allison University.
        Developed through the support of the 
        <ref target="https://nbif.ca/en">NBIF</ref>.</p>
      </correction>
    </editorialDecl>
    <p>The following text is encoded in accordance with EpiDoc standards and with the CTS/CITE Architecture</p>
    <refsDecl n="CTS">
      <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)" n="sections"
      replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])" />
    </refsDecl>
    <p>This pointer pattern extracts sections.</p>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">English</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <!-- put your name in 'who' and this date in YYYY-MM-DD format in 'when' -->
    <change when="2020-10-10" who="Ann Burns">initial markup of new file.</change>
    <change when="2020-11-27" who="Charlotte Houghton">CTS and EpiDoc work.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
  <body>
    <div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0317.tlg001.1st1K-eng2" xml:lang="eng">
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18">
        <p rend="indent">
        <pb facs="JAMESApocryphalNewTestament1924_0254" />Now John was hastening to Ephesus, moved thereto by a
        vision. Damonicus therefore, and Aristodemus his kinsman, and a certain very rich man Cleobius, and the wife of
        Marcellus, hardly prevailed to keep him for one day in Miletus, reposing themselves with him. And when very
        early in the morning they had set forth, and already about four miles of the journey were accomplished, a voice
        came from heaven in the hearing of all of us, saying: John, thou art about to give glory to thy Lord in
        Ephesus, whereof thou shalt know, thou and all the brethren that are with thee, and certain of them that are
        there, which shall believe by thy means. John therefore pondered, rejoicing in himself, what it should be that
        should befall (meet) him at Ephesus, and said: Lord, behold 1 go according to thy will: let that be done which
        thou desirest. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19">
        <p rend="indent"> And as we drew near to the city, Lycomedes the praetor of the Ephesians, a man of large substance,
        met us, and falling at John’s feet besought him, saying: Is thy name John? the God whom thou preachest hath
        sent thee to do good unto my wife, who hath been smitten with palsy now these seven days and lieth incurable.
        But glorify thou thy God by healing her, and have compassion on us. For as I was considering with myself what
        resolve to take in this matter, one stood by me and said: Lycomedes, cease from this thought which warreth
        against thee, for it is evil (hard): submit not thyself unto it. For I have compassion upon mine handmaid
        Cleopatra, and have sent from Miletus a man named John who shall raise her up and restore her to thee whole.
        Tarry not, therefore, thou servant of the God who hath manifested himself unto me, but hasten unto my wife who
        hath no more than breath. And straightway John went from the gate, with the brethren that were with 
        <pb facs="JAMESApocryphalNewTestament1924_0255" />him and Lycomedes, unto his house. But Cleobius said to
        his young men: Go ye to my kinsman Callippus and receive of him comfortable entertainment—for I am come hither
        with his son—that we may find all things decent. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20">
        <p rend="indent"> Now when Lycomedes came with John into the house wherein his wife lay, he caught hold again of his
        feet and said: See, lord, the withering of the beauty, see the youth, see the renowned flower of my poor wife,
        whereat all Ephesus was wont to marvel: wretched me, I have suffered envy, I have been humbled, the eye of mine
        enemies hath smitten me: I have never wronged any, though I might have injured many, for I looked before to
        this very thing, and took care, lest I should see any evil or any such ill fortune as this. What profit, then,
        hath Cleopatra from my anxiety? what have I gained by being known for a pious man until this day? nay, I suffer
        more than the impious, in that I see thee, Cleopatra, lying in such plight. The sun in his course shall no more
        see me conversing with thee: I will go before thee, Cleopatra, and rid myself of life: I will not spare mine
        own safety though it be yet young. I will defend myself before Justice, that I have rightly deserted, for I may
        indict her as judging unrighteously. I will be avenged on her when I come before her as a ghost &lt;bereft&gt;
        of life. I will say to her: Thou didst force me to leave the light when thou didst rob me of Cleopatra: thou
        didst cause me to become a corpse when thou sentest me this ill fortune: thou didst compel me to insult
        Providence, by cutting off my joy in life (my confidence). </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="21">
        <p rend="indent"> And with yet more words Lycomedes addressing Cleopatra came near to the bed and cried aloud and
        lamented: but John pulled him away, and said: Cease from these lamentations and from thine unfitting words:
        thou must not disobey him that (?) appeared unto thee: for know that thou shalt receive thy consort again.
        Stand, therefore, with us that have come hither on her account and pray to the God whom thou sawest manifesting
        himself unto thee in dreams. What, then, is it, Lycomedes? Awake, thou also, and open thy soul. Cast off the
        heavy sleep from thee: beseech the Lord, entreat him for thy wife, and he will raise her up. But he fell upon
        the floor and lamented, fainting.<ref target="n1"><hi rend="superscript">1</hi></ref>
        <note xml:id="n1" type="foot">It is evident from what follows that Lycomedes died: but the text does not say so; 
        some words may have fallen out</note></p>
        <p rend="indent">John therefore said with tears: Alas for the fresh (new) betraying of my
        vision! for the new temptation that is prepared for me! for the new device of him that contriveth against me!
        the voice from heaven that was borne unto me in the way, hath it devised this for me? was it this that it
        foreshowed me should come to pass here, betraying me to this great multitude of the citizens because of
        Lycomedes? the man lieth without 
        <pb facs="JAMESApocryphalNewTestament1924_0256" /> breath, and I know well that they will not suffer me
        to go out of the house alive. Why tarriest thou, Lord (or, what wilt thou do)? why hast thou shut off from us
        thy good promise? Do not, I beseech thee, Lord, do not give him cause to exult who rejoiceth in the suffering
        of others; give him not cause to dance who alway derideth us; but let thy holy name and thy mercy make haste.
        Raise up these two dead whose death is against me. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="22">
        <p rend="indent">And even as John thus cried out, the city of the Ephesians ran together to the house of Lycomedes,
        hearing that he was dead. And John, beholding the great multitude that was come, said unto the Lord: Now is the
        time of refreshment and of confidence toward thee, O Christ; now is the time for us who are sick to have the
        help that is of thee, O physician who healest freely; keep thou mine entering in hither safe from derision. I
        beseech thee, Jesu, succour this great multitude that it may come to thee who art Lord of all things: behold
        the affliction, behold them that lie here. Do thou prepare, even from them that are assembled for that end,
        holy vessels for thy service, when they behold thy gift. For thyself hast said, O Christ, ‘Ask, and it shall be
        given you’. We ask therefore of thee, O king, not gold, not silver, not substance, not possessions, nor aught
        of what is on earth and perisheth, but two souls, by whom thou shalt convert them that are here unto thy way,
        unto thy teaching, unto thy liberty (confidence), unto thy most excellent (or unfailing) promise: for when they
        perceive thy power in that those that have died are raised, they will be saved, some of them. Do thou thyself,
        therefore, give them hope in thee: and so go I unto Cleopatra and say: Arise in the name of Jesus Christ.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="23">
        <p rend="indent">And he came to her and touched her face and said: Cleopatra, He saith, whom every ruler feareth, and
        every creature and every power, the abyss and all darkness, and unsmiling death, and the height of heaven, and
        the circles of hell [and the resurrection of the dead, and the sight of the blind], and the whole power of the
        prince of this world, and the pride of the ruler: Arise, and be not an occasion unto many that desire not to
        believe, or an affliction unto souls that are able to hope and to be saved. And Cleopatra straightway cried
        with a loud voice: I arise, master: save thou thine handmaid. </p>
        <p rend="indent">Now when she had arisen &lt;who had lain
        incurable for&gt; seven days, the city of the Ephesians was moved at the unlooked-for sight. And Cleopatra
        asked concerning her husband Lycomedes, but John said to her: Cleopatra, if thou keep thy soul unmoved and
        steadfast, thou shalt forthwith have Lycomedes thine husband standing here beside thee, if at least thou be not
        disturbed nor moved at that which hath befallen, having believed on my God, who by my means shall grant him
        unto thee alive. 
        <pb facs="JAMESApocryphalNewTestament1924_0257" />Come therefore with me into thine other bedchamber, and
        thou shalt behold him, a dead corpse indeed, but raised again by the power of my God. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="24">
        <p rend="indent"> And Cleopatra going with John into her bedchamber, and seeing Lycomedes dead for her sake, had no
        power to speak (suffered in her voice), and ground her teeth and bit her tongue, and closed her eyes, raining
        down tears: and with calmness gave heed to the apostle. But John had compassion on Cleopatra when he saw that
        she neither raged nor was beside herself, and called upon the perfect and condescending mercy, saying: Lord
        Jesus Christ, thou seest the pressure of sorrow, thou seest the need; thou seest Cleopatra shrieking her soul
        out in silence, for she constraineth within her the frenzy that cannot be borne; and I know that for Lycomedes’
        sake she also will die upon his body. And she said quietly to John: That have I in mind, master, and nought
        else. </p>
        <p rend="indent">And the apostle went to the couch whereon Lycomedes lay, and taking Cleopatra’s hand he said: Cleopatra,
        because of the multitude that is present, and thy kinsfolk that have come in, with strong crying, say thou to
        thine husband: Arise and glorify the name of God, for he giveth back the dead to the dead. And she went to her
        husband and said to him according as she was taught, and forthwith raised him up. And he, when he arose, fell
        on the floor and kissed John’s feet, but he raised him, saying: O man, kiss not my feet but the feet of God by
        whose power ye are both arisen. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="25">
        <p rend="indent"> But Lycomedes said to John:  I entreat and adjure thee by the God in whose name thou hast raised us,
        to abide with us, together with all them that are with thee. Likewise Cleopatra also caught his feet and said
        the same. And John said to them: For to-morrow I will be with you. And they said to him again: We shall have no
        hope in thy God, but shall have been raised to no purpose, if thou abide not with us. And Cleobius with
        Aristodemus and Damonicus were touched in the soul and said to John: Let us abide with them, that they continue
        without offence towards the Lord. So he continued there with the brethren. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="26">
        <p rend="indent"> There came together therefore a gathering of a great multitude on John’s account; and as he
        discoursed to them that were there, Lycomedes, who had a friend who was a skilful painter, went hastily to him
        and said to him: You see me in a great hurry to come to you: come quickly to my house and paint the man whom I
        show you without his knowing it. And the painter, giving some one the necessary implements and colours, said to
        Lycomedes: Show him to me, and for the rest have no anxiety. And Lycomedes pointed out John to the painter, and
        brought him near him, and shut him up in a room from which the apostle of Christ could be seen. And Lycomedes
        was with the blessed man, feasting on the faith and the knowledge 
        <pb facs="JAMESApocryphalNewTestament1924_0258" /> of our God, and rejoiced yet more in the thought
        that he should possess him in a portrait. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="27">
        <p rend="indent"> The painter, then, on the first day made an outline of him and went away. And on the next he painted
        him in with his colours, and so delivered the portrait to Lycomedes to his great joy. And he took it and set it
        up in his own bedchamber and hung it with garlands: so that later John, when he perceived it, said to him: My
        beloved child, what is it that thou always doest when thou comest in from the bath into thy bedchamber alone?
        do not I pray with thee and the rest of the brethren? or is there something thou art hiding from us? And as he
        said this and talked jestingly with him, he went into the bedchamber, and saw the portrait of an old man
        crowned with garlands, and lamps and altars set before it. And he called him and said: Lycomedes, what meanest
        thou by this matter of the portrait? can it be one of thy gods that is painted here? for I see that thou art
        still living in heathen fashion. And Lycomedes answered him: My only God is he who raised me up from death with
        my wife: but if, next to that God, it be right that the men who have benefited us should be called gods—it is
        thou, father, whom I have had painted in that portrait, whom i crown and love and reverence as having become my
        good guide. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="28">
        <p rend="indent"> And John who had never at any time seen his own face said to him: Thou mockest me, child: am I like
        that in form, &lt;excelling&gt; thy Lord? how canst thou persuade me that the portrait is like me? And
        Lycomedes brought him a mirror. And when he had seen himself in the mirror and looked earnestly at the
        portrait, he said: As the Lord Jesus Christ liveth, the portrait is like me: yet not like me, child, but like
        my fleshly image; for if this painter, who hath imitated this my face, desireth to draw me in a portrait, he
        will be at a loss, &lt;needing more than&gt; the colours that are now given †to thee†, and boards and plaster
        (?) and glue (?), and the position of my shape, and old age and youth and all things that are seen with the
        eye. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="29">
        <p rend="indent"> But do thou become for me a good painter, Lycomedes. Thou hast colours which he giveth thee through
        me, who painteth all of us for himself, even Jesus, who knoweth the shapes and appearances and postures and
        dispositions and types of our souls. And the colours wherewith I bid thee paint are these: faith in God,
        knowledge, godly fear, friendship, communion, meekness, kindness, brotherly love, purity, simplicity,
        tranquillity, fearlessness, grieflessness, sobriety, and the whole band of colours that painteth the likeness
        of thy soul, and even now raiseth up thy members that were cast down, and levelleth them that were lifted up,
        and tendeth thy bruises, and healeth thy wounds, and ordereth thine hair that was disarranged, and washeth thy
        face, and chasteneth thine eyes, and purgeth thy bowels, and emptieth thy belly, and cutteth off that which is 
        <pb facs="JAMESApocryphalNewTestament1924_0259" />beneath it; and in a word, when the whole company and
        mingling of such colours is come together, into thy soul, it shall present it to our Lord Jesus Christ
        undaunted, whole (unsmoothed), and firm of shape. But this that thou hast now done is childish and imperfect:
        thou hast drawn a dead likeness of the dead. </p>
        <note type="inline">There need be no portion of text lost at this point: but possibly 
        some few sentences have been omitted. The transition is abrupt and the new episode has not,
        as elsewhere, a title of its own.</note>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="30">
        <p rend="indent"> And he commanded Verus (Berus), the brother that ministered to him, to gather the aged women that
        were in all Ephesus, and made ready, he and Cleopatra and Lycomedes, all things for the care of them. Verus,
        then, came to John, saying: Of the aged women that are here over threescore years old I have found four only
        sound in body, and of the rest some . . . <note type="inline">(a word gone)</note> and some palsied and others sick. And when he heard
        that, John kept silence for a long time, and rubbed his face and said: O the slackness (weakness) of them that
        dwell in Ephesus! O the state of dissolution, and the weakness toward God! O devil, that hast so long mocked
        the faithful in Ephesus! Jesus, who giveth me grace and the gift to have my confidence in him, saith to me in
        silence: Send after the old women that are sick and come (be) with them into the theatre, and through me heal
        them: for there are some of them that will come unto this spectacle whom by these healings I will convert and
        make them useful for some end. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="31">
        <p rend="indent"> Now when all the multitude was come together to Lycomedes, he dismissed them on John’s behalf,
        saying: To-morrow come ye to the theatre, as many as desire to see the power of God. And the multitude, on the
        morrow, while it was yet night, came to the theatre: so that the proconsul also heard of it and hasted and took
        his seat with all the people. And a certain praetor, Andronicus, who was the first of the Ephesians at that
        time, put it about that John had promised things impossible and incredible: But if, said he, he is able to do
        any such thing as I hear, let him come into the public theatre, when it is open, naked, and holding nothing in
        his hands, neither let him name that magical name which I have heard him utter. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="32">
        <p rend="indent">John therefore, having heard this and being moved by these words, commanded the aged women to be
        brought into the theatre: and when they were all brought into the midst, some of them upon beds and others
        lying in a deep sleep, and all the city had run together, and a great silence was made, John opened his mouth
        and began to say: </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="33">
        <p rend="indent">Ye men of Ephesus, learn first of all wherefore I am visiting in your city, or what is this great
        confidence which I have towards you, so that it may become manifest to this general assembly and to all of you
        (or, so that I manifest myself to). I have been sent, then, upon a mission which is not of man’s ordering, and 
        <pb facs="JAMESApocryphalNewTestament1924_0260" />not upon any vain journey; neither am I a merchant that
        make bargains or exchanges; but Jesus Christ whom I preach, being compassionate and kind, desireth by my means
        to convert all of you who are held in unbelief and sold unto evil lusts, and to deliver you from error; and by
        his power will I confound even the unbelief of your praetor, by raising up them that lie before you, whom ye
        all behold, in what plight and in what sicknesses they are. And to do this (to confound Andronicus) is not
        possible for me if they perish: therefore shall they †be healed†. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="34">
        <p rend="indent"> But this first I have desired to sow in your ears, even that ye should take care for your souls—on
        which account I am come unto you—and not expect that this time will be for ever, for it is but a moment, and
        not lay up treasures upon the earth where all things do fade. Neither think that when ye have gotten children
        ye can rest upon them (?), and try not for their sakes to defraud and overreach. Neither, ye poor, be vexed if
        ye have not wherewith to minister unto pleasures; for men of substance when they are diseased call you happy.
        Neither, ye rich, rejoice that ye have much money, for by possessing these things ye provide for yourselves
        grief that ye cannot be rid of when ye lose them; and besides, while it is with you, ye are afraid lest some
        one attack you on account of it. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="35">
        <p rend="indent"> Thou also that art puffed up because of the shapeliness of thy body, and art of an high look, shalt
        see the end of the promise thereof in the grave; and thou that rejoicest in adultery, know that both law and
        nature avenge it upon thee, and before these, conscience; and thou, adulteress, that art an adversary of the
        law, knowest not whither thou shalt come in the end. And thou that sharest not with the needy, but hast monies
        laid up, when thou departest out of this body and hast need of some mercy when thou burnest in fire, shalt have
        none to pity thee; and thou the wrathful and passionate, know that thy conversation is like the brute beasts;
        and thou, drunkard and quarreller, learn that thou losest thy senses by being enslaved to a shameful and dirty
        desire. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="36">
        <p rend="indent"> Thou that rejoicest in gold and delightest thyself with ivory and jewels, when night falleth, canst
        thou behold what thou lovest? thou that art vanquished by soft raiment, and then leavest life, will those
        things profit thee in the place whither thou goest? And let the murderer know that the condign punishment is
        laid up for him twofold after his departure hence. Likewise also thou poisoner, sorcerer, robber, defrauder,
        sodomite, thief, and as many as are of that band, ye shall come at last, as your works do lead you, unto
        unquenchable fire, and utter darkness, and the pit of punishment, and eternal threatenings. Wherefore, ye men
        of Ephesus, turn yourselves, knowing this also, that kings, rulers, tyrants, boasters, and they that 
        <pb facs="JAMESApocryphalNewTestament1924_0261" />have conquered in wars, stripped of all things when they
        depart hence, do suffer pain, lodged in eternal misery. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="37">
        <p rend="indent"> And having thus said, John by the power of God healed all the diseases. </p>
        <note type="inline"><p>This sentence must be an abridgement of a much longer narration.
        The manuscrip indicates no break at this point: but we must suppose
        a not inconsiderable loss of text. For one thing, Andronicus, who is
        here an unbeliever, appears as a convert in the next few lines. Now
        he is, as we shall see later, the husband of an eminent believer, Drusiana;
        and his and her conversion will have been told at some length;
        and I do not doubt that among other things there was a discourse of
        John persuading them to live in continence.</p></note>
          <p rend="indent"><note type="inline">37 continued.</note> Now the
        brethren from Miletus said unto John: We have continued a long time at Ephesus; if it seem good to thee, let us
        go also to Smyrna; for we hear already that the mighty works of God have reached it also. And Andronicus said
        to them: Whensoever the teacher willeth, then let us go. But John said: Let us first go unto the temple of
        Artemis, for perchance there also, if we show ourselves, the servants of the Lord will be found. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="38">
        <p rend="indent"> After two days, then, was the birthday of the idol temple. John therefore, when all were clad in
        white, alone put on black raiment and went up into the temple. And they took him and essayed to kill him. But
        John said: Ye are mad to set upon me, a man that is the servant of the only God. And he gat him up upon an high
        pedestal and said unto them: </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="39">
        <p rend="indent"> Ye run hazard, men of Ephesus, of being like in character to the sea: every river that floweth in and
        every spring that runneth down, and the rains, and waves that press upon each other, and torrents full of rocks
        are made salt together by the bitter †element† <note type="inline">(MS. promise!)</note> that is therein. So ye also remaining unchanged
        unto this day toward true godliness are become corrupted by your ancient rites of worship. How many wonders and
        healings of diseases have ye seen wrought through me? And yet are ye blinded in your hearts and cannot recover
        sight. What is it, then, O men of Ephesus? I have adventured now and come up even into this your idol temple. I
        will convict you of being most godless, and dead from the understanding of mankind. Behold, I stand here: ye
        all say that ye have a goddess, even Artemis: pray then unto her that I alone may die; or else I only, if ye
        are not able to do this, will call upon mine own god, and for your unbelief I will cause every one of you to
        die. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="40">
        <p rend="indent"> But they who had beforetime made trial of him and had seen dead men raised up, cried out: Slay us not
        so, we beseech thee, John. We know that thou canst do it. And John said to them: If then ye desire not to die,
        let that which ye worship be confounded, †and wherefore it is confounded,† that ye also may 
        <pb facs="JAMESApocryphalNewTestament1924_0262"/>depart from your ancient error. For now is it time that
        either ye be converted by my God, or I myself die by your goddess; for I will pray in your presence and entreat
        my God that mercy be shown unto you. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="41">
        <p rend="indent"> And having so said he prayed thus: O God that art God above all that are called gods, that until this
        day hast been set at nought in the city of the Ephesians; that didst put into my mind to come into this place,
        whereof I never thought; that dost convict every manner of worship by turning men unto thee; at whose name
        every idol fleeth and every evil spirit and every unclean power; now also by the flight of the evil spirit here
        at thy name, even of him that deceiveth this great multitude, show thou thy mercy in this place, for they have
        been made to err. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="42">
        <p rend="indent"> And as John spake these things, immediately the altar of Artemis was parted into many pieces, and all
          the things that were dedicated in the temple fell, and †<note type="inline">[MS. that which seemed good to him]</note>† was rent asunder,
        and likewise of the images of the gods more than seven. And the half of the temple fell down, so that the
        priest was slain at one blow by the falling of the (? roof,? beam). The multitude of the Ephesians therefore
        cried out: One is the God of John, one is the God that hath pity on us, for thou only art God: now are we
        turned to thee, beholding thy marvellous works! have mercy on us, O God, according to thy will, and save us
        from our great error! And some of them, lying on their faces, made supplication, and some kneeled and besought,
        and some rent their clothes and wept, and others tried to escape. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="43">
        <p rend="indent"> But John spread forth his hands, and being uplifted in soul, said unto the Lord: Glory be to thee, my
        Jesus, the only God of truth, for that thou dost gain (receive) thy servants by divers devices. And having so
        said, he said to the people: Rise up from the floor, ye men of Ephesus, and pray to my God, and recognize the
        invisible power that cometh to manifestation, and the wonderful works which are wrought before your eyes.
        Artemis ought to have succoured herself: her servant ought to have been helped of her and not to have died.
        Where is the power of the evil spirit? where are her sacrifices? where her birthdays? where her festivals?
        where are the garlands? where is all that sorcery and the poisoning (witchcraft) that is sister thereto?
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="44">
        <p rend="indent"> But the people rising up from off the floor went hastily and cast down the rest of the idol temple,
        crying: The God of John only do we know, and him hereafter do we worship, since he hath had mercy upon us! And
        as John came down from thence, much people took hold of him, saying: Help us, O John! Assist us that do perish
        in vain! Thou seest our purpose: thou seest the multitude following thee and hanging upon thee in hope toward
        thy God. We have seen the way wherein we went astray when we lost him: we have seen our gods that were set up
        in vain: we have seen the great and shameful derision that is come to 
        <pb facs="JAMESApocryphalNewTestament1924_0263" />them: but suffer us, we pray thee, to come unto thine
        house and to be succoured without hindrance. Receive us that are in bewilderment. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="45">
        <p rend="indent"> And John said to them: Men (of Ephesus), believe that for your sakes I have continued in Ephesus, and
        have put off my journey unto Smyrna and to the rest of the cities, that there also the servants of Christ may
        turn to him. But since †I am not yet perfectly assured concerning you†, I have continued praying to my God and
        beseeching him that I should then depart from Ephesus when I have confirmed you in the faith: and whereas I see
        that this is come to pass and yet more is being fulfilled, I will not leave you until I have weaned you like
        children from the nurse’s milk, and have set you upon a firm rock. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="46">
        <p rend="indent">John therefore continued with them, receiving them in the house of Andronicus. And one of them that
        were gathered laid down the dead body of the priest of Artemis before the door (of the temple], for he was his
        kinsman, and came in quickly with the rest, saying nothing of it. John, therefore, after the discourse to the
        brethren, and the prayer and the thanksgiving (eucharist) and the laying of hands upon every one of the
        congregation, said by the spirit: There is one here who moved by faith in God hath laid down the priest of
        Artemis before the gate and is come in, and in the yearning of his soul, taking care first for himself, hath
        thought thus in himself: It is better for me to take thought for the living than for my kinsman that is dead:
        for I know that if I turn to the Lord and save mine own soul, John will not deny to raise up the dead also. And
        John arising from his place went to that into which that kinsman of the priest who had so thought was entered,
        and took him by the hand and said: Hadst thou this thought when thou camest unto me, my child? And he, taken
        with trembling and affright, said: Yes, lord, and cast himself at his feet. And John said: Our Lord is Jesus
        Christ, who will show his power in thy dead kinsman by raising him up. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="47">
        <p rend="indent">And he made the young man rise, and took his hand and said: It is no great matter for a man that is
        master of great mysteries to continue wearying himself over small things: or what great thing is it to rid men
        of diseases of the body? And yet holding the young man by the hand he said: I say unto thee, child, go and
        raise the dead thyself, saying nothing but this only: John the servant of God saith to thee, Arise. And the
        young man went to his kinsman and said this only—and much people was with him—and entered in unto John,
        bringing him alive. And John, when he saw him that was raised, said: Now that thou art raised, thou dost not
        truly live, neither art partaker or heir of the true life: wilt thou belong unto him by whose name and power
        thou wast raised? And now believe, and thou shall live unto all ages. And he forthwith believed upon the Lord
        Jesus and thereafter clave unto John. 
        <pb facs="JAMESApocryphalNewTestament1924_0264" /></p>
        <note type="inline"><p rend="indent">[Another manuscript (Q. Paris Gr. 1468, of the eleventh century)
        has another form of this story. John destroys the temple of
        Artemis, and then 'we' go t Smyrna and all the idols are broken:
        Bucolus, Polycarp, and Andronicus are left to preside over the
        district. There were there two priest of Artemis, brothers, and
        one died. The raising is told mouch as in the older text, but more
        shortly.</p>
        <p rend="indent">'We' remained four years in the region, which was wholly
        converted, and then returned to Ephesus.]</p></note>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="48">
        <p rend="indent">Now on the next day John, having seen in a dream that he must walk three miles outside the gates,
        neglected it not, but rose up early and set out upon the way, together with the brethren. </p>
        <p rend="indent">And a certain
        countryman who was admonished by his father not to take to himself the wife of a fellow labourer of his who
        threatened to kill him—this young man would not endure the admonition of his father, but kicked him and left
        him without speech (sc. dead). And John, seeing what had befallen, said unto the Lord: Lord, was it on this
        account that thou didst bid me come out hither to-day? </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="49">
        <p rend="indent"> But the young man, beholding the violence (sharpness) of death, and looking to be taken, drew out the
        sickle that was in his girdle and started to run to his own abode; and John met him and said: Stand still, thou
        most shameless devil, and tell me whither thou runnest bearing a sickle that thirsteth for blood. And the young
        man was troubled and cast the iron on the ground, and said to him: I have done a wretched and barbarous deed
        and I know it, and so I determined to do an evil yet worse and more cruel, even to die myself at once. For
        because my father was alway curbing me to sobriety, that I should live without adultery, and chastely, I could
        not endure him to reprove me, and I kicked him and slew him, and when I saw what was done, I was hasting to the
        woman for whose sake I became my father’s murderer, with intent to kill her and her husband, and myself last of
        all: for I could not bear to be seen of the husband of the woman, and undergo the judgement of death. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="50">
        <p rend="indent"> And John said to him: That I may not by going away and leaving you in danger give place to him that
        desireth to laugh and sport with thee, come thou with me and show me thy father, where he lieth. And if I raise
        him up for thee, wilt thou hereafter abstain from the woman that is become a snare to thee. And the young man
        said: If thou raisest up my father himself for me alive, and if I see him whole and †continuing† in life, I
        will hereafter abstain from her. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="51">
        <p rend="indent"> And while he was speaking, they came to the place where the old man lay dead, and many passers-by
        were standing near thereto. And John said to the youth: Thou wretched man, didst thou not spare even the old
        age of thy father? And he, weeping and tearing his hair, said that he repented thereof; and 
        <pb facs="JAMESApocryphalNewTestament1924_0265"/>
        John the servant of the Lord said: Thou didst show me I was to
        set forth for this place, thou knewest that this would come to pass,
        from whom nothing can be hid of things done in life, that givest
        me power to work every cure and healing by thy will: now
        also give me this old man alive, for thou seest that his murderer
        is become his own judge: and spare him, thou only Lord,
        that spared not his father (because he) counselled him for the best.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="52">
        <p rend="indent">And with these words he came near to the old man and
          said: My Lord will not be weak to spread out his kind pity and
          his condescending mercy even unto thee: rise up therefore and
          give glory to God for the work that is come to pass †at this
          moment†. And the old man said: I arise, Lord. And he rose
          and sat up and said: I was released from a terrible life and had
          to bear the insults of my son, dreadful and many, and his want
          of natural affection, and to what end hast thou called me back,
          O man of the living God? (And John answered him: If) thou
          art raised only for the same end, it were better thee to die; 
          but raise theyseld unto better things. And he took him and led
          him into the city, preaching unto him the grace of God, so that 
          befor he entered the gate the old man believed.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="53">
      <p rend="indent">But the young man, when he beheld the unlooked-for
        raising of his father, and the saving of himself, took a sickle and
        mutilated himself, and ran to the house wherein he had his
        adulteress, and reproacherd her, saying: For thy sake I became 
        the murderer of my father and of you two and of myself: there
        thou hast that which is alike guilty of all. For on me God hath
        had mercy, that I should know his power.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="54">
        <p rend="indent"> And he came back and told John in presence of brethren
          what he had done. But John said to him: He that put it into
          thine heart, young man, to kill  thy father and become the
          adulterer of another man's wife. the same made thee think it
          a right deed to take away also the unruly members. But thou
          shouldst have done away, not with the place of sin, but the 
          thought which through those members showed itself harmful:
          for it is not the instruments that are injurious, but the unseen
          springs by which every shameful emotion is stirred and cometh
          to light. Repent therefore, my child, of this fault, and having 
          learnt the wiles of Satan thou shalt have God to help thee in all
          the necessities of thy soul. And the young man kept silence and
          attended, having repented of his former sins, that he should
          obtain pardon from the goodness of God: and he did not separate 
          from John.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="55">
        <p  rend="indent"> When, then, these things had been done by him in the city
          of the Ephesians, they of Smyrna sent unto him saying: We
          hear that the God whom thou preachest is not envious, and hath
          charged thee not to show partiality by abiding in one place.
          Since, then, thou art a preacher of such a God, come unto Smyrna
        <pb facs="JAMESApocryphalNewTestament1924_0266"/>and unto the other cities, that we may come to know thy
        God, and having known him may have our hope in him. </p>
        <note type="inline"><p rend="indent">[Q has the above story also, and continues with an incident
        which is also quoted in a different form (and not as from these Acts) by John Cassian. Q has it thus:</p>
          <p rend="indent">Now one
        day as John was seated, a partridge flew by and came and played in the dust before him; and John looked on it
        and wondered. And a certain priest came, who was one of his hearers, and came to John and saw the partridge
        playing in the dust before him, and was offended in himself and said: Can such and so great a man take pleasure
        in a partridge playing in the dust? But John perceiving in the spirit the thought of him, said to him: It were
        better for thee also, my child, to look at a partridge playing in the dust and not to defile thyself with
        shameful and profane practices: for he who awaiteth the conversion and repentance of all men hath brought thee
        here on this account: for I have no need of a partridge playing in the dust. For the partridge is thine own
        soul. </p>
          <p rend="indent">Then the elder, hearing this and seeing that he was not hidden, but that the apostle of Christ had told
        him all that was in his heart, fell on his face on the earth and cried aloud, saying: Now know I that God
        dwelleth in thee, O blessed John! for he that tempteth thee tempteth him that cannot be tempted. And he
        entreated him to pray for him. And he instructed him and delivered him the rules (canons) and let him go to his
        house, glorifying God that is over all. </p>
        <p rend="indent">Cassian, Collation XXIV. 21, has it thus:</p>
        <p rend="indent">It is told that the most
        blessed Evangelist John, when he was gently stroking a partridge with his hands, suddenly saw one in the habit
        of a hunter coming to him. He wondered that a man of such repute and fame should demean himself to such small
        and humble amusements, and said: Art thou that John whose eminent and widespread fame hath enticed me also with
        great desire to know thee? Why then art thou taken up with such mean amusements? The blessed John said to him:
        What is that which thou carriest in thy hands? A bow, said he. And why, said he, dost thou not bear it about
        always stretched? He answered him: I must not, lest by constant bending the strength of its vigour be wrung and
        grow soft and perish, and when there is need that the arrows be shot with much strength at some beast, the
        strength being lost by excess of continual tension, a forcible blow cannot be dealt. Just so, said the blessed
        John, let not this little and brief relaxation of my mind offend thee, young man, for unless it doth sometimes
        ease and relax by some remission the force of its tension, it will grow slack through unbroken rigour and will
        not be able to obey the power of the spirit. </p>
        <p rend="indent"> The only common point of the two stories is that St. John amuses
        <pb facs="JAMESApocryphalNewTestament1924_0267"/>
        himself with a partridge, and a spectator thinks it unworthy of him.
        The two morals differ wholly. The amount of text lost here is of quite
        uncertain length, It must have told of the doings at Smyrna, and
        also, it appears, at Laodica (see title of the next section). One
        of the episodes must have been the conversion of a woman of evil life
        (see below, 'the harlot that was chaste').]</p>
          <p rend="indent">Our best manuscript prefixes a title to the next section:</p>
          <p rend="indent">From Laodicea to Ephesus the second time. </p></note>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="58">
        <p rend="indent">Now when some long time had passed, and none of the brethren had been at any time grieved by John,
        they were then grieved because he had said: Brethren, it is now time for me to go to Ephesus (for so have I
        agreed with them that dwell there) lest they become slack, now for a long time having no man to confirm them.
        But all of you must have your minds steadfast towards God, who never forsaketh us.</p>
        <p rend="indent">But when they heard this
        from him, the brethren lamented because they were to be parted from him. And John said: Even if I be parted
        from you, yet Christ is alway with you: whom if ye love purely ye will have his fellowship without reproach,
        for if he be loved, he preventeth (anticipateth) them that love him. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="59">
        <p rend="indent">> And having so said, and bidden farewell to them, and left much money with the brethren for
        distribution, he went forth unto Ephesus, while all the brethren lamented and groaned. And there accompanied
        him, of Ephesus, both Andronicus and Drusiana and Lycomedes and Cleobius and their families. And there followed
        him Aristobula also, who had heard that her husband Tertullus had died on the way, and Aristippus with
        Xenophon, and the harlot that was chaste, and many others, whom he exhorted at all times to cleave to the Lord,
        and they would no more be parted from him. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="60">
        <p rend="indent"> Now on the first day we arrived at a deserted inn, and when we were at a loss for a bed for John, we
        saw a droll matter. There was one bedstead lying somewhere there without coverings, whereon we spread the
        cloaks which we were wearing, and we prayed him to lie down upon it and rest, while the rest of us all slept
        upon the floor. But he when he lay down was troubled by the bugs, and as they continued to become yet more
        troublesome to him, when it was now about the middle of the night, in the hearing of us all he said to them: I
        say unto you, O bugs, behave yourselves, one and all, and leave your abode for this night and remain quiet in
        one place, and keep your distance from the servants of God. And as we laughed, and went on talking for some
        time, John addressed himself to sleep; and we, talking low, gave him no disturbance (or, thanks to him we were
        not disturbed). </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="61">
        <p rend="indent"> But when the day was now dawning I arose first, and with me Verus and Andronicus, and we saw at the
        door of the house which we had taken a great number of bugs standing, and while we wondered at the great sight
        of them, and all the brethren 
        <pb facs="JAMESApocryphalNewTestament1924_0268" />were roused up because of them, John continued sleeping.
        And when he was awaked we declared to him what we had seen. And he sat up on the bed and looked at them and
        said: Since ye have well behaved yourselves in hearkening to my rebuke, come unto your place. And when he had
        said this, and risen from the bed, the bugs running from the door hasted to the bed and climbed up by the legs
        thereof and disappeared into the joints. And John said again: This creature hearkened unto the voice of a man,
        and abode by itself and was quiet and trespassed not; but we which hear the voice and commandments of God
        disobey and are light-minded: and for how long? </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="62">
        <p rend="indent"> After these things we came to Ephesus: and the brethren there, who had for a long time known that
        John was coming, ran together to the house of Andronicus (where also he came to lodge), handling his feet and
        laying his hands upon their own faces and kissing them (and many rejoiced even to touch his vesture, and were
        healed by touching the clothes of the holy apostle. <note type="inline">So the Latin, which has this section; the Greek has: so
        that they even touched his garments).</note></p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="63">
        <p rend="indent"> And whereas there was great love and joy unsurpassed among the brethren, a certain one, a messenger
        of Satan, became enamoured of Drusiana, though he saw and knew that she was the wife of Andronicus. To whom
        many said: It is not possible for thee to obtain that woman, seeing that for a long time she has even separated
        herself from her husband for godliness’ sake. Art thou only ignorant that Andronicus, not being aforetime that
        which now he is, a God-fearing man, shut her up in a tomb, saying: Hither I must have thee as the wife whom I
        had before, or thou shalt die. And she chose rather to die than to do that foulness. If, then, she would not
        consent, for godliness’ sake, to cohabit with her lord and husband, but even persuaded him to be of the same
        mind as herself, will she consent to thee desiring to be her seducer? depart from this madness which hath no
        rest in thee: give up this deed which thou canst not bring to accomplishment. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="64">
        <p rend="indent"> But his familiar friends saying these things to him did not convince him, but with shamelessness he
        courted her with messages; and †when he learnt the insults and disgraces which she returned, he spent his life
        in melancholy† (or better, she, when she learnt of this disgrace and insult at his hand, spent her life in
        heaviness). And after two days Drusiana took to her bed from heaviness, and was in a fever and said: Would that
        I had not now come home to my native place, I that have become an offence to a man ignorant of godliness! for
        if it were one who was filled with the word of God, he would not have gone to such a pitch of madness. But now
        (therefore) Lord, since I am become the occasion of a blow unto a soul devoid of knowledge, set me free from
        this chain and remove me unto thee quickly. And in the presence of John, who knew nothing at all of such a
        matter, 
        <pb facs="JAMESApocryphalNewTestament1924_0269" />Drusiana departed out of life not wholly happy, yea, even
        troubled because of the spiritual hurt of the man. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="65">
        <p rend="indent"> But Andronicus, grieved with a secret grief, mourned in his soul, and wept openly, so that John
        checked him often and said to him: Upon a better hope hath Drusiana removed out of this unrighteous life. And
        Andronicus answered him: Yea, I am persuaded of it, O John, and I doubt not at all in regard of trust in my
        God: but this very thing do I hold fast, that she departed out of life pure. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="66">
        <p rend="indent"> And when she was carried forth, John took hold on Andronicus, and now that he knew the cause, he
        mourned more than Andronicus. And he kept silence, considering the provocation of the adversary, and for a
        space sat still. Then, the brethren being gathered there to hear what word he would speak of her that was
        departed, he began to say: </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="67">
        <p rend="indent"> When the pilot that voyageth, together with them that sail with him, and the ship herself, arriveth
        in a calm and stormless harbour, then let him say that he is safe. And the husbandman that hath committed the
        seed to the earth, and toiled much in the care and protection of it, let him then take rest from his labours,
        when he layeth up the seed with manifold increase in his barns. Let him that enterpriseth to run in the course,
        then exult when he beareth home the prize. Let him that inscribeth his name for the boxing, then boast himself
        when he receiveth the crowns: and so in succession is it with all contests and crafts, when they do not fail in
        the end, †but show themselves to be like that which they promised† <note type="inline">(corrupt)</note>. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="68">
        <p rend="indent"> And thus also I think is it with the faith which each one of us practiseth, that it is then discerned
        whether it be indeed true, when it continueth like itself even until the end of life. For many obstacles fall
        into the way, and prepare disturbance for the minds of men: care, children, parents, glory, poverty, flattery,
        prime of life, beauty, conceit, lust, wealth, anger, uplifting, slackness, envy, jealousy, neglect, fear,
        insolence, love, deceit, money, pretence, and other such obstacles, as many as there are in this life: as also
        the pilot sailing a prosperous course is opposed by the onset of contrary winds and a great storm and mighty
        waves out of calm, and the husbandman by untimely winter and blight and creeping things rising out of the
        earth, and they that strive in the games ‘just do not win’, and they that exercise crafts are hindered by the
        divers difficulties of them. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="69">
        <p rend="indent"> But before all things it is needful that the believer should look before at his ending and understand
        it in what manner it will come upon him, whether it will be vigorous and sober and without any obstacle, or
        disturbed and clinging to the things that are here, and bound down by desires. So is it right that a body
        should be praised as comely when it is wholly stripped, and a general as great when he hath accomplished every
        promise of the 
        <pb facs="JAMESApocryphalNewTestament1924_0270" />war, and a physician as excellent when he hath succeeded
        in every cure, and a soul as full of faith and worthy (or receptive) of God when it hath paid its promise in
        full: not that soul which began well and was dissolved into all the things of this life and fell away, nor that
        which is numb, having made an effort to attain to better things, and then is borne down to temporal things, nor
        that which hath longed after the things of time more than those of eternity, nor that which exchangeth
        &lt;enduring things for&gt; those that endure not, nor that which hath honoured the works of dishonour that
        deserve shame, nor that which taketh pledges of Satan, nor that which hath received the serpent into its own
        house, nor that which suffereth reproach for God’s sake and then is [not] ashamed, nor that which with the
        mouth saith yea, but indeed approveth not itself: but that which hath prevailed not to be made weak by foul
        pleasure, not to be overcome by light-mindedness, not to be caught by the bait of love of money, not to be
        betrayed by vigour of body or wrath. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="70">
        <p rend="indent">And as John was discoursing yet further unto the brethren. that they should despise temporal things
        in respect of the eternal, he that was enamoured of Drusiana, being inflamed with an horrible lust and
        possession of the many-shaped Satan, bribed the steward of Andronicus who was a lover of money with a great
        sum: and he opened the tomb and gave him opportunity to wreak the forbidden thing upon the dead body. Not
        having succeeded with her when alive, he was still importunate after her death to her body, and said: If thou
        wouldst not have to do with me while thou livedst, I will outrage thy corpse now thou art dead. With this
        design, and having managed for himself the wicked act by means of the abominable steward, he rushed with him to
        the sepulchre; they opened the door and began to strip the grave-clothes from the corpse, saying: What art thou
        profited, poor Drusiana? couldest thou not have done this in life, which perchance would not have grieved thee,
        hadst thou done it willingly? </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="71">
        <p rend="indent"> And as these men were speaking thus, and only the accustomed shift now remained on her body, a
        strange spectacle was seen, such as they deserve to suffer who do such deeds. A serpent appeared from some
        quarter and dealt the steward a single bite and slew him: but the young man it did not strike; but coiled about
        his feet, hissing terribly, and when he fell mounted on his body and sat upon him. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="72">
        <p rend="indent">Now on the next day John came, accompanied by Andronicus and the brethren, to the sepulchre at dawn,
        it being now the third day from Drusiana’s death, that we might break bread there. And first, when they set
        out, the keys were sought for and could not be found; but John said to Andronicus: It is quite right that they
        should be lost, for Drusiana is not in the sepulchre; nevertheless, let us go, that thou mayest not be 
        <pb facs="JAMESApocryphalNewTestament1924_0271" />neglectful, and the doors shall be opened of themselves,
        even as the Lord hath done for us many such things. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="73">
        <p rend="indent">And when we were at the place, at the commandment of the master, the doors were opened, and we saw by
        the tomb of Drusiana a beautiful youth, smiling: and John, when he saw him, cried out and said: Art thou come
        before us hither too, beautiful one? and for what cause? And we heard a voice saying to him: For Drusiana’s
        sake, whom thou art to raise up—for I was within a little of finding her &lt;shamed&gt;—and for his sake that
        lieth dead beside her tomb. And when the beautiful one had said this unto John he went up into the heavens in
        the sight of us all. And John, turning to the other side of the sepulchre, saw a young man—even Callimachus,
        one of the chief of the Ephesians—and a huge serpent sleeping upon him, and the steward of Andronicus,
        Fortunatus by name, lying dead. And at the sight of the two he stood perplexed, saying to the brethren: What
        meaneth such a sight? or wherefore hath not the Lord declared unto me what was done here, he who hath never
        neglected me? </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="74">
        <p rend="indent"> And Andronicus seeing those corpses, leapt up and went to Drusiana’s tomb, and seeing her lying in
        her shift only, said to John: I understand what has happened, thou blessed servant of God, John. This
        Callimachus was enamoured of my sister; and because he never won her, though he often assayed it, he hath
        bribed this mine accursed steward with a great sum, perchance designing, as now we may see, to fulfil by his
        means the tragedy of his conspiracy, for indeed Callimachus avowed this to many, saying: If she will not
        consent to me when living, she shall be outraged when dead. And it may be, master, that the beautiful one knew
        it and suffered not her body to be insulted, and therefore have these died who made that attempt. And can it be
        that the voice that said unto thee, ‘Raise up Drusiana’, foreshowed this? because she departed out of this life
        in sorrow of mind. But I believe him that said that this is one of the men that have gone astray; for thou wast
        bidden to raise him up: for as to the other, I know that he is unworthy of salvation. But this one thing I beg
        of thee: raise up Callimachus first, and he will confess to us what is come about. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="75">
        <p rend="indent"> And John, looking upon the body, said to the venomous beast: Get thee away from him that is to be a
        servant of Jesus Christ; and stood up and prayed over him thus: O God whose name is glorified by us, as of
        right: O God who subduest every injurious force: O God whose will is accomplished, who alway hearest us: now
        also let thy gift be accomplished in this young man; and if there be any dispensation to be wrought through
        him, manifest it unto us when he is raised up. And straightway the young man rose up, and for a whole hour kept
        silence. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="76">
        <p rend="indent">But when he came to his right senses, John asked of him 
        <pb facs="JAMESApocryphalNewTestament1924_0272" />about his entry into the sepulchre, what it meant, and
        learning from him that which Andronicus had told him, namely, that he was enamoured of Drusiana, John inquired
        of him again if he had fulfilled his foul intent, to insult a body full of holiness. And he answered him: How
        could I accomplish it when this fearful beast struck down Fortunatus at a blow in my sight: and rightly, since
        he encouraged my frenzy, when I was already cured of that unreasonable and horrible madness: but me it stopped
        with affright, and brought me to that plight in which ye saw me before I arose. And another thing yet more
        wondrous I will tell thee, which yet went nigh to slay and was within a little of making me a corpse. When my
        soul was stirred up with folly and the uncontrollable malady was troubling me, and I had now torn away the
        grave-clothes in which she was clad, and I had then come out of the grave and laid them as thou seest, I went
        again to my unholy work: and I saw a beautiful youth covering her with his mantle, and from his eyes sparks of
        light came forth unto her eyes; and he uttered words to me, saying: Callimachus, die that thou mayest live. Now
        who he was I knew not, O servant of God; but that now thou hast appeared here, I recognize that he was an angel
        of God, that I know well; and this I know of a truth that it is a true God that is proclaimed by thee, and of
        it I am persuaded. But I beseech thee, be not slack to deliver me from this calamity and this fearful crime,
        and to present me unto thy God as a man deceived with a shameful and foul deceit. Beseeching help therefore of
        thee, I take hold on thy feet. I would become one of them that hope in Christ, that the voice may prove true
        which said to me, ‘Die that thou mayest live’: and that voice hath also fulfilled its effect, for he is dead,
        that faithless, disorderly, godless one, and I have been raised by thee, I who will be faithful, God-fearing,
        knowing the truth, which I entreat thee may be shown me by thee. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="77">
        <p rend="indent">And John, filled with great gladness and perceiving the whole spectacle of the salvation of man,
        said: What thy power is, Lord Jesu Christ, I know not, bewildered as I am at thy much compassion and boundless
        long-suffering. O what a greatness that came down into bondage! O unspeakable liberty brought into slavery by
        us! O incomprehensible glory that is come unto us! thou that hast kept the dead tabernacle safe from insult;
        that hast redeemed the man that stained himself with blood and chastened the soul of him that would defile the
        corruptible body; Father that hast had pity and compassion on the man that cared not for thee; We glorify thee,
        and praise and bless and thank thy great goodness and long-suffering, O holy Jesu, for thou only art God, and
        none else: whose is the might that cannot be conspired against, now and world without end. Amen. 
        <pb facs="JAMESApocryphalNewTestament1924_0273" /></p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="78">
        <p rend="indent"> And when he had said this John took Callimachus and saluted (kissed) him, saying: Glory be to our
        God, my child, who hath had mercy on thee, and made me worthy to glorify his power, and thee also by a good
        course to depart from that thine abominable madness and drunkenness, and hath called thee unto his own rest and
        unto renewing of life. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="79">
        <p rend="indent">But Andronicus, beholding the dead Callimachus raised, besought John, with the brethren, to raise up
        Drusiana also, saying: O John, let Drusiana arise and spend happily that short space (of life) which she gave
        up through grief about Callimachus, when she thought she had become a stumblingblock to him: and when the Lord
        will, he shall take her again to himself. And John without delay went unto her tomb and took her hand and said:
        Upon thee that art the only God do I call, the more than great, the unutterable, the incomprehensible: unto
        whom every power of principalities is subjected: unto whom all authority boweth: before whom all pride falleth
        down and keepeth silence: whom devils hearing of tremble: whom all creation perceiving keepeth its bounds. Let
        thy name be glorified by us, and raise up Drusiana, that Callimachus may yet more be confirmed unto thee who
        dispensest that which unto men is without a way and impossible, but to thee only possible, even salvation and
        resurrection: and that Drusiana may now come forth in peace, having about her not any the least hindrance —now
        that the young man is turned unto thee—in her course toward thee. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="80">
        <p rend="indent">And after these words John said unto Drusiana: Drusiana, arise. And she arose and came out of the
        tomb; and when she saw herself in her shift only, she was perplexed at the thing, and learned the whole
        accurately from Andronicus, the while John lay upon his face, and Callimachus with voice and tears glorified
        God, and she also rejoiced, glorifying him in like manner. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="81">
        <p rend="indent">And when she had clothed herself, she turned and
        saw Fortunatus lying, and said unto John: Father, let this man also rise, even if he did assay to become my
        betrayer. But Callimachus, when he heard her say that, said: Do not, I beseech thee, Drusiana, for the voice
        which I heard took no thought of him, but declared concerning thee only, and I saw and believed: for if he had
        been good, perchance God would have had mercy on him also and would have raised him by means of the blessed
        John: the knew† therefore that the man was come to a bad end <note type="inline">[Lat. he judged him worthy to die whom he did not
        declare worthy to rise again]</note>. And John said to him: We have not learned, my child, to render evil for evil:
        for God, though we have done much ill and no good toward him, hath not given retribution unto us, but
        repentance, and though we were ignorant of his name he did not neglect us but had mercy on us, and when we
        blasphemed him, he did not punish but pitied us,
        <pb facs="JAMESApocryphalNewTestament1924_0274"/>
        and when we disbelived him he bore us no grudge, and when
        we persecuted his brethren he did not recompense us evil but
        put into our minds repentance and abstinence from evil, and
        exhorted us to come unto him, as he hath thee also, my son
        Callimachus, and not remembering thy former evil hath made
        thee his servant, waiting upon his mercy. Wherefore if thou
        allowest not me to raise up Fortunatus, it is for Drusiana to do so.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="82">
        <p  rend="indent">And she, denying not, went with rejoicing of spirit and
          soul unto the body of Fortunatus and said: Jesu Christ, God
          of the ages, God of truth, that hast granted me to see wonders
          and signs, and given to me to become partaker of thy name;
          that didst breathe thyself into me with thy many-shaped countenance,
          and hadst mercy on me in many ways; that didst protect 
          me by thy great goodness when I was oppressed by Andronicus
          that was of old my husband; that didst give me thy servant
          Andronicus to be my brother; that hast kept me thine handmaid
          pure unto this day; that didst raise me up by thy servant John,
          and when I was raised didst show me him that was made to
          stumble free from stumbling; that hast given me perfect rest in
          thee, and lightened me of the secret madness; whom I have
          loved and affectioned; I pray thee, O Christ, refuse not thy
          Drusiana that asketh thee to raise up Fortunatus, even though
          he assayed to become my betrayer.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="83">
        <p rend="indent">And taking the hand of the dead man she said: Rise up,
        Fortunatus, in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ. And Fortunatus
        arose, and when he saw John in the sepulchre, and Andronicus,
        and Drusiana raised from the dead, and Callimachus
        a believer, and the rest of the brethren glorifying God, he said:
        O, to what have the powers of these clever men attained! I did
        not want to be raised, but would rather die, so as not to see
        them. And with these words he fled and went out of the sepulchre.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="84">
        <p rend="indent">And John, when he saw the unchanged mind (soul) of
          Fortunatus, said: O nature that is not changed for the better!
          O fountain of the soul that abideth in foulness! O essence of
          corruption full of darkness! O death exulting in them that are
          thine! O fruitless tree full of fire! O tree that bearest coals
          for fruit! O matter that dwellest with the madness of matter
          (al. O wood of trees full of unwholesome shoots) and neighbor
          of unbelief! Thou hast proved who thou art, and thou art always
          convicted, with thy children. And thou knowest not how to 
          praise better things: for thou hast them not. Therefore,
          such as is thy way (?fruit), such also is thy root and thy nature.
          Be thou destroyed from among them that trust in the Lord:
          from their thoughts. from their mind, from their souls, from
          their bodies. from their acts. their life, their conversation, from
          their †business†, their occupations, their counsel, from the resurrection
          unto (or rest in) God, from their sweet savour wherein
          thou wilt &lt;not&gt; share, from their faith, their prayers, from the
        <pb facs="JAMESApocryphalNewTestament1924_0275"/>holy bath, from the eucharist, from the food of the
        flesh, from drink, from clothing, from love, from care, from abstinence, from righteousness: from all these,
        thou most unholy Satan, enemy of God, shall Jesus Christ our God and &lt;the judge&gt; of all that are like
        thee and have thy character, make thee to perish. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="85">
        <p rend="indent">And having thus said, John prayed, and took bread and bare it into the sepulchre to break it; and
        said: We glorify thy name, which converteth us from error and ruthless deceit: we glorify thee who hast shown
        before our eyes that which we have seen: we bear witness to thy loving-kindness which appeareth in divers ways:
        we praise thy merciful name, O Lord (we thank thee), who hast convicted them that are convicted of thee: we
        give thanks to thee, O Lord Jesu Christ, that we are persuaded of thy &lt;grace&gt; which is unchanging: we
        give thanks to thee who hadst need of our nature that should be saved: we give thanks to thee that hast given
        us this sure &lt;faith&gt;, for thou art &lt;God&gt; alone, both now and ever. We thy servants give thee
        thanks, O holy one, who are assembled with &lt;good&gt; intent and are gathered out of the world (or risen from
        death). </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="86">
        <p rend="indent">And having so prayed and given glory to God, he went out of the sepulchre after imparting unto all
        the brethren of the eucharist of the Lord. And when he was come unto Andronicus’ house he said to the brethren:
        Brethren, a spirit within me hath divined that Fortunatus is about to die of blackness (poisoning of the blood)
        from the bite of the serpent; but let some one go quickly and learn if it is so indeed. And one of the young
        men ran and found him dead and the blackness spreading over him, and it had reached his heart: and came and
        told John that he had been dead three hours. And John said: Thou hast thy child, O devil.</p>
        <note type="inline"><p  rend="indent">'John therefore was
        with the brethren rejoicing in the Lord.' This sentence is in the best manuscript. In Bonnet’s edition it
        introduces the last section of the Acts, which follows immediately in the manuscript. It may belong to either
        episode. The Latin has: And that day he spent joyfully with the brethren. </p>
          <p rend="indent">There cannot be much of a gap between
        this and the next section, which is perhaps the most interesting in the Acts. </p>
          <p  rend="indent">The greater part of this episode
        is preserved only in one very corrupt fourteenth-century manuscript at Vienna. Two important passages (93-5
        (part) and 97-8 (part)) were read at the Second Nicene Council and are preserved in the Acts thereof: a few
        lines of the Hymn are also cited in Latin by Augustine (Ep. 237 (253) to Ceretius): he found it current
        separately among the Priscillianists. The whole discourse is the best popular exposition we have of the Docetic
        view of our Lord’s person. </p></note>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="87">
        <p rend="indent">Those that were present inquired the cause, and were especially perplexed, because Drusiana had said:
        the Lord 
        <pb facs="JAMESApocryphalNewTestament1924_0276" />appeared unto me in the tomb in the likeness of John, and
        in that of a youth. Forasmuch, therefore, as they were perplexed and were, in a manner, not yet stablished in
        the faith, so as to endure it steadfastly, John said (or John bearing it patiently, said): </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="88">
        <p rend="indent"> Men and brethren, ye have suffered nothing strange or incredible as concerning your perception of the
        &lt;Lord&gt;, inasmuch as we also, whom he chose for himself to be apostles, were tried in many ways: I,
        indeed, am neither able to set forth unto you nor to write the things which I both saw and heard: and now is it
        needful that I should fit them for your hearing; and according as each of you is able to contain it I will
        impart unto you those things whereof ye are able to become hearers, that ye may see the glory that is about
        him, which was and is, both now and for ever. </p>
        <p rend="indent">For when he had chosen Peter and Andrew, which were brethren, he
        cometh unto me and James my brother, saying: I have need of you, come unto me. And my brother hearing that,
        said: John, what would this child have that is upon the sea-shore and called us? And I said: What child? And he
        said to me again: That which beckoneth to us. And I answered: Because of our long watch we have kept at sea,
        thou seest not aright, my brother James; but seest thou not the man that standeth there, comely and fair and of
        a cheerful countenance? But he said to me: Him I see not, brother; but let us go forth and we shall see what he
        would have. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="89">
        <p rend="indent"> And so when we had brought the ship to land, we saw him also helping along with us to settle the
        ship: and when we departed from that place, being minded to follow him, again he was seen of me as having &lt;a
        head&gt; rather bald, but the beard thick and flowing, but of James as a youth whose beard was newly come. We
        were therefore perplexed, both of us, as to what that which we had seen should mean. And after that, as we
        followed him, both of us were by little and little &lt;yet more&gt; perplexed as we considered the matter. Yet
        unto me there then appeared this yet more wonderful thing: for I would try to see him privily, and I never at
        any time saw his eyes closing (winking), but only open. And oft-times he would appear to me as a small man and
        uncomely, and †then again† as one reaching unto heaven. Also there was in him another marvel: when I sat at
        meat he would take me upon his own breast; and sometimes his breast was felt of me to be smooth and tender, and
        sometimes hard like unto stones, so that I was perplexed in myself and said: Wherefore is this so unto me? And
        as I considered this, he... </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="90">
        <p rend="indent"> And at another time he taketh with him me and James and Peter unto the mountain where he was wont to
        pray, and we saw in him a light such as it is not possible for a man that useth corruptible (mortal) speech to
        describe what it was like. 
        <pb facs="JAMESApocryphalNewTestament1924_0277"/>
          Again in like manner he bringeth us three up into the mountain,
          saying: Come ye with me. And we went again: and we saw
          him at a distance praying. I, therefore, because he loved me,
          drew nigh unto him softly, as though he could not see me, and
          stood looking upon his hinder parts: and I saw that he was not
          in any wise clad with garments, but was seen of us naked, and
          not in any wise a man, and that his feet were whiter than
          any snow, so that the earth there was lighted up by his feet,
          and that his head touched the heaven: so that I was afraid
          and cried out, and he, turning about, appeared as a man of small
          stature, and caught hold on my beard and pulled it and said
          to me: John, be not faithless but believing, and not curious.
          And I said unto him: But what have I done, Lord? And I say
          unto you, brethren, I suffered so great pain in that place where
          he took hold of my beard for thirty days, that I said to him:
          Lord, if thy twitch when thou wast in sport hath given me
          so great pain, what were it if thou had given me a buffet?
          And he said unto me: Let it be thine henceforth not to tempt
          him that cannot be tempted.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="91">
        <p rend="indent">But Peter and James were wroth because I spake with
          the Lord, and beckoned unto me that I should come unto them
          and leave the Lord alone. And I went, and they both said
          unto me: He (the old man) that was speaking with the Lord
          upon the top of the mount, who was he? for we heard both of
          them speaking. And I, havng in mind his great grace, and his 
          unity which hath many faces, and his wisdom which without ceasing
          looketh upon us, said: That shall ye learn if ye inquire of him.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="92">
        <p rend="indent">And, once when all we his disciples were at Gennesaret
          sleeping in one house, I alone havng wrapped myself in my
          mantle (or watched from beneath my mantle) what
          he should do: and first I heard him say: John, go thou to sleep.
          And I thereon feigning to sleep saw another like unto him
          [sleeping], whom also I heard say unto my Lord: Jesus, they
          whom thou hast chosen believe not yet on thee (or do they not
          yet, &amp;c.?). And my Lord said unto him: Thou sayest well:
          for they are men.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="93">
        <p rend="indent">Another glory also I will tell you, brethren: Sometimes
          when I would lay hold on him, I met with a material and solid
          body, and at other times, again, when I felt him, the substance
          was immaterial and as if it existed not at all. And if at any
          time he were bidden by some one of the Pharisees and went
          to the bidding, we went with him, and there was set before each
          one of us a loaf by them that had bidden us, and with us he
          also received one; and his own he would bless and part it among
          us: and of that little one every one was filled, and out own loaves
          were saved whole, so that they which bade him were amazed.
          And oftentimes when I walked with him, I desired to see the
          print of his foot, whether it appeared on the earth; for I saw
          <pb facs="JAMESApocryphalNewTestament1924_0278"/>him as it were lifting himself up from the earth: and I
        never saw it. And these things I speak unto you, brethren, for the encouragement of your faith toward him; for
        we must at the present keep silence concerning his mighty and wonderful works, inasmuch as they are unspeakable
        and, it may be, cannot at all be either uttered or heard. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="94">
        <p rend="indent"> Now before he was taken by the lawless Jews, †who also were governed by (had their law from) the
        lawless serpent,† he gathered all of us together and said: Before I am delivered up unto them let us sing an
        hymn to the Father, and so go forth to that which lieth before us. He bade us therefore make as it were a ring,
        holding one another’s hands, and himself standing in the midst he said: Answer Amen unto me. He began, then, to
        sing an hymn and to say:</p>
        <p rend="indent">Glory be to thee, Father. </p>
        <p rend="indent">And we, going about in a ring, answered him: Amen. </p>
        <p rend="indent">Glory be to thee, Word: Glory be to thee, Grace. Amen.</p>
        <p rend="indent">Glory be to thee, Spirit: Glory be to thee, Holy One:</p>
        <p rend="indent">Glory be to thy glory. Amen.</p>
        <p rend="indent">We praise thee, O Father; we give thanks to thee, O Light, wherein darkness dwelleth not. Amen. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="95">
        <p rend="indent"> Now whereas (or wherefore) we give thanks, I say:</p>
        <p rend="indent">I would be saved, and I would save. Amen. </p>
        <p rend="indent">I would be loosed, and I would loose. Amen. </p>
        <p rend="indent">I would be wounded, and I would wound. Amen.</p>
        <p rend="indent">I would be born, and I would bear. Amen. </p>
        <p rend="indent">I would eat, and I would be eaten. Amen.</p>
        <p rend="indent">I would hear, and I would be heard. Amen. </p>
        <p rend="indent">I would be thought, being wholly thought. Amen. </p>
        <p rend="indent">I would be washed, and I would wash. Amen.</p>
        <p rend="indent">Grace danceth. I would pipe; dance ye all. Amen. </p>
        <p rend="indent">I would mourn: lament ye all. Amen. </p>
        <p rend="indent">The number Eight <note type="inline">(lit. one ogdoad)</note> singeth praise with us. Amen.</p>
        <p rend="indent">The number Twelve danceth on high. Amen.</p>
        <p rend="indent">†The Whole on high hath part in our dancing. Amen. </p>
        <p rend="indent">Whoso danceth not, knoweth not what cometh to pass. Amen.</p>
        <p rend="indent">I would flee, and I would stay. Amen. </p>
        <p rend="indent">I would adorn, and I would be adorned. Amen. </p>
        <p rend="indent">I would be united, and I would unite. Amen. </p>
        <p rend="indent">A house I have not, and I have houses. Amen. </p>
        <p rend="indent">A place I have not, and I have places. Amen. </p>
        <p rend="indent">A temple I have not, and I have temples. Amen. </p>
        <p rend="indent">A lamp am I to thee that beholdest me. Amen. </p>
        <p rend="indent">A mirror am I to thee that perceivest me. Amen. </p>
        <p rend="indent">A door am I to thee that knockest at me. Amen. </p>
        <p rend="indent">A way am I to thee a wayfarer. &lt;Amen&gt;. 
        <pb facs="JAMESApocryphalNewTestament1924_0279" /></p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="96">
        <p rend="indent">Now answer thou (or as thou respondest) unto my dancing. Behold thyself in me who speak, and seeing
        what I do, keep silence about my mysteries. </p>
        <p rend="indent">Thou that dancest, perceive what I do, for thine is this passion of
        the manhood, which I am about to suffer. For thou couldest not at all have understood what thou sufferest if I
        had not been sent unto thee, as the word of the Father. Thou that sawest what I suffer sawest me as suffering,
        and seeing it thou didst not abide but wert wholly moved, †moved to make wise†. Thou hast me as a bed, rest
        upon me. Who I am, thou shalt know when I depart. What now I am seen to be, that I am not. Thou shalt see when
        thou comest. If thou hadst known how to suffer, thou wouldest have been able not to suffer. Learn thou to
        suffer, and thou shalt be able not to suffer. What thou knowest not, I myself will teach thee. Thy God am I,
        not the God of the traitor. I would keep tune with holy souls. In me know thou the word of wisdom. Again with
        me say thou: Glory be to thee, Father; glory to thee, Word; glory to thee, Holy Ghost. †And if thou wouldst
        know concerning me, what I was, know that† with a word did I deceive all things and I was no whit deceived. I
        have leaped: but do thou understand the whole and having understood it, say: Glory be to thee, Father. Amen..
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="97">
        <p rend="indent"> Thus, my beloved, having danced with us the Lord went forth. And we as men gone astray or dazed with
        sleep fled this way and that. I, then, when I saw him suffer, did not even abide by his suffering, but fled
        unto the Mount of Olives, weeping at that which had befallen. And when he was crucified on the Friday, at the
        sixth hour of the day, darkness came upon all the earth. And my Lord standing in the midst of the cave and
        enlightening it, said: John, unto the multitude below in Jerusalem i am being crucified and pierced with lances
        and reeds, and gall and vinegar is given me to drink. But unto thee I speak, and what I speak hear thou. I put
        it into thy mind to come up into this mountain, that thou mightest hear those things which it behoveth a
        disciple to learn from his teacher and a man from his God. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="98">
        <p rend="indent">And having thus spoken, he showed me a cross of light fixed (set up), and about the cross a great
          multitude, †not having one form: and in it (the cross) was one form and one likeness† <note type="inline">[so the MS.; I would
        read: and therein was one form and one likeness: and in the cross another multitude, not having one form]</note>. And
        the Lord himself I beheld above the cross, not having any shape, but only a voice: and a voice not such as was
        familiar to us, but one sweet and kind and truly of God, saying unto me: John, it is needful that one should
        hear these things from me, for I have need of one that will hear. This cross of light is sometimes called the
        (or a) word by me for your 
        <pb facs="JAMESApocryphalNewTestament1924_0280"/>
        sakes, sometimes mind, sometimes Jesus, sometimes Christ, sometimes 
        door, sometimes a way, sometimes bread, sometimes 
        seed, sometimes resurrection, sometimes Son, sometimes Father,
        sometimes Spirit, sometimes life, sometimes truth, sometimes 
        faith, sometimes grace. And by these names it is called as 
        toward men: but that which it is in truth, as conceived of in 
        itself and as spoken of unto you <note type="inline">(MS. us)</note>, it is the marking-off
        of all things, and the firm uplifting of things fixed out of things
        unstable, and the harmony of wisdom, and indeed wisdom in 
        harmony <note type="inline">[this last clause in the MS. is joined to the next: ‘and
        being wisdom in harmony’]</note>. There are &lt;places&gt; of the right
        hand and the left, powers also, authorities, lordships and demons, 
        workings, threatenings, wraths, devils, Satan, and the lower 
        root whence the nature of the things that come into being proceeded.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="99">
        <p rend="indent">This cross, then, is that which fixed all things apart (al.
        joined all things unto itself) by the (or a) word, and separate off
        the things that are from those that are below (lit. the things
        from birth and below it), and then also, being one, streamed 
        forth into all things (or, made all flow forth. <note type="inline">I suggested: compacted 
        all into &lt;one&lt;</note>). But this is not the cross of wood which
        thou wilt see when thou goest down hence: neither am I he 
        that is on the cross, whom now thou seest not, but only hearest
        his (or a) voice. I was reckoned to be that which I am not, not 
        being what I was unto many others: but they will call me 
        (say of me) something else which is vile and not worthy of me. 
        As, then, the place of rest is neither seen nor spoken of, much 
        more shall I, the Lord thereof, be neither seen &lt;nor spoken of&gt;.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="100">
        <p rend="indent">Now the multitude of one aspect (al. &lt;not&gt; of one aspect) 
        that is about the cross is the lower nature: and they whom 
        thou seest in the cross, if they have not one form, it is because 
        not yet hath every member of him that came down been comprehended. 
        But when the human nature (or the upper nature)
        is taken up, and the race which draweth near unto me and
        obeyeth my voice, he that now heareth me shall be united
        therewith, and shall no more be that which now he is, but above
        them, as I also now am. For so long as thou callest not thyself 
        mine, I am not that which I am (or was): but if thou hear me, 
        thou, hearing, shalt be as I am, and I shall be that which I was,
        when I &lt;have&gt; thee as I am with myself. For from me thou 
        art that (which I am). Care not therefore for the many, and
        them that are outside the mystery despise; for know thou
        that I am wholly with the Father, and the Father with me.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="101">
        <p rend="indent">Nothing, therefore, of the things which they will say of 
          me have I suffered: nay, that suffering also which I showed 
          unto thee and the rest in the dance, I will that it be called a 
          mystery. For what thou art, thou seest, for I showed it thee;
          but what I am I alone know, and no man else. Suffer me then
          <pb facs="JAMESApocryphalNewTestament1924_0281"/>
          to keep that which is mine, and that which is thine behold thou
          through me, and behold me in truth, that I am, not what I said, 
          but what thou art able to know, because thou art akin thereto. 
          Thou hearest that I suffered, yet did I not suffer; that I suffered 
          not, yet did I suffer; that I was pierced, yet I was not smitten; 
          hanged, and I was not hanged; that blood flowed from me, 
          and it flowed not; and, in a word, what they say of me, that
          befell me not, but what they say not, that did I suffer. Now 
          what those things are I signify unto thee, for I know that 
          thou wilt understand. Perceive thou therefore in me the 
          praising (al . slaying al . rest) of the (or a) Word (Logos), the piercing 
          of the Word, the blood of the Word, the wound of the Word, 
          the hanging up of the Word, the suffering of the Word, the nailing 
          (fixing) of the Word, the death of the Word. And so speak I, 
          separating off the manhood. Perceive thou therefore in the 
          first place of the Word; then shalt thou perceive the Lord, and 
          in the third place the man, and what he hath suffered.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="102">
        <p rend="indent"> When he had spoken unto me these things, and others
        which I know not how to say as he would have me, he was taken
        up, no one of the multitudes having beheld him. And when
        I went down I laughed them all to scorn, inasmuch as he had
        told me the things which they have said concerning him; holding
        fast this one thing in myself, that the Lord contrived all
        things symbolically and by a dispensation toward men, for their
        conversion and salvation.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="103">
        <p rend="indent">Having therefore beheld, brethren, the grace of the Lord 
          and his kindly affection toward us, let us worship him as those
          unto whom he hath shown mercy, not with our fingers, nor 
          our mouth, nor our tongue, nor with any part whatsoever 
          of our body, but with the disposition of our soul—even him who 
          became a man apart from this body; and let us watch because 
          (or we shall find that) now also he keepeth ward over prisons 
          for our sake, and over tombs, in bonds and dungeons, in reproaches
          and insults, by sea and on dry land, in scourgings, 
          condemnations, conspiracies, frauds, punishments, and in a word,
          he is with all of us, and himself suffereth with us when we suffer, 
          brethren. When he is called upon by each one of us, he endureth
          not to shut his ears to us, but as being everywhere he hearkeneth 
          to all of us; and now both to me and to Drusiana,—forasmuch as 
          he is the God of them that are shut up—bringing us help by
          his own compassion.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="104">
        <p rend="indent">Be ye also persuaded, therefore, beloved, that it is not a
          man whom I preach unto you to worship, but God unchangeable, 
          God invincible, God higher than all authority and all power, 
          and elder and mightier than all angels and creatures that are 
          named, and all aeons. If then ye abide in him, and are builded 
          up in him, ye shall possess your soul indestructible.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="105">
        <p rend="indent">And when he had delivered these things unto the brethren,
        <pb facs="JAMESApocryphalNewTestament1924_0282"/>
        John departed, with Andronicus, to walk. And Drusiana also 
        followed afar off with all the brethren, that they might behold 
        the acts that were done by him, and hear his speech at all times 
        in the Lord.</p>
        <note type="inline"><p>The remaining episode which is extant in the Greek is the conclusion
        of the book, the Death or Assumption of John. Before it must be
        placed the stories which we have only in the Latin (of ‘Abdias’ and 
        another text by 'Mellitus’, i. e. Melito), and the two or three isolated 
        fragments.</p></note>
      </div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="XIV">
        <p rend="indent">Now on the next (or another) day Craton, a 
          philosopher, had proclaimed in the market-place that he would 
          give an example of the contempt of riches: and the spectacle 
          was after this manner. He had persuaded two young men, the 
          richest of the city, who were brothers, to spend their whole 
          inheritance and buy each of them a jewel, and these they brake
          in pieces publicly in the sight of the people. And while they were
          doing this, it happened by chance that the apostle passed by. 
          And calling Craton the philosopher to him, he said: That is 
          a foolish despising of the world which is praised by the mouths 
          of men, but long ago condemned by the judgement of God. For
          as that is a vain medicine whereby the disease is not extirpated, 
          so is it a vain teaching by which the faults of souls and of conduct
          are not cured. But indeed my master taught a youth who desired 
          to attain to eternal life, in these words; saying that if he would
          be perfect, he should sell all his goods and give to the poor, and 
          so doing he would gain treasure in heaven and find the life that
          has no ending. And Craton said to him: Here the fruit of 
          covetousness is set forth in the midst of men, and hath been 
          broken to pieces. But if God is indeed thy master and willeth
          this to be, that the sum of the price of these jewels should be given
          to the poor, cause thou the gems to be restored whole, that what
          I have done for the praise of men, thou mayest do for the glory 
          of him whom thou callest thy master. Then the blessed John
          gathered together the fragments of the gems, and holding them
          in his hands, lifted up his eyes to heaven and said: Lord Jesu 
          Christ, unto whom nothing is impossible: who when the world 
          was broken by the tree of concupiscence, didst restore it again
          in thy faithfulness by the tree of the cross: who didst give to one
          born blind the eyes which nature had denied him, who didst 
          recall Lazarus, dead and buried, after the fourth day unto the 
          light; and has subjected all diseases and all sicknesses unto the
          word of thy power: so also now do with these precious stones 
          which these, not knowing the fruits of almsgiving, have broken 
          in pieces for the praise of men: recover thou them, Lord, now by 
          the hands of thine angels, that by their value the work of mercy 
          may be fulfilled, and make these men believe in thee the unbegotten
          Father through thine only-begotten Son Jesus Christ 
          our Lord, with the Holy Ghost the illuminator and sanctifier of
          <pb facs="JAMESApocryphalNewTestament1924_0283"/>
          the whole Church, world without end. And when the faithful
          who were with the apostle had answered and said Amen, the 
          fragments of the gems were forthwith so joined in one that no
          mark at all that they had been broken remained in them . And 
          Craton the philosopher, with his disciples, seeing this, fell at the 
          feet of the apostle and believed thenceforth (or immediately) 
          and was baptized, with them all, and began himself publicly to 
          preach the faith of our Lord Jesus Christ.</p>
      </div>
       <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="XV">
        <p rend="indent">Those two brothers, therefore, of whom we spake, sold
          the gems which they had bought by the sale of their inheritance, 
          and gave the price to the poor; and thereafter a very great 
          multitude of believers began to be joined to the apostle .</p>
        <p rend="indent">And when all this was done, it happened that after the same 
          example, two honourable men of the city of the Ephesians <ref target="n1.1"><hi rend="superscript">1</hi></ref>
        <note xml:id="n1.1" type="foot">Rather, as Pseudo-Mellitus has it, the same two brothers .</note> sold 
          all their goods and distributed them to the needy, and followed 
          the apostle as he went through the cities preaching the word of 
          God But it came to pass, when they entered the city of Pergamum, 
          that they saw their servants walking abroad arrayed in 
          silken raiment and shining with the glory of this world: whence
          it happened that they were pierced with the arrow of the devil 
          and became sad, seeing themselves poor and clad with a single 
          cloak while their own servants were powerful and prosperous 
          But the apostle of Christ, perceiving these wiles of the devil, 
          said: I see that ye have changed your minds and your countenances 
          on this account, that, obeying the teaching of my Lord 
          Jesus Christ, ye have given all ye had to the poor Now, if ye 
          desire to recover that which ye formerly possessed of gold, silver, 
          and precious stones, bring me some straight rods, each of you 
          a bundle And when they had done so, he called upon the name 
          of the Lord Jesus Christ, and they were turned into gold And 
          the apostle said to them: Bring me small stones from the seashore
          And when they had done this also, he called upon the 
          majesty of the Lord, and all the pebbles were turned into gems 
          Then the blessed John turned to those men and said to them: 
          Go about to the goldsmiths and jewellers for seven days, and
          when ye have proved that these are true gold and true jewels, 
          tell me And they went, both of them, and after seven days 
          returned to the apostle, saying: Lord, we have gone about the 
          shops of all the goldsmiths, and they have all said that they 
          never saw such pure gold Likewise the jewellers have said the 
          same, that they never saw such excellent and precious gems</p>
       </div>
       <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="XVI">
        <p rend="indent">Then the holy John said unto them: Go, and redeem
          to you the lands which ye have sold, for ye have lost the estates 
          of heaven Buy yourselves silken raiment, that for a time ye
          may shine like the rose which showeth its fragrance and redness 
          and suddenly fadeth away For ye sighed at beholding your 
          servants and groaned that ye were become poor Flourish, therefore,
          <pb facs="JAMESApocryphalNewTestament1924_0284"/>
          that ye may fade: be rich for the time, that ye may be 
          beggars for ever Is not the Lord ' s hand able to make riches
          overflowing and unsurpassably glorious? but he hath appointed 
          a conflict for souls, that they may believe that they shall have 
          eternal riches, who for his name ' s sake have refused temporal
          wealth Indeed, our master told us concerning a certain rich man 
          who feasted every day and shone with gold and purple, at whose
          door lay a beggar, Lazarus, who desired to receive even the 
          crumbs that fell from his table, and no man gave unto him And 
          it came to pass that on one day they died, both of them, and 
          that beggar was taken into the rest which is in Abraham ' s bosom,
          but the rich man was cast into flaming fire: out of which he 
          lifted up his eyes and saw Lazarus, and prayed him to dip his 
          finger in water and cool his mouth, for he was tormented in the
          flames And Abraham answered him and said: Remember, son, 
          that thou receivedst good things in thy life, but this Lazarus 
          likewise evil things Wherefore rightly is he now comforted, 
          while thou art tormented, and besides all this, a great gulf is 
          fixed between you and us, so that neither can they come thence 
          hither, nor hither thence But he answered: I have five brethren:
          I pray that some one may go to warn them, that they come not 
          into this flame And Abraham said to him: They have Moses 
          and the prophets, let them hear them To that he answered: 
          Lord, unless one rise up again, they will not believe Abraham 
          said to him: If they believe not Moses and the prophets, neither 
          will they believe, if one rise again And these words our Lord 
          and Master confirmed by examples of mighty works: for when 
          they said to him: Who hath come hither from thence, that we 
          may believe him? he answered: Bring hither the dead whom
          ye have And when they had brought unto him a young man 
          which was dead (Ps-Mellitus: three dead corpses), he was waked 
          up by him as one that sleepeth, and confirmed all his words</p>
        <p rend="indent">But wherefore should I speak of my Lord, when at this present 
          there are those whom in his name and in your presence and sight 
          I have raised from the dead: in whose name ye have seen palsied 
          men healed, lepers cleansed, blind men enlightened, and many
          delivered from evil spirits? But the riches of these mighty 
          works they cannot have who have desired to have earthly wealth 
          Finally, when ye yourselves went unto the sick and called upon
          the name of Jesus Christ, they were healed: ye did drive out devils
          and restore light to the blind Behold, this grace is taken from
          you, and ye are become wretched, who were mighty and great 
          And whereas there was such fear of you upon the devils that at
          your bidding they left the men whom they possessed, now ye 
          will be in fear of the devils For he that loveth money is the s
          ervant of Mammon: and Mammon is the name of a devil who 
          is set over carnal gains, and is the master of them that love the 
          world But even the lovers of the world do not possess riches,
          <pb facs="JAMESApocryphalNewTestament1924_0285"/>
          but are possessed of them For it is out of reason that for one 
          belly there should be laid up so much food as would suffice 
          a thousand, and for one body so many garments as would furnish
          clothing for a thousand men In vain, therefore, is that stored up
          which cometh not into use, and for whom it is kept, no man 
          knoweth, as the Holy Ghost saith by the prophet: In vain is
          every man troubled who heapeth up riches and knoweth not for 
          whom he gathereth them Naked did our birth from women 
          bring us into this light, destitute of food and drink: naked will
          the earth receive us which brought us forth We possess in 
          common the riches of the heaven; the brightness of the sun is
          equal for the rich and the poor, and likewise the light of the moon 
          and the stars, the softness of the air and the drops of rain, and 
          the gate of the church and the fount of sanctification, and the 
          forgiveness of sins, and the sharing in the altar, and the eating 
          of the body and drinking of the blood of Christ, and the anointing 
          of the chrism, and the grace of the giver, and the visitation of the
          Lord, and the pardon of sin: in all these the dispensing of the
          Creator is equal, without respect of persons Neither doth the 
          rich man use these gifts after one manner and the poor after another</p>
        <p>But wretched and unhappy is the man who would have something 
          more than sufficeth him: for of this come heats of fevers, 
          rigours of cold, divers pains in all the members of the body, and
          he can neither be fed with food nor sated with drink; that covetousness
          may learn that money will not profit it, which being laid 
          up bringeth to the keepers thereof anxiety by day and night, 
          and suffereth them not even for an hour to be quiet and secure 
          For while they guard their houses against thieves, till their 
          estate, ply the plough, pay taxes, build storehouses, strive for 
          gain, try to bafiile the attacks of the strong, and to strip the weak,
          exercise their wrath on whom they can, and hardly bear it from 
          others, shrink not from playing at tables and from public shows,
          fear not to defile or to be defiled, suddenly do they depart out 
          of this world, naked, bearing only their own sins with them, for 
          which they shall suffer eternal punishment</p>
       </div>
       <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="XVII">
        <p rend="indent">While the apostle was thus speaking, behold there was 
          brought to him by his mother, who was a widow, a young man 
          who thirty days before had first married a wife And the people
          which were waiting upon the burial came with the widowed mother 
          and cast themselves at the apostle ' s feet all together with groans,
          weeping, and mourning, and besought him that in the name of 
          his God, as he had done with Drusiana, so he would raise up this
          young man also And there was so great weeping of them all
          that the apostle himself could hardly refrain from crying and tears
          He cast himself down, therefore, in prayer, and wept a long time: 
          and rising from prayer spread out his hands to heaven, and for 
          a long space prayed within himself And when he had so done
          <pb facs="JAMESApocryphalNewTestament1924_0286"/>
          thrice, he commanded the body which was swathed to be loosed,
          and said: Thou youth Stacteus, who for love of thy flesh hast
          quickly lost thy soul: thou youth which knewest not thy creator,
          nor perceivedst the Saviour of men, and wast ignorant of thy
          true friend, and therefore didst fall into the snare of the worst 
          enemy: behold, I have poured out tears and prayers unto my
          Lord for thine ignorance, that thou mayest rise from the dead, 
          the bands of death being loosed, and declare unto these two, to 
          Atticus and Eugenius, how great glory they have lost, and how
          great punishment they have incurred Then Stacteus arose and
          worshipped the apostle, and began to reproach his disciples,
          saying: I beheld your angels weeping, and the angels of Satan 
          rejoicing at your overthrow For now in a little time ye have
          lost the kingdom that was prepared for you, and the dwelling-places
          builded of shining stones, full of joy, of feasting and
          delights, full of everlasting life and eternal light: and have gotten
          yourselves places of darkness, full of dragons, of roaring flames,
          of torments, and punishments unsurpassable, of pains and 
          anguish, fear and horrible trembling Ye have lost the places
          full of unfading flowers, shining, full of the sounds of instruments 
          of music (organs), and have gotten on the other hand places 
          wherein roaring and howling and mourning ceaseth not day nor 
          night Nothing else remaineth for you save to ask the apostle
          of the Lord that like as he hath raised me to life, he would raise 
          you also from death unto salvation and bring back your souls
          which now are blotted out of the book of life</p>
       </div>
       <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="XVIII">
        <p rend="indent">Then both he that had been raised and all the people, 
          together with Atticus and Eugenius, cast themselves at the 
          apostle's feet and besought him to intercede for them with the
          Lord Unto whom the holy apostle gave this answer: that for 
          thirty days they should offer penitence to God, and in that space
          pray especially that the rods of gold might return to their nature
          and likewise the stones return to the meanness wherein they
          were made And it came to pass that after thirty days were 
          accomplished, and neither the rods were turned into wood nor
          the gems into pebbles, Atticus and Eugenius came and said to the 
          apostle: Thou hast always taught mercy, and preached forgiveness,
          and bidden that one man should spare another And if 
          God willeth that a man should forgive a man, how much more 
          shall he, as he is God, both forgive and spare men We are confounded 
          for our sin: and whereas we have cried with our eyes 
          which lusted after the world, we do now repent with eyes that 
          weep We pray thee, Lord, we pray thee, apostle of God, show
          in deed that mercy which in word thou hast always promised 
          Then the holy John said unto them as they wept and repented,
          and all interceded for them likewise: Our Lord God used these
          words when he spake concerning sinners: I will not the death of 
          a sinner, but I will rather that he be converted and live For
          <pb facs="JAMESApocryphalNewTestament1924_0287"/>
          when the Lord Jesus Christ taught us concerning the penitent, 
          he said: Verily I say unto you, there is great joy in heaven over
          one sinner that repenteth and turneth himself from his sins: 
          and there is more joy over him than over ninety and nine which
          have not sinned Wherefore I would have you know that the 
          Lord accepteth the repentance of these men And he turned 
          unto Atticus and Eugenius and said: Go, carry back the rods 
          unto the wood whence ye took them, for now are they returned 
          to their own nature, and the stones unto the sea-shore, for they 
          are become common stones as they were before And when this
          was accomplished, they received again the grace which they had 
          lost, so that again they cast out devils as before time and healed 
          the sick and enlightened the blind, and daily the Lord did many
          mighty works by their means.</p>
       </div>
       <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="XIX">
        <note type="inline"><p rend="indent">XIX tells shortly the destruction of the temple of Ephesus and the 
          conversion of 12, 000 people</p>
         <p rend="indent">Then follows the episode of the poison - cup in a form which probably
           represents the story in the Leucian Acts (We have seen that the 
           late Greek texts place it at the beginning, in the presence of Domitian)</p></note>
       </div>
       <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="XX">
        <p rend="indent">Now when Aristodemus, who was chief priest of all those
          idols, saw this, filled with a wicked spirit, he stirred up sedition
          among the people, so that one people prepared themselves to fight 
          against the other And John turned to him and said: Tell me, 
          Aristodemus, what can I do to take away the anger from thy 
          soul? And Aristodemus said: If thou wilt have me believe in thy 
          God, I will give thee poison to drink, and if thou drink it, and die 
          not, it will appear that thy God is true The apostle answered: 
          If thou give me poison to drink, when I call on the name of my 
          Lord, it will not be able to harm me Aristodemus said again: 
          I will that thou first see others drink it and die straightway,
          that so thy heart may recoil from that cup And the blessed John 
          said: I have told thee already that I am prepared to drink it,
          that thou mayest believe on the Lord Jesus Christ when thou 
          seest me whole after the cup of poison Aristodemus therefore 
          went to the proconsul and asked of him two men who were to 
          undergo the sentence of death And when he had set them in 
          the midst of the market-place before all the people, in the sight
          of the apostle he made them drink the poison: and as soon as 
          they had drunk it, they gave up the ghost Then Aristodemus
          turned to John and said: Hearken to me and depart from thy
          teaching wherewith thou callest away the people from the worship 
          of the gods; or take and drink this, that thou mayest show that 
          thy God is almighty, if after thou hast drunk, thou canst remain 
          whole Then the blessed John, as they lay dead which had drunk
          the poison, like a fearless and brave man took the cup, and making
          the sign of the cross, spake thus: My God, and the Father of 
          our Lord Jesus Christ, by whose word the heavens were established, 
          unto whom all things are subject, whom all creation serveth,
          <pb facs="JAMESApocryphalNewTestament1924_0288"/>
          whom all power obeyeth, feareth, and trembleth, when we call
          on thee for succour: whose name the serpent hearing is still,
          the dragon fleeth, the viper is quiet, the toad (which is called
          a frog) is still and strengthless, the scorpion is quenched, the
          basilisk vanquished, and the phalangia (spider) doth no hurt; 
          in a word, all venomous things, and the fiercest reptiles and 
          noisome beasts, are pierced (or covered with darkness) <note type="inline">[Ps. 
          Mellitus adds: and all roots hurtful to the health of men dry up.]</note>
          Do thou, I say, quench the venom of this poison, put out the
          deadly workings thereof, and void it of the strength which it 
          hath in it: and grant in thy sight unto all these whom thou hast 
          created, eyes that they may see, and ears that they may hear,
          and a heart that they may understand thy greatness And
          when he had thus said, he armed his mouth and all his body
          with the sign of the cross and drank all that was in the cup
          And after he had drunk, he said: I ask that they for whose sake 
          I have drunk, be turned unto thee, O Lord, and by thine enlightening 
          receive the salvation which is in thee And when for 
          the space of three hours the people saw that John was of a
          cheerful countenance, and that there was no sign at all of paleness 
          or fear in him, they began to cry out with a loud voice: He is
          the one true God whom John worshippeth</p>
       </div>
       <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="XXI">
        <p rend="indent">But Aristodemus even so believed not, though the
          people reproached him: but turned unto John and said: This 
          one thing I lack — if thou in the name of thy God raise up these 
          that have died by this poison, my mind will be cleansed of all 
          doubt When he said that, the people rose against Aristodemus,
          saying: We will burn thee and thine house if thou goest on to 
          trouble the apostle further with thy words John, therefore,
          seeing that there was a fierce sedition, asked for silence, and 
          said in the hearing of all: The first of the virtues of God 
          which we ought to imitate is patience, by which we are able to
          bear with the foolishness of unbelievers Wherefore if Aristodemus
          is still held by unbelief, let us loose the knots of his 
          unbelief He shall be compelled, even though late, to acknowledge
          his creator; for I will not cease from this work until 
          a remedy shall bring help to his wounds, and like physicians 
          which have in their hands a sick man needing medicine, so 
          also, if Aristodemus be not yet cured by that which hath now 
          been done, he shall be cured by that which I will now do And 
          he called Aristodemus to him, and gave him his coat, and he 
          himself stood clad only in his mantle And Aristodemus said to
          him: Wherefore hast thou given me thy coat? John said to 
          him: That thou mayest even so be put to shame and depart
          from thine unbelief And Aristodemus said: And how shall thy
          coat make me to depart from unbelief? The apostle answered: 
          Go and cast it upon the bodies of the dead, and thou shalt say 
          thus: The apostle of our Lord Jesus Christ hath sent me that 
          <pb facs="JAMESApocryphalNewTestament1924_0289"/>
          in his name ye may rise again, that all may know that life and 
          death are servants of my Lord Jesus Christ Which when
          Aristodemus had done, and had seen them rise, he worshipped 
          John, and ran quickly to the proconsul and began to say with
          a loud voice: Hear me, hear me, thou proconsul; I think thou 
          rememberest that I have often stirred up thy wrath against John 
          and devised many things against him daily, wherefore I fear lest
          I feel his wrath: for he is a god hidden in the form of a man,
          and hath drunk poison, and not only continueth whole, but them 
          also which had died by the poison he hath recalled to life by my
          means, by the touch of his coat, and they have no mark of death 
          upon them Which when the proconsul heard he said: And
          what wilt thou have me to do? Aristodemus answered: Let us
          go and fall at his feet and ask pardon, and whatever he commandeth 
          us let us do Then they came together and cast themselves
          down and besought forgiveness: and he received them 
          and offered prayer and thanksgiving to God, and he ordained 
          them a fast of a week, and when it was fulfilled he baptized them
          in the name of the Lord Jesus Christ and his Almighty Father,
          and the Holy Ghost the illuminator [And when they were
          baptized, with all their house and their servants and their kindred,
          they brake all their idols and built a church in the name of
          Saint John: wherein he himself was taken up, in manner following:]</p>
         <note type="inline"><p rend="indent">This bracketed sentence, of late complexion, serves to introduce the 
           last episode of the book</p>
           <p rend="indent">Here we may insert a notice of three detached fragments of the Acts</p>
           <p rend="indent">a The upper portion of a papyrus leaf of the fourth century, 
             Oxyrhynchus papyri, no 850 (vol vi, 1908) The order of the two 
             pages is doubted by the editors, who suggest that the recto should follow the verso</p></note>
          <p rend="align(center)">Recto</p>
          <l>departure</l>
          <l>. . . . Andronicus and his wife . . . . </l>
          <l>(this is the title of the following episode) </l>
          <l n="1, 2"> And when a few days had passed, John went forth with many of the brethren to . . .</l>
          <l n="3">  . . . . to cross a bridge under which a deep river ran</l>
         <l n="4"> (and as John) went to the brethren</l>
         <l n="5"> (behold a man) came towards him clad in the manner of a soldier</l>
         <l n="6"> and standing before him said: John, into </l>
         <l n="7"> (my) hands thou shall shortly come And John (in wrath)</l>
         <l n="8"> (said): the Lord shall quench thy threatening and thy wrath and</l>
         <l n="9"> (thy trans) gression And lo he vanished away (When therefore)</l>
         <l n="10"> John was come to those to whom he went, and found</l>
         <pb facs="JAMESApocryphalNewTestament1924_0290"/>
         <l n="11"> (them) gathered together, he said: Rise up my breth </l>
         <l n="12"> (ren) let us bow our knees unto the Lord and</l>
         <l n="12, 13"> brought to nought the unseen working of the great enemy</l>
         <l n="14"> bowed his knees together with them . . . said </l>
         <l n="15"> . . . . God</l>
         <note type="inline"><p rend="indent">Here is the appearance of a demon disguised as a soldier who 
         threatens John, perhaps predicting his arrest, and is routed John is 
         about to pray with the brethren</p></note>
         <p rend="align (center)">Verso</p>
         <l n="1"> for him</l> 
         <l n="2"> groanings and</l>
         <l n="3"> but John</l>
         <l n="4"> to Zeuxis, having risen and taken up a (cup)</l>
         <l n="5"> . . . . who didst compel me with</l>
         <l n="6, 7"> thinking to strangle himself: that dost turn things 
           despaired of unto thee: 7, 8 that makest known . . . . the things that</l>
         <l n="8"> are known to no man: that weepest for the afflicted </l>
         <l n="9"> that raisest up those that have been put to death </l>
         <l n="10"> of the helpless: Jesu the comforter of the</l>
         <l n="11"> we praise thee and worship and give thanks </l>
         <l n="12"> for all thy gifts: and for thy present dispensation</l>
         <l n="13, 14"> and ministry And unto Zeuxis only he gave of the eucharist, and afterward gave to them that would receive</l>
         <l n="15"> looking on him durst not: but the proconsul</l>
         <l n="16"> (? sending a) centurion in the midst of the assembly (church?) saith to John</l>
         <l n="17"> : Servant of the unnameable (God</l>
         <l n="18"> hath brought letters from Caesar </l>
         <l n="19"> (? in which is contained: Domitianus Caesar) and the sen (ate . . . .</l>
         <note type="inline"><p rend="indent">Zeuxis has tried to hang himself He has been delivered and a service
           of thanksgiving is held The proconsul is already there and 
           has seen the miracle: he brings letters from the emperor</p>
         <p rend="indent">The editor questions whether there is room in the lower part of the 
           recto to finish John ' s prayer and introduce the episode of Zeuxis 
           But the author, while often very prolix, can also get over much ground
           in few lines And it is equally difficult to see how the emperor's letter
           should be dismissed and done with in half a page and a story about Andronicus follow immediately</p>
          <p rend="indent">The interest of the fragment for the general course of the story
            lies in this, that it confirms our belief that John was represented as 
            coming under the notice of the emperor; and probably either exile
            or the caldron of oil, or both, were the sequels of the transaction:
            I doubt, however, whether the trial was laid at Rome</p>
           <p rend="indent">b and c are quotations preserved in a barbarous Latin Apocryphon 
             called the Epistle of Titus, mainly a declamation about virginity, which 
          <pb facs="JAMESApocryphalNewTestament1924_0291"/>
          exists in one manuscript at Würzburg (eighth century) Dom Donatien
          de Bruyne printed them in the Revue Bénédictine for 1908 (pp 149 – 60)</p></note>
         <p rend="indent">b Or is that outside the law which we are taught, how the
           very devils (when they ] confessed to Dyrus (read Verus) the deacon 
           as to the coming of John: consider what they said: Many will 
           come to us in the last times to turn us out of our vessels (i. e. the 
           bodies possessed by them), saying that they are pure and clean
           from women and are not held by desire of them: whom (MS. 
           while) if we desired, we (could) possess them also</p>
         <note type="inline"><p rend="indent">This should come from an early part of the book I take it to 
           precede John ' s first visit to Ephesus My rendering indicates the 
           obscurity of the original</p>
           <p rend="indent">c is so confused (and wearisome) that it defies translation It is 
             a diatribe of John ' s against matrimony and begins thus:</p></note>
         <p rend="indent">Receive therefore in thy heart the admonition of the blessed 
         John, who, when he was bidden to a marriage, came not save for
         the sake of chastity, and consider what he said: Little children,
         while yet your flesh is pure and ye have your body untouched 
         and not destroyed, and are not defiled by Satan, the great enemy 
         and shameless (foe) of chastity: know therefore more fully the
         mystery of the nuptial union: it is the experiment of the serpent, 
         the ignorance of teaching, injury of the seed, the gift of death,
        . . . (thirty-one (!) clauses follow, many of which are quite corrupt;
         the last are) the impediment which separateth from 
         the Lord, the beginning of disobedience, the end of life, and 
         death Hearing this, little children, join yourselves together in
         an inseparable marriage, holy and true, waiting for the one true
         incomparable bridegroom from heaven, even Christ, the everlasting 
         bridegroom</p>
         <p rend="indent">If, then, the apostle severed a marriage, lest it should be an occasion of sin . . . &amp;c</p>
         <note type="inline"><p rend="indent">This is the most avowedly Encratite passage in the Acts: true, 
         John persuaded Andronicus and others to dissolve their marriage in 
         all but name: but there is nowhere else such a wealth of abuse of the
         institution of marriage as such The speech belongs to an episode of
         which we know nothing; it cannot refer to Andronicus or Lycomedes,
         who were both married when first we hear of them</p>
         <p rend="indent">A third quotation in the Epistle of Titus is taken from an extant 
           part of the Acts, the last prayer of John</p>
         <p rend="indent">The last episode of these Acts (as is the case with several others 
           of the Apocryphal Acts) was preserved separately for reading in church on 
           the Saint ' s day We have it in at least nine Greek manuscripts, and in
           many versions: Latin, Syriac, Armenian, Coptic, Ethiopic, Slavonic</p></note>
       </div>
       <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="106">
        <p rend="indent">John therefore continued with the brethren, rejoicing
          in the Lord And on the morrow, being the Lord ' s day, and all
          the brethren being gathered together, he began to say unto 
          them: Brethren and fellow-servants and coheirs and partakers
          with me in the kingdom of the Lord, ye know the Lord, how 
          <pb facs="JAMESApocryphalNewTestament1924_0292"/>
          many mighty works he hath granted you by my means, how
          many wonders, healings, signs, how great spiritual gifts, teachings, 
          governings, refreshings, ministries, knowledges, glories, graces, 
          gifts, beliefs, communions, all which ye have seen given you by
          him in your sight, yet not seen by these eyes nor heard by these 
          ears Be ye therefore stablished in him, remembering him in 
          your every deed, knowing the mystery of the dispensation which
          hath come to pass towards men, for what cause the Lord hath 
          accomplished it He beseecheth you by me, brethren, and 
          entreateth you, desiring to remain without grief, without insult, 
          not conspired against, not chastened: for he knoweth even the 
          insult that cometh of you, he knoweth even dishonour, he 
          knoweth even conspiracy, he knoweth even chastisement, from 
          them that hearken not to his commandments</p>
       </div>
       <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="107">
        <p rend="indent">Let not then our good God be grieved, the compassionate, 
          the merciful, the holy, the pure, the undefiled, the immaterial, 
          the only, the one, the unchangeable, the simple, the guileless, 
          the unwrathful, even our God Jesus Christ, who is above every 
          name that we can utter or conceive, and more exalted Let 
          him rejoice with us because we walk aright, let him be glad 
          because we live purely, let him be refreshed because our conversation 
          is sober Let him be without care because we live continently,
          let him be pleased because we communicate one with another, 
          let him smile because we are chaste, let him be merry because we
          love him These things I now speak unto you, brethren, because 
          I am hasting unto the work set before me, and already being 
          perfected by the Lord For what else could I have to say unto
          you? Ye have the pledge of our God, ye have the earnest of
          ħis goodness, ye have his presence that cannot be shunned If, 
          then, ye sin no more, he forgiveth you that ye did in ignorance:
          but if after that ye have known him and he hath had mercy on
          you, ye walk again in the like deeds, both the former will be laid 
          to your charge, and also ye will not have a part nor mercy before him</p>
       </div>
       <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="108">
        <p rend="indent">And when he had spoken this unto them, he prayed thus: 
          O Jesu who hast woven this crown with thy weaving, who 
          hast joined together these many blossoms into the unfading
          flower of thy countenance, who hast sown in them these words: 
          thou only tender of thy servants, and physician who healest
          freely: only doer of good and despiser of none, only merciful
          and lover of men, only saviour and righteous, only seer of all,
          who art in all and everywhere present and containing all things 
          and filling all things: Christ Jesu, God, Lord, that with thy
          gifts and thy mercy shelterest them that trust in thee, that 
          knowest clearly the wiles and the assaults of him that is everywhere 
          our adversary, which he deviseth against us: do thou 
          only, O Lord, succour thy servants by thy visitation Even so, Lord
          <pb facs="JAMESApocryphalNewTestament1924_0293"/></p>
       </div>
       <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="109">
        <p rend="indent">And he asked for bread, and gave thanks thus: What
          praise or what offering or what thanksgiving shall we, breaking
          this bread, name save thee only, O Lord Jesu? We glorify thy 
          name that was said by the Father: we glorify thy name that
          was said through the Son (or we glorify the name of Father that
          was said by thee . . . the name of Son that was said by thee):
          we glorify thine entering of the Door We glorify the resurrection
          shown unto us by thee We glorify thy way, we glorify of 
          thee the seed, the word, the grace, the faith, the salt, the unspeakable
          (al chosen) pearl, the treasure, the plough, the net, the greatness,
          the diadem, him that for us was called Son of man, that gave
          unto us truth, rest, knowledge, power, the commandment, the 
          confidence, hope, love, liberty, refuge in thee For thou, Lord,
          art alone the root of immortality, and the fount of incorruption,
          and the seat of the ages: called by all these names for us now, 
          that calling on thee by them we may make known thy greatness 
          which at the present is invisible unto us, but visible only unto the
          pure, being portrayed in thy manhood only</p>
       </div>
       <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="110">
        <p rend="indent">And he brake the bread and gave unto all of us, praying 
          over each of the brethren that he might be worthy of the grace
          of the Lord and of the most holy eucharist And he partook
          also himself likewise, and said: Unto me also be there a part 
          with you, and: Peace be with you, my beloved</p>
       </div>
       <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="111">
        <p rend="indent">After that he said unto Verus: Take with thee some two
          men, with baskets and shovels, and follow me And Verus
          without delay did as he was bidden by John the servant of God
          The blessed John therefore went out of the house and walked 
          forth of the gates, having told the more part to depart from him
          And when he was come to the tomb of a certain brother of ours,
          he said to the young men: Dig, my children And they dug: 
          and he was instant with them yet more, saying: Let the trench
          be deeper And as they dug he spoke unto them the word of
          God and exhorted them that were come with him out of the
          house, edifying and perfecting them unto the greatness of God, 
          and praying over each one of us And when the young men had 
          finished the trench as he desired, we knowing nothing of it, he
          took off his garments wherein he was clad and laid them as it 
          were for a pallet in the bottom of the trench: and standing in 
          his shift only he stretched his hands upward and prayed thus:</p>
       </div>
       <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="112">
        <p rend="indent">O thou that didst choose us out for the apostleship of the 
          Gentiles: O God that sentest us into the world: that didst
          reveal thyself by the law and the prophets: that didst never
          rest, but alway from the foundation of the world savedst them
          that were able to be saved: that madest thyself known through 
          all nature: that proclaimedst thyself even among beasts: that
          didst make the desolate and savage soul tame and quiet: that 
          gavest thyself to it when it was athirst for thy words: that didst 
          appear to it in haste when it was dying: that didst show thyself
          <pb facs="JAMESApocryphalNewTestament1924_0294"/>
          to it as a law when it was sinking into lawlessness: that didst
          manifest thyself to it when it had been vanquished by Satan: 
          that didst overcome its adversary when it fled unto thee: that
          gavest it thine hand and didst raise it up from the things of
          Hades: that didst not leave it to walk after a bodily sort (in
          the body): that didst show to it its own enemy: that hast made 
          for it a clear knowledge toward thee: O God, Jesu, the Father 
          of them that are above the heavens, the Lord of them that are
          in the heavens, the law of them that are in the ether, the course
          of them that are in the air, the keeper of them that are on the 
          earth, the fear of them that are under the earth, the grace of 
          them that are thine own: receive also the soul of thy John, 
          which it may be is accounted worthy by thee</p>
       </div>
       <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="113">
        <p rend="indent">O thou who hast kept me until this hour for thyself and 
          untouched by union with a woman: who when in my youth 
          I desired to marry didst appear unto me and say to me: John, 
          I have need of thee: who didst prepare for me also a sickness of 
          the body: who when for the third time I would marry didst 
          forthwith prevent me, and then at the third hour of the day 
          saidst unto me on the sea: John, if thou hadst not been mine, 
          I would have suffered thee to marry: who for two years didst 
          blind me (or afflict mine eyes), and grant me to mourn and
          entreat thee: who in the third year didst open the eyes of my 
          mind and also grant me my visible eyes: who when I saw clearly
          didst ordain that it should be grievous to me to look upon a
          woman: who didst save me from the temporal fantasy and 
          lead me unto that which endureth always: who didst rid me of
          the foul madness that is in the flesh: who didst take me from
          the bitter death and establish me on thee alone: who didst
          muzzle the secret disease of my soul and cut off the open deed:
          who didst afflict and banish him that raised tumult in me: who 
          didst make my love of thee spotless: who didst make my joining 
          unto thee perfect and unbroken: who didst give me undoubting 
          faith in thee, who didst order and make clear my inclination
          toward thee: thou who givest unto every man the due reward
          of his works, who didst put into my soul that I should have 
          no possession save thee only: for what is more precious than 
          thee? Now therefore Lord, whereas I have accomplished the 
          dispensation wherewith I was entrusted, account thou me 
          worthy of thy rest, and grant me that end in thee which is
          salvation unspeakable and unutterable</p>
       </div>
       <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="114">
        <p rend="indent">And as I come unto thee, let the fire go backward, let the
          darkness be overcome, let the gulf be without strength, let the 
          furnace die out, let Gehenna be quenched Let angels follow,
          let devils fear, let rulers be broken, let powers fall; let the
          places of the right hand stand fast, let them of the left hand 
          not remain Let the devil be muzzled, let Satan be derided, let
          his wrath be burned out, let his madness be stilled, let his
          <pb facs="JAMESApocryphalNewTestament1924_0295"/>
          vengeance be ashamed, let his assault be in pain, let his children
          be smitten and all his roots plucked up And grant me to
          accomplish the journey unto thee without suffering insolence or
          provocation, and to receive that which thou hast promised unto
          them that live purely and have loved thee only</p>
       </div>
       <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="115">
        <p rend="indent">And having sealed himself in every part, he stood and 
          said: Thou art with me, O Lord Jesu Christ: and laid himself
          down in the trench where he had strown his garments: and 
          having said unto us: Peace be with you, brethren, he gave up his spirit rejoicing</p>
         <note type="inline"><p rend="indent">The less good Greek manuscripts and some versions are not content 
           with this simple ending The Latin says that after the prayer a great 
           light appeared over the apostle for the space of an hour, so bright that 
           no one could look at it (Then he laid himself down and gave up the 
           ghost) We who were there rejoiced, some of us, and some mourned.
           . . . And forthwith manna issuing from the tomb was seen of all, 
           which manna that place produceth even unto this day, &amp;c But 
           perhaps the best conclusion is that of one Greek manuscript:</p></note>
         <p rend="indent">We brought a linen cloth and spread it upon him, and went 
           into the city And on the day following we went forth and 
           found not his body, for it was translated by the power of our 
           Lord Jesus Christ, unto whom be glory, &amp;c</p>
         <p rend="indent">Another says: On the morrow we dug in the place, and him 
           we found not, but only his sandals, and the earth moving (lit 
           springing up like a well), and after that we remembered that 
           which was spoken by the Lord unto Peter, &amp;c</p>
         <note type="inline"><p rend="indent">Augustine (on John xxi) reports the belief that in his time the earth
           over the grave was seen to move as if stirred by John's breathing</p></note>
      </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</text>
</TEI>
