<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
    
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>CATENÆ GRÆCORUM PATRUM IN NOVUM TESTAMENTUM</title>
    <editor>J. A. CRAMER, S.T.P.</editor>
    <sponsor>University of Leipzig</sponsor>
    <funder>European Social Fund Saxony</funder>
    <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
    <principal>Monica Berti</principal>
    <meeting/>
    <respStmt>
     <persName xml:id="DDD">Digital Divide Data</persName>
     <resp>Corrected and encoded the text</resp>
    </respStmt>
    <respStmt>
     <persName>Greta Franzini</persName>
     <resp>Project Manager (University of Leipzig)</resp>
    </respStmt>
    <respStmt>
     <persName>Simona Stoyanova</persName>
     <resp>Project Assistant (University of Leipzig)</resp>
    </respStmt>
    <respStmt>
     <persName>Bruce Robertson</persName>
     <resp>Technical Advisor</resp>
    </respStmt>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <authority>University of Leipzig</authority>
    <idno type="filename">TO BE ADDED BY LEIPZIG</idno>
    <availability>
     <p>Available under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International
      License</p>
    </availability>
    <date>2014</date>
    <publisher>University of Leipzig</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Germany</pubPlace>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <listBibl xml:lang="la">
     <biblStruct>
      <monogr>
       <title>CATENÆ GRÆCORUM PATRUM IN NOVUM TESTAMENTUM</title>
       <editor>
        <persName>
         <name xml:lang="la">J. A. CRAMER, S.T.P.</name>
        </persName>
       </editor>
       <author ref="urn:tmp">J. A. CRAMER, S.T.P.</author>
       <imprint>
        <publisher>E TYPOGRAPHEO ACADEMICO.</publisher>
        <pubPlace>OXONII,</pubPlace>
        <date>MDCCCXL.</date>
       </imprint>
       <biblScope unit="volume">vol. viii</biblScope>
      </monogr>
     </biblStruct>
    </listBibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <p>Text encoded in accordance with the latest EpiDoc standards (January 2014)</p>
  <refsDecl>
        <cRefPattern n="" matchPattern="(.+).(.+).(.+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div[@type='edition']/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:div[@n='$2']/tei:div[@n='$3'])"/>
        <cRefPattern n="" matchPattern="(.+).(.+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div[@type='edition']/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:div[@n='$2'])"/>
        <cRefPattern n="" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div[@type='edition']/tei:div[@n='$1'])"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <langUsage>
    <language ident="el">Greek</language>
    <language ident="la">Latin</language>
   </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change/>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
	<text><body><div type="edition" n="vol. iii_1_1_1_1">
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="1">
<pb n="1"/>
<head>June, 1884.</head>
<head>Dlarendon Press, Oxford</head>
<p>Α SELECTION OF
BΟΟKS
PUBLISHED FOR THE UNIVERSITY BY
HENRY FROWDE,
AT THE OXFORD UNIVERSITY PRESS WAREHOUSE,
AMEN CORNER, LONDON.
ALSO TO BE HAD AT THE
CLARENDON PRESS DEPOSITORY, OXFORD.</p>
<p>[Every book is bound in cloth, unless otherwise .]</p>
<p>LEXICONS, QRAMMARS, c.</p>
<p>(See also Clarendon Fress Series, pp. 14, 18, 21, 24, 25.)</p>
<p>ANGLO-SAXON. — An Anglo-Saxon Dictionary, based on the
MS. CoUections of the late Joseph Bosworth, D.D., Professor of Anglo-Saxon,
Oxford. Edited and enlarged by Prof. T. Ν. Toller, Μ.Α. (To be completed
in four parts.) Parts I and II. Α— HWISTLIAN (pp. vi, 576). 1882. 4to.
15 s. each.</p>
<p>Chixese. — A Handbook of the Chinese Language. Parts I
and II, Grammar and Chrestomathy. By James Summers. 1863. 1863.
half bound, il. 8s.</p>
<p>ENGLISH.— A New English Dictionary, on Historical Principles:
founded mainly on the materials collected by the Philological Society.
Edited by James Α. H. Murray, LL.D., President of the Philological Society;
with the assistance of many Scholars and men of Science. Part I. — ANT
(pp. xvi, 352). Imperial 410. 12s. 6d.</p>
<p>— An Etymological Dictionary of the English Language,
arranged on an Historical Basis. By. W. W. Skeat, Μ.Α. Second Editimt.
1884. 4to. 2l. 4s.</p>
<p>— Supplement to the First Edition of the above. 1884.
4to. 2s. 6d. Just Published.</p>
<p>—A Concise Etymological Dictionary of the English Language.
By W. W. Skeat, M.A. 1884. Crown 1884. νυ. 6d.</p>
<p>Greek. — A Greek-English Lexicon, by Henry George
Liddell, D.D., and Robert Scott, D.D. Seventh Edition, Revised and Augmented
mented throughout. 1883. 1883. 4to. I6s.</p>
<p>— A Greek-English Lexicon, abridged from Liddell and
Scotfs 4to. edition, chiefiy for the use of Schools. Tweutieth Edition.
Carefully Revised throughout. 1883. Square 12mo. 7s. 6d.</p>

<pb n="2"/>
<p>Greek.—A copious Greek-English Vocabtdary, compiled from
the best authorities. 1850. 24mo. 3s.</p>
<p>— A Practical Introduction to Greek Accentuation, by Η.
W. Chandler, M.A. Second Edition. 1881. 1881. los. 6d.</p>
<p>Hebrew.—Tke Book of Hebrew Roots, by Abu ᾿I-Waîd
Marwan ibn Janah, otherwise called Rabbi Yonah. Now first edited, with an
Appendix, by Ad. Neubauer. 1875. 4to. 2l. 7s. 6d.</p>
<p>— A Treatise on the tise of the Tenses in Hebrew. By
S. R. Driver, M.A. Second Edition, Revised and Enlarged. 1881. Extra
fcap. 8vo. 7s. 6d.</p>
<p>— Hebrew Accentuation of Psalms, Proverbs, and Job,
By William Wickes, D.D. 1881. Demy 8vo. stiff covers, 5s.</p>
<p>ICELANDIC.—An Icelandic-English Dictionary, based on the
MS. coUections of the late Richard Cleasby. Enlarged and completed by
G. Vigfusson, Α. With an Introduction, and Life of Richard Cleasby, by
G. Webbe Dasent, D.C.L. 1874. 1874. 4to. 3l. 7s.</p>
<p>— A List of English Words the Etymology of which is
illustrated by comparison with Icelandic. Prepared in the form ὁ an
APPENDIX to the above. By W. W. Skeat, M.A. 1876. stitched, 2s.</p>
<p>— An Icelandic Prose Reader, with Notes, Grammar and
Glossary, by Dr. Gudbrand Vigfiisson and F. York Powell, M.A. 1879.
Extra fcap. 8vo. los, 6d.</p>
<p>Latin. — A Latin Dictionary, founded on ’ edition
of ’s Latin Dictionary, revised, enlarged, and in great part rewritten
by Charlton T. Lewis, Ph.D., and Charles Short, LL.D. 1879. 4to. 1l. 5s.</p>
<p>Sanskrit.—A Practical Grammar of the Sanskrit Language,
arranged with reference to the Classical Languages of Europe, for the use of
English Students, by Monier Williams, M.A. Fourth Edition, 1877, 8vo. 15s.</p>
<p>— A Sanskrit-English Dictionary, Etymologically and
Philologically arranged, with special reference to Greek, Latin, German, Anglo-
Saxon, English, and other cognate Indo-European Languages, By Monier
Williams, M.A. 1872. 4to. 4l. 14s. 6d.</p>
<p>— Nalopdkhydnam. Story of Nala, an Episode of the
Maha-Bharata: the Sanskrit text, with a copious Vocabulary, and an improved
version of Dean ’s Translation, by Monier Williams, M.A. Second
Edition, Revised and Improved. 1879. 8vo. 15s.</p>
<p>— Sakuntald. A Sanskrit Drama, in Seven Acts. Edited
by Monier Williams, M.A. Second Edition, 1876. 8vo. 21s.</p>
<p>Syriac.—Thesaurus Syriacus: collegerunt Quatremere, Bernstein,
Lorsbach, Arnoldi, Agrell, Field, Roediger: edidit R, Payne Smith,
S.T.P. Fasc. I-VI. 1868-83. sm. fol, each, 1l. 1s. Vol. I, containing
Fasc. I-V, sm. fol, 5l. 5s.</p>
<p>— The Book ofKalllah and Dimnah. Translated from Arabic
into Syriac. Edited by W. Wright, LL.D, Profcssor of Arabic in the University
of Cambridge. 8vo. 1884. 21s.</p>

<pb n="3"/>
<p>GREEK CLASSICS, &amp;c.</p>
<p>Aristophanes: A Complete Concordance to the Comedies
and Fragments. By Henry Dunbar, M.D, 4to. 1l. 1s.</p>
<p>Aristotle: The Politics, translated into English, with Introduction,
Marginal Analysis, Notes, and Indices, by B. Jowett, M.A. Medium
8vo. Nearly ready.</p>
<p>Heracliti Ephesii Reliquiae. Recensuit I. Bywater, M.A.
Appendicis loco additae sunt Diogenis Laertii Vita Heracliti, Particulae Hiprocratei
De Diaeta Libri Primi, Epistolae Heracliteae. 1877. 8vo. 6s.</p>
<p>Homer: A Complete Concordance to the Odyssey and
Hymns of Homer; to which is added a Concordance to the Parallel Passages
in the Iliad, Odyssey, and Hymns. By Henry Dunbar, M.D. 1880. 1880. 1l. 1s.</p>
<p>— Scholia Graeca in Iliadem. Edited by Professor W.
Dindorf, after a new coUation of the Venetian MSS. by D. B. Monro, M.A.,
Fellow of Oriel College.</p>
<p>Vols. I. II. 1875. 8vo. 24s.</p>
<p>Vols. III. IV. 1877. 8vo. 26s.</p>
<p>Vols. V. VI. In Preparation.</p>
<p>— Scholia Graeca in Odysseam. Edidit Guil. Dindorfius
Tomi IL 1855. 8vo. 15s. 6d.</p>
<p>Plato : Apology, with a revised Text and English Notes, and
a Digest of Platonic Idioms, by James Riddell, M.A. 1878. 8vo. 8s. 6d.</p>
<p>— Philebus, with a revised Text and EngHsh Notes, by
Edward Poste, M.A. 1860. 1860. 7s. 6d.</p>
<p>— Sophistes and Politicus, with a revised Text and English
Notes, by L. Campbell, M.A. 1867. 8vo. 18s.</p>
<p>— Theaetetus, with a revised Text and English Notes,
by L. Campbell, M.A. Second Edition. 8vo. 10s. 6d.</p>
<p>— The Dialogues, translated into English, with Analyses
and Introductions, by B. Jowett, M.A. A new Edition in 5 volumes, medium
8vo. 1875. 3l. 10s.</p>
<p>— The Repuhlic, translated into English, with an Analysis
and Introduction, by B. Jowett, M.A. Medium 8vo. 12s. 6d.</p>
<p>Index to. Compiled for the Second Edition of Professor
Jowett's Translation of the Dialogues. By Evelyn Abbott, M.A. 1875.
8vo. paper covers, 2s. 6d.</p>
<p>Thucydides: Translated into English, with Introduction,
Marginal Analysis, Notes, and Indices. By B, Jowett, M.A. 2 vols. 1881.
Mediom 8vo. 1l. 12s.</p>

<pb n="4"/>
<p>THE HOLY SCRIPTUBES, c.</p>
<p>English.—The Holy Bible in the earliest English Versions,
made from the Latin Vulgate by John Wycliffe and his foUowers : edited by
the Rev. J. Forshall and Sir F. Madden. 4 vols. 1850. Royal 4to. 3l. 3s.</p>
<p>[Also reprinted from the above, with Introduction and Qlossary
by W. W. Skeat, M.A.</p>
<p>— The Books of Job, Psahns, Proverbs, Ecclesiastes, and the
Song of Solomon: according to the Wycliffite Version made by Nicholas
de Hereford, about A.D. 1381, and Revised by John Purvey, about A.D. 1388.
Extra fcap. Svo. 8vo. 3s. 6d.</p>
<p>— The New Testament in English, according to the Version
by John Wycliffe, about A.D. 1380, and Revised by John Purvey, about A.D,
1388. Extra fcap. .8vo. 6s.]</p>
<p>— The Holy Bihle : an exact reprint, page for page, of the
AuthorisedVersion publishedin the year 1611. Demy 4to. halfbound, 1l. 1s.</p>
<p>Gothic.—The Gospel of St. Mark in Gothic, according to
the translation made by Wulfila in the Fourth Century. Edited with a
Grammatical Introduction and Glossarial Index by W. W. Skeat, M.A.
Extra fcap. 8vo. 4s.</p>
<p>Greek. — Vetus Testamentum ex Versione Septuaginta Interpretum
secundum exemplar Vaticanum Romae editum. Accedit polior varietas
Codicis Alexandrini. Tomi III. Editio Altera. 18mo. 18s.</p>
<p>— Origenis Hexaplorum quae supersunt ; sive, Veterum
Interpretum Graecorum in totum Vetus Testamentum Fragmenta. Edidit
Fridericus Field, A.M. 2 vols. 1875. 4to. 5l. 5s.</p>
<p>— The Book of Wisdom : the Greek Text, the Latin
Vulgate, and the Authorised English Version ; with an Introduction, Critical
Apparatus, and a Commentary. By William J. Deane, M.A. Small 4to. 12s. 6d.</p>
<p>— Nounm Testamentum Graece. Antiquissimorum Codicum
Textus in ordine parallelo dispositi. Accedit coUatio Codicis Sinaitici. Edidit
Ε. Η. Hansell, S.T. B. Tomilll. 1864. 8vo. halfmorocco, 2l. 12s. 6d.</p>
<p>— Nounm Testamentum Graece. Accedunt parallela S.
Scripturae loca, necnon vetus capitulorum notatio et canones Eusebii, Edidit
Carolus Lloyd, S.T.P.R. 18mo. 3s.</p>
<p>The same on writing paper, with large margin, 10s.</p>
<p>— Nounm Testamenttim Graece juxta Exemplar MilHanum.
18mo. 2s. 6d.</p>
<p>The same on writing paper, with large margin, 9s.</p>

<pb n="5"/>
<p>Greek, — Evangelia Sacra Graece. Fcap. 8vo. limp, 1s. 6d.</p>
<p>— The Greek Testament, with the Readings adopted by
the Revisers of the Authorised Version: —</p>
<p>(1) Pica type. Second Edition, with Marginal References. Demy 8vo.
10s. 6d.</p>
<p>(2) Long Primer type, Fcap. 8vo. 4s. 6d.</p>
<p>(3) The same, on writing paper, with wide margin, 15s.</p>
<p>— The Parallel New Testament, Greek and English ; being
the Anthorised Version, 1611; the Revised Version, 1881; and the Greek
Text followed in the Revised Version. 8vo. 12s. 6d.</p>
<p>The Revised Version is the joint froperty ofthe Universities of Oxford and Cambridge.</p>
<p>— Canon Mtiratorianus : the earliest Catalogue of the
Books of the New Testament. Edited with Notes and a Facsimile of the
MS. in the Ambrosian Library at Milan, by S. Ρ. Tregelles, LL.D. 1867.
4to. 10s. 6d.</p>
<p>— Outlines of Textual Criticism applied to tJie New Testament.
By C. Ε Hammond, Μ.Α. Third Edition. Extra fcap. 8vo. 3s. 6d.</p>
<p>Hebrew, etc. — The Psalms in Hebrew without points. 1879.
Crown 8vo. 3s. 6d.</p>
<p>— A Cominentary on the Book of Proverhs. Attributed
to Abraham Ibn Ezra. Edited from a MS. in the Bodleian Library by
S. R. Driver, M.A. Crown 8vo. paper covers, 3s. 6d.</p>
<p>— The Book of Tobit. A Chaldee Text, from a unique
MS. in the Bodleian Library ; with other Rabbinical Texts, English Transla-
tions, and the Itala. Edited by Ad. Neubauer, M.A. 1878. Crown 8vo. 6s.</p>
<p>— Horae Hebraicae et Talmudicae, a J. Lightfoot. Α new
Edition, by R. Gandell, Μ.Α. 4 vols. 1859. 8vo. 1l. 1s.</p>
<p>Latin. — Libri Psalmorum Versio antiqua Latina, cum Paraphrasi
Anglo-Saxonica. Edidit B. Thorpe, F.A.S. 1835. 8vo. 10s. 6d.</p>
<p>— Old-Latin Biblical Texts: Ἄτθ’. I. The Gospel according
to St. Matthew from the St. Germain MS. (g1). Edited with Introduction
and Appendices by John Wordsworth, Μ.Α. Small 4to. stiff covers, 6s.</p>
<p>Old-French. — Libri Psalmorum Versio antiqua Gallica e
Cod. MS. in Bibl. Bodleiana adservato, una cum Versione Metrica aliisque
Monumentis pervetustis. Nunc primum descripsit et edidit Franciscus Michel,
Phil. Doct. 1860. 8vo Tor. 6d.</p>

<pb n="6"/>
<p>FATHERS OF THE CHURCH, c.</p>
<p>St. Athanasius : Hisiorical Writings, according to the Benedictine
Text. With an Introduction by William Bright, D.D. 1881. Crown
8vo. 10s. 6d.</p>
<p>— Orations against the Arians. With an Account of his
Life by William Bright, D.D. 1873. Crown 8vo. 9s.</p>
<p>St. Augusiine: Select Antt-Pelagian Treatises, and the Acts
of the Second Council of Orange. With an Introduction by William Bright,
D.D. Crown 8vo. 9s.</p>
<p>Canons of the First Four General Councils of Nicaea, Constantinople,
Ephesus, and Chalcedon. 1877. Crown 8vo. 2s. 6d.</p>
<p>— Notes on the Canons of the First Four General Councils.
By William Bright, D.D. 1882. Crown 8vo. 5s.</p>
<p>Cyrilli Archiepiscopi Alexandrini in XII Prophetas. Edidit
Ρ. Ε. Pusey, A.M. Tomi II. 1868. 8vo. cloth. 2l. 2s.</p>
<p>— in D. Joannis Evangelium. Accedunt Fragmenta varia
necnon Tractatus ad Tiberium Diaconum duo. Edidit post Aubertum P.
Ε. Pusey, A.M. Tomi IIi. 1872. 8vo. 2l. 5s.</p>
<p>— Commentarii in Lucae Evangelium quae supersunt
Syriace. E MSS. apud Mus. Britan. edidit R. Payne Smith, A.M. 1858.
4to. 1l. 2s.</p>
<p>— Translated by R. Payne Smith, M.A. 3 vols. 1859.
8vo. 14s.</p>
<p>Ephraemi Syri, Rabulae Episcopi Edesseni, Balaei, aliorum-
que Opera Selecta. Ε Codd. Syriacis MSS. in Museo Britannico et Bibliotheca
Bodleiana asservatis primus edidit J. J. Overbeck. 1865. 8vo. 1l. 1s.</p>
<p>Eusebius' Ecclesiastical History., according to the text of
Burton, with an Introduction by William Bright, D.D. 1881. Crown 8vo.
8s. 6d.</p>
<p>Irenaeus: The Third Book of St. Ircftaeus, Bishop of Lyons,
against Heresies. With short Notes and a Glossary by Η. Deane, B.D.
1874. Crown 8vo. 5s. 6d.</p>
<p>Patrum Apostolicorum, S. Clementis Romani, S. Ignatii,
S. Polycarpi, quae supersimt. Edidit Guil. Jacobson, S.T.P.R. Tomi II.
Fourth Edition, 1863. 8vo. 1l. 1s.</p>
<p>Socrates' Ecclesiastical History, according to the Text of
Hussey, with an Introduction by William Bright, D.D. 1878. Crown 8vo.
7s. 6d.</p>

<pb n="7"/>
<p>ECCLESIASTICAL HISTORY, BIOGRAPHY, c.</p>
<p>Ancient Liturgy of the Church of England, according to the
uses of Saram, York, Hereford, and Bangor, and the Roman Liturgy arranged
in parallel columns, with preface and notes. By William Maskell, M.A.
Third Edition. 1882. 8vo. 15s.</p>
<p>Baedae Historia Ecclesiastica. Edited, with English Notes,
by G. Η. Moberly, Μ.Α. 1881. Crown 8vo. 10s. 6d.</p>
<p>Bright (W.). Chapters of Early English Church History.
1878. 8vO. 12s.</p>
<p>Burnets History of the Reformation of tJie Church of England.
Α new Edition. Carefully revised, and the Records collated with the originals,
by Ν. Pocock, ΜΑ. 7 vols. 1865. 8vo. Frice redttced to 1l. 10s.</p>
<p>Councils and Ecclesiastical Documents relatifig to Great Britain
and Ireland. Edited, after Spelman and Wilkins, by Α. W. Haddan, B.D.,
and W. Stubbs, M.A. Vols. I. and III. 1869-71. Medium 8vo. each 1l.</p>
<p>Vol. II. Part I. 1873. Medium 8vo. ioj. dd.</p>
<p>Vol. II. Partll. 1878. Church of Ireland; Memorials of St. Patrick.
StiflF covers, 3s. 6d.</p>
<p>Hammond (C. E.) Liturgies, Eastern and Western. Edited,
with Introduction, Notes, and a Liturgical Glossary. 1878. Crown 8vo.
10s. 6d.</p>
<p>An Appendix to the above. 1879. Crown 8vo. paper covers, is. 6d.</p>
<p>John, Bishop of Ephesus. The Third Part of his Ecclesiastical
History. [In Syriac.] Now first edited by William Cureton, M.A.
1853. 4to. 1l. 12s.</p>
<p>— Translated by R. Payne Smith, Μ.Α. 1860. 8vo. 10s.</p>
<p>Leofric Missal, The, as used in the Cathedral of Exeter
during the Episcopate of its first Bishop, A.D. 1050-1072; together with some
Account of the Red Book of Derby, the Missal of Robert of Jumieges, and a
few other early MS. Service Books of the English Church. Edited, with Introduction
and Notes, by F. Ε. Warren, B.D. 4to. half morocco, 35a.</p>
<p>Monumenta Ritualia Ecclesiae Anglicanae. The occasional
Offices of the Church of England according to the old use of Salisbury, the
Prymer in English, and other prayers and forms, with dissertations and notes.
By William Maskell, M.A. Second Edition. 1882. 3 vols. 8vo. 2l. 10s.</p>
<p>Records of tlie Reformation. The Divorce, 1527-1533. Mostly
now for the first time printed from MSS. in the British Museum and other
libraries. Collected and arranged by N. Pocock, M.A. 1870. 2 vols. 8vo.
1l. 16s.</p>

<pb n="8"/>
<p>Shirley (W. W.). Some Account of the Church in the Apostolic
Age. Second Edition, 1874. fcap. 8vo. 35. 6d.</p>
<p>Stubbs (W.). Registrum Sacrum Anglicanum. An attempt
to exhibit the course of Episcopal Succession in England. 1858. Small 4to.
8s. 6d.</p>
<p>Warren (F. E.). Liturgy and Ritual of the Celtic Church.
1881. 8vo. 14s.</p>
<p>ENGLISH THEOLOGY.</p>
<p>Butler᾿s Works, with an Index to the Analogy. 2 vols. 1874.
8vo. iis.</p>
<p>Also separately,</p>
<p>Sermons, 5s. 6d. Analogy of Religion, 5s. 6d.</p>
<p>Greswells Harmonia Evangelica. Fifth Edition. 8vo. 1855.
9s. 6d.</p>
<p>Heurtley's Harmonia Symbolica: Creeds of the Western
Church. 1858. 8vo. 6s. 6d.</p>
<p>Homilies appohtted to be read in Churches. Edited by
J. Griffiths, M.A. 1859. 8vo. 7s. 6d.</p>
<p>Hookers Works, with his life by Walton, arranged by John
Keble, M.A. Sixth Edition, 1874. 3 vols. 8vo. 1l. 1l. 11s. 6d.</p>
<p>— the text as arranged by John Keble, M.A. 2 vols.
1875. 8vo. 11s.</p>
<p>Fewel's Works. Edited by R. W. Jelf, D.D. 8 vols. 1848.
8vo. 1l. 10s.</p>
<p>Pearson's Exposition of the Creed. Revised and corrected by
E. Burton, D.D. Sixth Edition, 1877. 8vo. 10s. 6d.</p>
<p>Waterland's Review of the Doctrine of the Eucharist, with
a Preface by the present Bishop of London. 1880. Crown 8vo, 6s. 6d.</p>
<p>— Works, with Life, by Bp. Van Mildert. A new Edition,
with copious Indexes. 6 vols. 1856. 8vo. 2l. 11s.</p>
<p>Wheatly's Illustration of the Book of Common Prayer. Α new
Edition, 1846. 8vo. 5s.</p>
<p>Wyclif. A Catalogue of the Original Works of John Wyclif
by W. W. Shirley, D.D. 1865. 8vo. 3s. 6d.</p>
<p>— Select English Works. By T. Arnold, M.A. 3 vols.
1869-1871 8vo. Price reduced to 1l. 1s.</p>
<p>Trialogus. With the Supplement now first edited.
By Gotthard Lechler. 1869. 8vo. Price reduced to 7s.</p>

<pb n="9"/>
<p>HISTORICAL AND DOCUMENTARY WORKS.</p>
<p>British Barrows, a Record of the Examination of Sepulchral
Mounds in various parts of England. By William Greenwell, Μ.Α., F.S.A.
Together with Description of Figures of Skulls, General Remarks on Prehistoric
Crania, and an Appendix by George RoUeston, M.D., F.R.S. 1877.
Medium 8vo. 25s.</p>
<p>Britton. A Treatise upon the Conimon Law of England,
composed by order of King Edward I. The French Text carefuUy revised,
with an English Translation, Introduction, and Notes, by F. M. Nichols, ΜΑ.
2 vols. 1865. Royal Svo. 1l. 16s.</p>
<p>Clarendon's History of the Rebellion and Civil Wars in
England. 7 vols. 1839. 18mo. 1l. 1s.</p>
<p>Clarendons History of tJie RebelUon and Civil Wars in
England. Also his Life, written by himself, in which is included a Continuation
of his History of the Grand Rebellion. With copious Indexes.
In one volume, royal 8vo. 1842. 1l. 2s.</p>
<p>Clintons Epitome of the Fasti Hellenici. 185 1. 8vo. 6s. 6d.</p>
<p>— Epitome of the Fasti Romani. 1854. 8vo. 75s.</p>
<p>Corpus Poeticvm Boreale. The Poetry of the Old Northern
Tongue, from the Earliest Times to the Thirteenth Century. Edited, classified,
and translated. with Introduction, Excursus, and Notes, by Gudbrand
Vigfusson, Μ.Α., and F. York Powell, Μ.Α. 2 vols. 1883. 8vo. 42s.</p>
<p>Freeman [E. A.). History of the Norman Conquest of Eng-
land ; its Causes and Results. In Six Volumes. 8vo. 5l. 9s. 6d.</p>
<p>Vols. I-II together, 3rd edition, 1877. 1l. 16s.</p>
<p>Vol. III, 2nd edition, 1874. 1l. 1s.</p>
<p>Vol. IV, 2nd edition, 1875. 1l. 1s.</p>
<p>Vol. V, 1876. 1l. 1s.</p>
<p>Vol. VI. Index. 1879. 8vo. 10s. 6d.</p>
<p>Freeman (E A.). The Reign of William Rufus and the
Accession of Henry the First. 2 vols. 8vo. 1l. 16s.</p>
<p>Gascoigne's Theological Dictionary “Liber Veritatum”):
Selected Passages, illustrating the condition of Church and State, 1403-1458.
With an Introduction by James E. Thorold Rogers, M.P. Small 4to. 10s. 6d.</p>
<p>Magna Carta, a careful Reprint. Edited by W. Stubbs, M.A.
1879. 4to. stitched, 1s.</p>
<p>Passio et Miracula Beati Olaui. Edited from a Twelfth-
Century MS. in the Library of Corpus Christi College, Oxford, with an Introduction
and Notes, by Frederick Metcalfe, M.A. Small 4to. stiff covers, 6s.</p>

<pb n="10"/>
<p>Protests of the Lords, including those which have been expunged,
from 1624 to 1874; with Historical Introductions. Edited by James
E. Thorold Rogers, M.A. 1875. 3vols. 8vo. 2l. 2s.</p>
<p>Rogers (F E. T.). History of Agriculture and Prices in
England, A.D. 1259-1793.</p>
<p>Vols. I and II (i 259-1400). 1866. Svo. 2l. 2s.</p>
<p>Vols. III and IV (1401-1582). 1882. 8vo. 2l. 10s.</p>
<p>Saxon Chronicles (Two of The) parallel, with
Extracts from the Others. Edited, with Introduction, Notes, and a Glowsarial
Index, by J. Earle, M.A. 1865. 8vo. 16s.</p>
<p>Sturlunga Saga, including the Islendinga Saga of Lawman
Sturla Thordsson and other works. Edited by Dr. Gudbrand Vigfusson.
In 2 vols. 1878. 8vo. 2l. 2s.</p>
<p>Statutes madefor the University of Oxford, andfor the Colleges
and Halls therein, by the University of Oxford Commissioners. 1882. 8vo.
12s. 6d.</p>
<p>Also separately,</p>
<p>Statutes made for the University. 2s.</p>
<p>— the Colleges. is. each.</p>
<p>Statuta Universitatis Oxoniensis. 1883. 8vo. 5s.</p>
<p>The Studenfs Handbook to the University and Colleges of
Oxford. Seventh Edition. 1883, Extra fcap. 8vo. 2s. dd.</p>
<p>MATHEMATICS, PHYSICAL SCIENCE, &amp;c.</p>
<p>Aclatid (H W., M.D., F.R.S.). Synopsis of the Pathological
Series in the Oxford Museum. 1867. 8vo. 2s. 6d.</p>
<p>Astronomical Observations made at the University Observatory,
Oxford, under the direction of C. Pritchard, M.A. No. 1. 1878.
Royal 8vo. paper covers, 3s. dd.</p>
<p>Müller (f.) On certain Variations in the Vocal Organs of
the Passeres that have hitherto escaped notice. Translated by F. J. Bell, B.A.,
and edited, with an Appendix, by A. H. Garrod, M.A., F.R.S. With Plates.
1878. 4to. paper covers, 7s. 6d.</p>
<p>Phillips (fon, M.A., F.RS.). Geology of Oxford and the
Valleyofthe of the Thames. 1871. 8vo. 21s.</p>
<p>— Vesuvius. 1869. Crown 8vo. 10s. 6d.</p>

<pb n="11"/>
<p>Price (Bartholomew, M.A., F.R.S.). Treatise on Infijiitesimal
Calculus.</p>
<p>Vol. I. Differential Calculus. Second Edition. 8vo. 14s. 6d.</p>
<p>Vol. II. Integral Calculus, Calculus of Variations, and Differential Equations.
Second Edition, 1865. 8vo. 18s.</p>
<p>Vol. III. Statics, including Attractions; Dynamics of a Material Particle.
Second Edition, 1868. 8vo. 16s.</p>
<p>Vol. IV. Dynamics of Material Systems; together with a chapter on Theoretical
Dynamics, byW. F. Donkin, M.A., F.R.S. 1862. 8vo. 16s.</p>
<p>Rigaud's Correspondence of Scientific Men of the 17th Century,
with Table of Contents by Α. de Morgan, and Index by the Rev. J. Rigaud,
M.A. 2 vols. 1841-4186. 8vo. 18s. 6d.</p>
<p>Sachs' Text-Book of Botany, Morphological and Physiological.
A New Edition. Translated by S. Η. Vines, M.A. 1882. Royal 8vo., half
morocco, 1l. 11s. 6d.</p>
<p>Westwood (y. (f M.A., F.R.S.). Thesaurus Entomologicus
Hcpeianus, or a Description of the rarest Insects in the CoUection given to
the University by the Rev. WiUiam Hope. With 40 Plates. 1874. Small
folio, half morocco, 7l. 10s.</p>
<p>Dbe Sacred Books of the East.</p>
<p>TRANSLATED BY NARIOUS ORIENTAL SCHOLARS, AND EDITED BY
F. MAX ÜLLER.</p>
<p>[Demy 8vo. cloth.]</p>
<p>Vol. I. The Upanishads. Translated by F. Max Miiller.
Part I. The ândogya-upanishad, The Talavakara-upanishad, The Aitareya-
arawyaka, The Kaushitaki-brahmawa-upanishad, and The âgasaneyi-samhitâupanished.
10s. 6d.</p>
<p>Vol. II. The Sacred Laws of the Aryas, as taught in the
Schools of Apastamba, Gautama, âsishtha, and Baudhayana. Translated by
Prof. Georg Biihler. Part I. Apastamba and Gautama. 10s. 6d.</p>
<p>Vol. III. The Sacred Books of China. The Texts of Confucianism.
Translated by James Legge. Part I. The Shu King, The Religius
portions of the Shih King, and The Hsiao King. 1 12s. 6d.</p>
<p>Vol. IV. The Zend-Avesta. Translated by James Darmesteter.
Part I. The Vendîdâd. 10s. 6d.</p>

<pb n="12"/>
<p>Vol. V. The Pahlavi Texts. Translated by Ε. W. West.
Part I. The Bundahis, Bahman Yast, and Shâgast lâ-shâgast. 12s.</p>
<p>Vols. VI and IX. The Qur'ân. Parts I and II. Translated
by Ε. Η. Palmer. 21s.</p>
<p>Vol. VII. The Institutes of Vishnu. Translated by Julius
Jolly. 10s. 6d.</p>
<p>Vol. VIII. The Bhagavadgîtâ, with The Sanatsugâtîga,
The Angugîtâ. Translated by Kâshinâth Trimbak Telang. 10s. 6d.
Vol. Χ. The Dhammapada, translated from Pali by F. Max
Müller; and The Sutta-Nipâta, translated from Pâli by V. Fausböll; being
Canonical Books of the Buddhists. 10s. 6d.</p>
<p>Vol. XI. Buddhist Suttas. Translated from Pâli by T. W.
Rhys Davids. I. The Mahâparinibbâna Suttanta; 2. The Dhamma-kakkappavattana
Sutta; 3. The Tevigga Suttanta ; 4. The Akahkheyya Sutta ;
5. The Aetokhila Sutta; 6. The Mahâ-sudassana Suttanta; 7. The Sabbâsava
Sutta. 10s. 6d.</p>
<p>Vol. XII. The Satapatha-Brâhmana, according to the
of the Madhyandina School. Translated by Julius Eggeling. Part I.
Books I and II. 12s. 6d.</p>
<p>Vol. XIII. Vinaya Texts. Translated from the Pali by
T. W. Rhys Davids and Hermann Oldenberg. Part I. The Patimokkha.
The Mahâvagga, I-IV. 10s. 6d.</p>
<p>Vol. XIV. The Sacred Laws of the Ârgas, as taught in the
Schools of Apastamba, Gautama, Vâsishtha and Baudhâgana.
by Georg Bühler. Part II. VasishMa and Baudhâgana. 10s. 6d.</p>
<p>Vol. XV. The Upanishads. Translated by F. Max Müller.
Part II. The KaMa-upanishad, The Mundaka-upanishad, The Taittirîgakauranishad,
The Brzhadarawyaka-upanishad, The Svetasnatara-upanishad, The
Prasña-upanishad, and The Maitrâgana-Brâhmana-upanishad. 10s.</p>
<p>Vol. XVI. The Sacred Books of China. The Texts of Confucianism.
Translated by James Legge. Part II. The Yî King. 10s.</p>
<p>Vol. XVII. Vinaya Texts. Translated from the Pâli by
T. W. Rhys Davids and Hermann Oldenberg. Part II. The Mahâvagga,
V-X. The Kullavagga, I-III. 10s. 6d.</p>
<p>Vol. XVIII. Pahlavi Texts. Translated by Ε. W. West.
Part II. The Dâdistân-î Dînîk and The Epistles of Mânûskîhar. 12s.</p>
<p>Vol. ΧΙΧ. The Fo-sho-hing-tsan-king. Α Life of Buddha
by Asvaghosha Bodhisattva, translated from Sanskrit into Chinese by Dharmaradsha,
A.D. 420, and from Chinese into English by Samuel Beal. 10s. 6d.</p>

<pb n="13"/>
<p>Vol. XXI. The Saddharma-pundarîka, or the Lotus of
True Law. Translated by Η. Kem. 6d.</p>
<p>Vol. XXIII. The The Zend-Avesta. Part II. The Sîrôzahs,
Yasts, and Nyâgis. Translated by James Darmesteter. 10s. dd.</p>
<p>The following Voltunes are in the Press :—</p>
<p>Vol. XX. Vinaya Texts. Translated from the Pâli by T. W.
Rhys Davids and Hermann Oldenberg. Part UI. The Aullavagga, I-IV.</p>
<p>Vol. XXII. The Âkârânga Sûtra. Translated by H. Jacobi.</p>
<p>Vol. XXIV. Pahlavi Texts. Translated by E. W. West.
Part III. Dînâ-î î Maînôg-î Khîrad, Shikand-gu-mânî and</p>
<p>Second Series.</p>
<p>Vol. XXV. Manu. Translated by Georg Bühler. Part I.</p>
<p>Vol. XXVI. Manu. Translated by Georg Bühler.
Part II.</p>
<p>Dnecdota Oxoniensia:</p>
<p>[ Small 4to.]</p>
<p>Classical Series. I. i. The English Manuscripts of the Nicomachean
Ethics, described in relation to Bekker's Manuscripts and other
Sources. By J. A. Stewart. M.A. 3s. 6d.</p>
<p>— I. ii. Nonius Marcellus, de Compendiosa Doctrina,
Harleian MS. 2719. Collated by J. H. Onions, M.A. 3s. 6d.</p>
<p>— I. iii. Aristotle's Physics. Book VII. CoIIation of
various MSS.; with an Introduction by R. Shute, MA. 2s.</p>
<p>I. iv. Bentleys Plautine Emendations. From his copy
of Gronovius. By E. A. Sonnenschein, M.A. 2s. 6d.</p>
<p>Semitic Series. I. i. Commentary on Ezra and Nehemiah.
By Rabbi Saadiah. Edited by Η. J. Mathews, M.A. 3s. 6d.</p>
<p>Aryan Series. I. i. Buddhist Texts from Japan. Edited
by F. Max Müller, M.A. 3s. 6d.</p>
<p>— I. ii. Sukhâuatî- Vgûha. Description of
Land of Bliss. Edited by F. Max Müller, M.A., and Bunyiu Nanjio. 7s. 6d.</p>
<p>Mediaeval and Modern Series. I. i. Sinonoma Bartholomei;
A Glossary from a Fourteenth-Century MS. in the Library of Pembroke
CoUege, Oxford. Edited by J. L. G. Mowat, M.A. is. 6d.</p>
<p>— I. iii. The Saltair Na Rann. Α CoIIection of Early
Middle Irish Poems. Edited from a MS. in the Bodleian Library by Whitley
Stokes, LL.D. 7s. 6d.</p>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="2">
<pb n="14"/>
<head>Clarendon Press Series</head>
<p>I. ENGLISH.</p>
<p>A First Reading Book. By Marie Eichens of Berlin; and
edited by Anne J. Clough. Extra fcap. 8vo. stiff covers, 4d.</p>
<p>Oxford Reading Book, Part Ι. For Little Children. Extra
fcap. 8vo. stiff covers, 6d.</p>
<p>Oxford Reading Book, Part II. For Junior Classes. Extra
fcap. 8vo. stiff covers, 6d.</p>
<p>An Elementary English Grammar and Exercise Book. By
Ο. W. Tancock, M.A. Second Edition. Extra fcap. 8vo. 1s. 6d.</p>
<p>An English Grammar and Readijtg Book, for Lower Forms
in Classical Schools. By O. W. Tancock, M.A. Fourth Edition. Extra
fcap. 8vo. 3s. 6d.</p>
<p>Typical Selections from the hest English Writers, with Introductory
Notices. Second Edition. In Two Volumes. Extra fcap. 8vo.
3s. 6d. each.</p>
<p>Vol. I. Latimer to Berkeley. Vol. II. Pope to Macaulay.</p>
<p>Shairp (f. C., LL.D.). Aspects of Poetry ; being Lectures
delivered at Oxford. Crown 8vo. 10s. 6d.</p>
<p>A Book for the Beginner in Anglo-Saxon. By John Earle,
Μ.Α. Second Edition. Extra fcap. 8vo. 2s. 6d.</p>
<p>An Anglo-Saxon Reader. In Prose and Verse. With Grammatical
Introduction, Notes, and Glossary. By Henry Sweet, M.A. Fourth
Edition, Revised and Enlarged. Extra fcap. 8vo. 8s. 6d.</p>
<p>An Anglo-Saxon Primer, with Grammar, Notes, and Glossary.
By the same Author. Extra fcap. 8vo. 2s, 6d.</p>
<p>The Philology of the English Tongue. By J. Earle, M.A.
Third Edition. Extra fcap. 8vo. ν. 6d.</p>
<p>A Handbook of Phonetics, including a Popular Exposition of
the Principles of Spelling Reform. By Henry Sweet, M.A. Extra fcap. 8vo,
4s. 6d.</p>
<p>The Ormulum; with the Notes and Glossary of Dr. R. M.
White. Edited by R. Holt, M.A. 1878. 2 vols. Extra fcap. 8vo. 21s.</p>

<pb n="15"/>
<p>English Plant Names from the Tenth to the Fifteenth
Centnry. By J. Earle, M.A. Small fcap. 8vo. 55.</p>
<p>Specimens of Early English. A Nevv and Revised Edition.
With Introduction, Notes, and Glossarial Index. By R. Morris, LL.D., and
W. W. Skeat, M.A.</p>
<p>Part I. From Old English Homilies to King Hom (A.D. 1150 to A.D. 1300).
Extra fcap. 8vo. 9s.</p>
<p>Part II. From Robert of Gloncester to Gower (A.D. 1298 to A.D. 1393).
Second Edition. Extra fcap. 8vo. 7s. 6d.</p>
<p>Specimens of English Literature, from the ‘ Ploughmans
Crede' to the ‘ Shepheardes Calender' (A.D. 1394 to A.D. 1579). With
Notes, and Glossarial Index. By W. W. Skeat, M A. Extra fcap.
8vo. 7s. 6d.</p>
<p>The Vision of William concerning Piers the Plowman, by
William Langland. Edited, with Notes, by W, W. Skeat, M.A. Third
Edition. Extra fcap. 8vo. 4s. 6d.</p>
<p>Chaucer. I. The Prologue to the Canterbury Tales; the
Knightes Tale; The Nonne Prestes Tale. Edited by R. Morris, Editor of
Specimens of Early English, &amp;c., &amp;c. Fifty-first Thousand. Extra fcap. 8vo.
2s. 6d.</p>
<p>— II. The Prioresses Tale; Sir Thopas; The Monkes
Tale; The Clerkes Tale; The Squieres Tale, c. Edited by W. W.
M.A. Second Edition. Extra fcap. 8vo. 4s. 6d.</p>
<p>— III. The Tale of the man of Lawe ; The Pardoneres
Tale; The Second Nonnes Tale; The Chanouns Yemannes Tale. By the
same Editor. Second Edition. Extra fcap. 8vo. 4s. 6d.</p>
<p>Spenser's Faery Queene. Books I and II. Designed chiefly
for the use of Schools. With Intioduction, Notes, and Glossary. By G. W.
Kitchin, M.A.</p>
<p>Book I. Tenth Edition. Extra fcap. 8vo. 2s. 6d.</p>
<p>Book 11. Sixth Edition. Extra fcap. 8vo. 2s. 6d.</p>
<p>Hooker. Ecclesiastical Polity, Book I. Edited by R. W.
Church, M.A. Second Edition. Extra fcap. 8vo. 2s.</p>
<p>Marlowe and Greene. Marlowe's Tragical History of Dr.
Faustus, and Greene's s Honourable History of Friar Baton and Friar Bungay.
Edited by A. W. Ward, M.A. 1878. Extra fcap. 8vo. 5s. 6d.</p>
<p>Marlowe. Edward II. With Introduction, Notes, c. By
O. W. Tancock, M.A. Extra fcap. 8vo. 3s.</p>

<pb n="16"/>
<p>Shakespeare. Select Plays. Edited by W. G. Clark, M.A.,
and W. Aldis Wright, M.A. Extra fcap. 8vo. tiff covers.</p>
<p>I. The Merchant of Venice. 1s.</p>
<p>II. Richard the Second. 1s. 6d.</p>
<p>III. Macbeth. 1s. 6d.</p>
<p>IV. Hamlet. 2s.</p>
<p>— Edited by W. Aldis Wright, M.A. Extra fcap. 8vo.
stiff covers.</p>
<p>V. The Tempest. 1s. 6d.</p>
<p>VI. As You Like It. 1s. 6d.</p>
<p>VII. Julius Caesar. 2s.</p>
<p>VIII. Richard the Third. 2s. 6d.</p>
<p>IX. King Lear. 1s. 6d.</p>
<p>X. A Midsummer Nighfs Dream. 1s. 6d.</p>
<p>XI. Coriolanus. 2s. 6d.</p>
<p>XII. Henry the Fifth. 2s.</p>
<p>XIII. Twelfth Night. In tbe Press.</p>
<p>Bacon. I. Advancement of Learning. Edited by W. Aldis
Wright, M.A. Second Edition. Extra fcap. 8vo. 4s. 6d.</p>
<p>— II. The Essays. With Introduction and Notes. By
J. R. Thursfield, M.A. In Preparation.</p>
<p>Milton. I. Areopagitica. With Introduction and Notes. By
J. W. Hales, M.A. Third Edition, Extra fcap. 8vo. 3s.</p>
<p>— II. Poems. Edited by R. C. Browne, M.A. 2 vols.
Fifth Edition. Extra fcap. 8vo. 6s. 6d.</p>
<p>Sold separately, Vol. I. ι. 4s., Vol. II. 3s.</p>
<p>In paper covers : —</p>
<p>Lycidas, id. ’Allegro, id. II Penseroso, 4d. Comus, 6d.</p>
<p>Samson Agonistes, 6d.</p>
<p>III. Samson Agonistes. Edited with Introduction and
Notes by John Churton CoUins. Extra fcap. 8vo. stiff covers, 1s.</p>
<p>Bunyan. I. The Pilgrinis Progress, Grace Abonnding, Relation
tion of the Imprisonment of Mr.John Bunyan. Edited, with Biographical
Introduction and Notes, by E. Venables, M.A. 1879. Extra fcap. 8vo. 5s.</p>
<p>II. Holy War, s—c Edited by E. Venables, M.A.
In the Press.</p>

<pb n="17"/>
<p>Dryden. Select Poems. Stanzas on the Death of Oliver
Cromwell; Astrsea Redux; Aimus Mirabilis; Absalom and Achitophel;
Religio Laici; The Hind and the Panther. Edited by W. D. Christie, M.A.
Second Edition. Extra fcap. 8vo. 3s. 6d.</p>
<p>Locke's Condtict of the Understanding. Edited, with Introduction,
Notes, c., by T. Fowler, M.A. Second Edition. Extra fcap. 8vo. 2s.</p>
<p>Addison. Selections froiH Papers in the Spectator. With
Notes. By T. Amold, M.A. Extra fcap. 8vo. 4s. 6d.</p>
<p>Pope. With Introduction and Notes. By Mark Pattison, B.D.</p>
<p>— I. Essay on Man. Sixth Edition. Extra fcap. 8vo.
1s. 6d.</p>
<p>— II. Satires and Epistles. Second Edition. Extra fcap.
8vo. 2s.</p>
<p>Parnell. The Hermit. Paper covers, 2d.</p>
<p>fohnson. I. Rasselas; Lives of Pope and Dryden. Edited
by Alfred Milnes, B.A. (London). Extra fcap. 8vo. 4s. 6d.</p>
<p>— II. Vanity of Human Wishes. With Notes, by Ε. J.
Payne, M.A. Paper covers, 4d.</p>
<p>Gray. Elegy and Ode on Eton College. Paper covers, 2d.</p>
<p>Goldsmith. The Deserted Village. Paper covers, 2d.</p>
<p>Cowper. Edited, with Life, Introductions, and Notes, by
H. T. Griffith, B.A.</p>
<p>— I. The Didactic Poems of 1782, with Selections from the
Minor Pieces, A.D. —1783. Extra fcap. 8vo. 3s.</p>
<p>— II. The Task, with Tirocininm, and Selections from the
Minor Poems, A.D. —1799. Second Edition. Extra fcap. 8vo.</p>
<p>Burke. Select Works. Edited, with Introduction and Notes,
by Ε. J. Payne, M.A.</p>
<p>— I. Thoughts on the Present Discontents; the two Speeches
on America. Second Edition. Extra fcap. 8vo. 4s. 6d.</p>
<p>— II. Reflections on the French Revolution. Second Edition.
Extra fcap. 8vo. 5s.</p>
<p>III. Four Letters on the Proposals for Peace with the
Regicide Directory of France. Second Edition, Extra fcap. 8vo. 5s.</p>

<pb n="18"/>
<p>Keats. Hyperion, Book I. With Notes by W. T. Arnold, B.A.
Paper covers, 4d.</p>
<p>Scott. Lay of the Last Minstrel. Introduction and Canto I,
with Preface and Notes by W. Minto, M.A. Paper covers, dd.</p>
<p>II. LATIN.</p>
<p>An Elementary Latin Grammar. By John B. Allen, M.A.
Third Edition, Revised and Corrected. Extra fcap. 8vo. 2s. 6d.</p>
<p>A First Latin Exercise Book. By the same Author. Fourth
Edition. Extra fcap. 8vo. 2s. 6d.</p>
<p>A Second Latin Exercise Book. By the same Author. In
the Press.</p>
<p>Reddenda Minora, or Easy Passages, Latin and Greek, for
Unseen Translation. For the use of Lower Forms. Composed and selected
by C. S. Jerram, M.A. Extra fcap. u. 6d.</p>
<p>Anglice Reddetida, or Easy Extracts, Latin and Greek, for
Unseen Translation. By C. S. Jerram, M.A. Third Edition, Revised and
Enlarged. Extra fcap. 8vo. 2s. 6d.</p>
<p>Passages for Translation into Latin. For the use of Passmen
and others. Selected by J. Y. Sargent, M.A. Fifth Edition. Extra fcap.
8vo. 2s. 6d.</p>
<p>First Latin Reader. By T. J. Nunns, M.A. Third Edition.
Extra fcap. 8vo. 2s.</p>
<p>Caesar. The Commentaries (for Schools). With Notes and
Maps. By Charles E. Moberly, M.A.</p>
<p>Part I. The Gallic War. Second Edition. Extra fcap. 8vo. 4s. 6d.</p>
<p>Part II. The Civil War. Extra fcap. 8vo 35. 6d.</p>
<p>The Civil War. Book I. Second Edition. Extra fcap. 8vo. 2s.</p>
<p>Cicero. Selection of interesting and descriptive passages. With
Notes. By Henry VValford, M.A. In three Parts. Extra fcap. 8vo. 4s. 6d.</p>
<p>Each Part separately, limp, 1s. 6d.</p>
<p>Part I. Anecdotes from Grecian and Roman History. Third Edition.</p>
<p>Part II. Omens and Dreams: Beauties of Nature. Third Editioa,</p>
<p>Part III. Rome's Rule of her Provinces. Third Edition.</p>
<p>— De Senectute and De Amicitia. With Notes. By W.
Heslop, M.A. Extra fcap. 8vo. 2s. Just Published.</p>

<pb n="19"/>
<p>Cicero. Selected Letters (for Schools). With Notes. By the
late C. Ε. Prichard, ΜΑ., and E. R. Bernard, M.A. Second Edition.
Extra fcap. 8vo. 3s.</p>
<p>— Select Orations (for Schools). In Verrem Ι. De Imperio
Gn. Pompeii. Pro Archia. Philippica ΙΧ. With Introduction and Notes by
J. R. King, M.A. Second Edition. Extra fcap. 8vo. 2s. 6d.</p>
<p>Cornelius Nepos. With Notes. By Oscar Browning, M.A.
Second Edition. Extra fcap. 8vo. 2s. 6d.</p>
<p>Livy. Selections (for Schools). With Notes and Maps. By
Η. Lee-Wamer, M.A. Extra fcap. 8vo. In Parts, limp, each 1s. 6d.</p>
<p>Part I. The Caudine Disaster.</p>
<p>Part II, Hannibars Campain in Italy.</p>
<p>Part III. The Macedonian War.</p>
<p>Livy. Books V-VII. With Introduction and Notes. By
A. R. Cluer, B.A. Extra fcap. 8vo. 3s. 6d.</p>
<p>Ovid. Selections for the use of Schools. With Introductions
and Notes, and an Appendix on the Roman Calendar. By W. Ramsay, M.A.
Edited by G. G. Ramsay, Μ.Α. Second Edition. Extra fcap. 8vo. 5s. 6d.</p>
<p>Pliny. Selected Letters (for Schools). With Notes. By the
late C. Ε. Prichard, Μ.Α., and Ε. R. Bernard, M.A. Second Edition. Extra
fcap. 8vo. 3s.</p>
<p>Catulli Veronensis Liber. Iterum recognovit, appatatum
criticur
8vo. 10s.</p>
<p>— A Commentary on Catullus. By Robinson Ellis, M.A.
1876. Demy 8vo, 16s.</p>
<p>— Veronensis Carmina Selectd, secundum recognitionem
Robinson Ellis, A.M. Extra fcap, 8vo. 3s. 6d.</p>
<p>Cicero de Oratore. With Introduction and Notes. By Α. S.
Wilkins, M.A.</p>
<p>Bookl, 1879. 8vo. 6s. Bookll. 1881. 8vo. 5s.</p>
<p>— Philippic Orations. With Notes, By J. R. King, M.A.
Second Edition. 1879. 8vo. 10s. 6d.</p>
<p>— Select Letters. With EngHsh Introductions, Notes, and
Appendices. By Albert Watson, M.A. Third Edition. 1881. Demy 8vo. Demy</p>

<pb n="20"/>
<p>Cicero. Select Letters. Text. By the same Editor. Second
Edition. Extra fcap. 8vo. 4s.</p>
<p>Cicero pro Cluentio. With Introduction and Notes. By W.
Ramsay, M.A. Edited by G. G. Ramsay, M.A. Second Edition. Extra fcap.
8vo. 3s. 6d.</p>
<p>Horace. With a Commentary. Volume I. The Odes, Carmen
Seculare, and Epodes. By Edward C. Wickham, Μ.Α. Second Edition.
1877. Demy 8vo. 12s.</p>
<p>— A reprint of the above, in a size suitable for the use
of Schools. Extra fcap. 8vo. 5s. 6d.</p>
<p>Liny, Book I. With Introduction, Historical Examination,
and Notes. By J. R. Seeley, Μ.Α. Second Edition. 1881. 8vo. 6s.</p>
<p>Ovid. P. Ovidii Nasonis Ibis. Ex Novis Codicibus edidit,
Scholia Vetera Commentarium cum Prolegomenis Appendice Indice addidit,
R. Ellis, A.M. Demy 8vo. 10s. 6d.</p>
<p>Persius. The Satires. With a Translation and Commentary.
By John Conington, Μ.Α. Edited by Henry Nettleship, M.A. Second
Edition. 1874. 8vo. 7s. 6d.</p>
<p>Plautus. The Trinummus. With Notes and Introductions.
Intended for the Higher Forms of Public Schools. By C. E. Freeman, M.A.,
and Α. Sloman, M.A. Extra fcap. 8vo. 3s.</p>
<p>Sallust. With Introduction and Notes. By W. W. Capes,
Μ.Α. In the Press.</p>
<p>Tacitus. The Annals. Books I-VI. Edited, with Intro-
duction and Notes, by Η. Fumeaux, M.A. 8vo. 18s.</p>
<p>Virgil. With Introduction and Notes. By T. L. Papillon,
M.A. Two vols. crown 8vo. 10s. 6d.</p>
<p>Nettleship [H., M.A.). The Roman Satura: its original form
in connection with its literary development. 8vo. sewed, 1s.</p>
<p>Vergil: Suggestions Introdtictory to a Study of the Aeneid.
By Η. Nettleship, M.A. 8vo. sewed, 1s. 6d.</p>
<p>Ancient Lives of Vergil. With an Essay on the Poems of
Vergil, in connection with his Life and Times. By Η. Nettleship, M.A. 8vo.
sewed, 2s.</p>
<p>Papillon Τ. L., M.A.). A Manual of Comparative Philology.
Third Edition, Revised and Corrected. 1882. Crown 8vo. 6s.</p>
<p>Pinder (North, M.A.). Selections from the less known Latin
Poets. 1869. Demy 8vo. 15s.</p>

<pb n="21"/>
<p>Sellar (W. Y., M.A.). Roman Poets of the Augustan Age.
ViRGiL. By William Young Sellar, M.A., Professor of Humanity in the
University of Edinburgh, New Edition. 1883. Crown 8vo. 9s.</p>
<p>— Roman Poets of the Republic. New Edition, Revised
and Enlarged. 1881. 8vo. 14s.</p>
<p>Wordsworth (f., M.A.). Fragments and Specimens of Early
Latin. With Introductions and Notes. 1874. 8vo. 18s.</p>
<p>III. GREEK.</p>
<p>A Greek Primer, for the use of beginners in that Language.
By the RightRev. CharlesWordsworth, D.C.L. Seventh Edition. Extra fcap.
8vo. 1S. 6d.</p>
<p>Graecae Grammaticae Rudimenta in usum Scholarum. Austore
Carolo Wordsworth, D.C.L. Nineteenth Edition, 1882. 12mo. 4S.</p>
<p>A Greek-English Lexicon, abridged from Liddell and ’s
4to. edition, chiefly for the use of Schools. Twentieth Edition. Carefully
revised throughout. 1883. Square izmo. 12s. 6d.</p>
<p>Greek Verbs, Irregular and Defective; their forms, meaning,
and quantity; embracing all the Tenses used by Greek writers, with references
to the passages in whidi they are found. By W. Veitch. Fourth Edition.
Crown 8vo. 10s. 6d.</p>
<p>The Elements of Greek Accentuation (for Schools): abridged
from his larger work by Η. W. Chandler, M.A. Extra fcap. 8vo. 2s.</p>
<p>A Series of Graduated Greek Readers: —</p>
<p>First Greek Reader. By W. G. Rushbrooke, M.L. Second
Edition. Extra fcap. 8vo. 2s. 6d.</p>
<p>Second Greek Reader. By Α. M. Bell, M.A. Extra fcap.
8vo. 3s. 6d.</p>
<p>Fourth Greek Reader; being Specimens of Greek Dialects.
With Introductions and Notes. By W. W. Merry, M.A. Extra fcap. 8vo.
4s. 6d.</p>
<p>Fifth Greek Reader. Part L Selections from Greek Epic
and Dramatic Poetry, with Introductions and Notes. By Evelyn Abbott,
Μ.Α. Extra fcap. 8vo. 4s. 6d.</p>
<p>The Golden Treasury of Ancient Greek Poetry: being a Colection
of the finest passages in the Greek Classic Poets, with Introductory
Notices and Notes. By R. S. Wright, M.A. Extra fcap. 8vo. 8s. 6d.</p>

<pb n="22"/>
<p>A Golden Treasury of Greek Prose, being a Collection of the
finest passages in the principal Greek Prose Writers, with Introductory Notices
and Notes. By R. S. Wright, M.A., and J. Ε. L. Shadwell, M.A. Extra fcap.
8vo. 4s. 6d.</p>
<p>Aeschylus. Prometheus Bound (for Schools). With Introduction
and Notes, by Α. O. Prickard, M.A. Second Edition. Extra fcap. 8vo. 2s.</p>
<p>— Agamemnon. With Introduction and Notes, by Arthur
Sidgwick, M.A. Extra fcap. 8vo. 3s.</p>
<p>— Choephoroe. With Introduction and Notes by the same
Editor. In the Press.</p>
<p>Aristophanes. In Single Plays. Edited, with English Notes,
Introductions, c., by W. W. Merry, M.A. Extra fcap. 8vo.</p>
<p>I. The Clouds, Second Edition, 2s.</p>
<p>II. The Acharnians, 2s.</p>
<p>III. The Frogs, 2s.</p>
<p>Other Plays will foUow.</p>
<p>Cebes. Tabula. With Introduction and Notes. By C S.
Jerram, M.A. Extra fcap. 8vo. 2s. 6d.</p>
<p>Euripides. Alcestis (for Schools). By C. S. Jerram, M.A.
Extra fcap. 8vo. 2s. 6d.</p>
<p>— Helena. Edited, with Introduction, Notes, and Critical
Appendix, for Upper and Middle Forms. By C. S. Jerram, M.A. Extra
fcap. 8vo. 3s.</p>
<p>Herodotus, Selections from. Edited, with Introduction, Notes,
and a Map, by W. W. Merry, M.A. Extra fcap. 8vo. 2s. 6d.</p>
<p>Homer. Odyssey, Books —XII (for Schools). By W.
Merry, M.A. Twenty-seventh Thousand. Extra fcap. 8vo. 4s. 6d.</p>
<p>Book II, separately, 1s. 6d.</p>
<p>— Odyssey, Books —XXIN (for Schools). By the
same Editor. Second Edition. Extra fcap. 8vo. 5s.</p>
<p>— Iliad, Book I (for Schools). By D. B. Monro, M.A.
Second Edition. Extra fcap. 8vo. 2s.</p>
<p>— Iliad, Books I-XII (for Schools). By D. B. Monro, M.A.
Nearly ready.</p>
<p>— Iliad, Books VI and XXI. With Introduction and
Notes. By Herbert Hailstone, M.A. Extra fcap. 8vo. 1s. 6d. each.</p>

<pb n="23"/>
<p>Ltician. Vera Historia (for Schools). By C. S. Jerram,
Μ.Α. Second Edition. Extra fcap. 8vo. 1s. 6d.</p>
<p>Plato. Selections from the Dialognes [including the whole of
the Apology and Crito]. Witli Introduction and Notes by John Purves, M.A.,
and a Preface by the Rev. B. Jowett, Μ.Α. Extra fcap. Svo. 6s. 6d.</p>
<p>Sophocles. In Single Plays, with EngUsh Notes, c. By
Lewis Campbell, Μ.Α., and Evelyn Abbott, M.A. Extra fcap. 8vo. limp.</p>
<p>Oedipus TjTannus, Philoctetes. New and Revised Edition, zs. each.</p>
<p>Oedipus Coloneus, Antigone, 1s. 9d. each.</p>
<p>Ajax, Electra, Trachiniae, 2s. each.</p>
<p>— Oedipns Rex: Dindorfs Text, with Notes by the
present Bishop of St. ’s. Ext. fcap. 8vo. limp, 1s. 6d.</p>
<p>Theocritus (for Schools). With Notes. By H. Kynaston,
M.A. (late Snow). Third Edition. Extra fcap. 8vo. 4s. td.</p>
<p>Xenophon. Easy Selections. (for Junior Classes). With a
Vocabulary. Notes, and Map. By J. S. Phillpotts, B.C.L., and C. S. Jerram,
M.A. Third Edition. Extra fcap. 8vo. y. bd.</p>
<p>— Selections (for Schools). With Notes and Maps. By
J. S. Phillpotts, B.C.L. Fourth Edition. Extra fcap. 8vo. 3s. 6d.</p>
<p>— Anabasis, Book II. With Notes and Map. By C. S.
Jerram, Μ.Α. Extra fcap. 8vo. 2s.</p>
<p>— Cyropaedia, Books IV and V. With Introduction and
Notes by C. Bigg, D.D. Extra fcap. 8vo. 2s. 6d.</p>
<p>Aristotles Politics. By W. L. Newman, Μ.Α. [In preparation.]</p>
<p>Aristotelian Studies. I. On the Structure of the Seventh
Book of the Nicomachean Ethics. By J. C. Wilson, Μ.Α. 1879. Medium 8vo.
stiff, 5s.</p>
<p>Demosthenes and Aeschines. The Orations of Demosthenes
and Æschines on the Crown. With Introductory Essays and Notes. By
G. Α. Simcox, Μ.Α., and W. Η. Simcox, Μ.Α. 1873. 8vo. 12s.</p>
<p>Geldart [E. M., B.A.). The Modern Greek Language in its
relation to Ancient Greek, Extra fcap. 8vo. 4s. 6d.</p>
<p>Hicks (E. L., M.A.). A Manual of Greek Historical Inscriptions.
Demy 8vo. 10s. 6d.</p>

<pb n="24"/>
<p>Homer. Odyssey, Books I—XII. Edited with English
Appendices, etc. By W. W. Merry, M.A., and the late James Riddell, Μ.Α.
1876. Demy 8vo. 16s.</p>
<p>— A Grammar of ihe Homeric Dialect. By D. B. Monro,
Μ.Α. Demy 8vo. 10s. dd.</p>
<p>Sophocles. The Plays and Fragments. With English Notes
and Introductions, by Lewis Campbell, M.A. 2 vols.</p>
<p>Vol. I. Oedipus Tyrannus. Oedipus Coloneus, Antigone. Second
Edition. 1879. 8vo. 16s.</p>
<p>Vol. II. Ajax. Electra. Trachiniae. Philoctetes. Fragments. 1881.
8vo. 16s.</p>
<p>Sophocles. The Text of the Seven Plays. By the same
Editor. Extra fcap. 8vo. 4s. 6d.</p>
<p>IV. PRENCH AND ITALIAN.</p>
<p>Brachefs Etymological Dictionary of the French Language.
with a Preface on the Principles of French Etymology, Translated into
English by G. W. Kitchin, Μ.Α. Third Edition. Crown 8vo. 7s. 6d.</p>
<p>— Historical Grammar of the French Language. Translated
into English by G. W. Kitchin, M.A. Fourth Edition. Extra fcap,
8vo. 3s. 6d.</p>
<p>Woks by GEOBGE SAINTSBUKY, M.A.</p>
<p>Primer of French Literature. Extra fcap, 8vo. 2s.</p>
<p>Short History of French Literature. Crown 8vo. 10s. 6d.</p>
<p>Specimens of French Literature, from Villon to Hugo. Crown
8vo. 9s.</p>
<p>Corneille's Horace. Edited, with Introduction and Notes, by
George Saintsbury, M.A. Extra fcap. 8vo. 2s. 6d.</p>
<p>Molière's Les Pricieuses Ridicules. Edited, with Introduction
and Notes, by Andrew Lang, M.A. Extra fcap. 8vo. 1s. 6d.</p>
<p>Beaumarchais' Le Barbier de Siville. Edited, with Introduction
and Notes, by Austin Dobson. Extra fcap. 8vo. 2s. 6d.</p>
<p>Other Plays to follow.</p>
<p>L' Eloquence de la Chaire et de la Tribune Frangaises. Edited
by Paul Blouët, B.A. (Univ, Gallic). Vol. I, French Sacred Oratory.
Extra fcap. 8vo. 2s. 6d. Just Published.</p>

<pb n="25"/>
<p>Edited by QUSTAVE MASSON, B.A.</p>
<p>Corneille's Cinna, and ère's Les Femmes Savantes. With
Introduction and Notes. Extra fcap. 8vo. 2s. 6d.</p>
<p>Louis XIV and his Contemporaries; as described in Extracts
from the best Memoirs of the Seventeenth Century. With English Notes,
Genealogical Tables, c. Extra fcap. 8vo. 2s. 6d.</p>
<p>Maistre, Xavier de. Voyage autour de ma Chambre. Ourika,
by Madame de Duras; La Dot de Suzette, by Fieuée; Les Jumeaux de
l'Hôtel Corneille, Edmond About; Mesaventures d'um Ecolier, by Rodolphe
Tbpffer. Second Edition. Extra fcap. 8vo. 2s. 6d.</p>
<p>Molière's Les Fourberies de Scapin. With Voltaire's Life of
Moliere. Extra fcap, 8vo. stiff ἲς 1s. 6d.</p>
<p>Molière's Les Fourberies de Scapin, and Racines Athalie.
With ’s Life of Moliere. Extra fcap. 8vo. 2s. 6d.</p>
<p>Racine's Andromaque, and Corneilles Le Menteur. With
Louis Racine's Life of his Father, Extra fcap. 8vo. 2s. 6d.</p>
<p>Regnard's Le Joueur, and Brueys and Palaprafs Le Grotideur.
Extra fcap. 8vo. 2s. 6d.</p>
<p>Séuigné, Madame de, and fier chief Cofttemporaries, Selections
from the Corresponderue of. Intended more especially for Girls' Schools.
Extra fcap. 8vo. 3s.</p>
<p>Dante. Selections from the Infemo. With Introduction and
Notes. By H. B. Cotterill, B.A. Extra fcap. 8vo. 4s. 6d.</p>
<p>Tasso. La Gerusalemme Liberata. Cantos i, ii. With Introduction
and Notes. By the same Editor. Extra fcap. 8vo. is. 6d.</p>
<p>V. GERMAN.</p>
<p>GERMAN COURSE. By HEBMANN LANGE.</p>
<p>The Gertnans at Home; a Practical Introduction to German
Conversation, with an Appendix containing the Essentials of German Grammar.
Second Edition. 8vo. 2s. 6d.</p>
<p>The German Manual; a German Grammar, Reading Book,
and a Handbook of German Conversation. 8vo. 7s. 6d.</p>

<pb n="26"/>
<p>Grammar of the German Language. 8vo. 3s. 6d.
This ‘Grammar’ is a reprint of the Grammar contained in ' The German Manual,’
and, in this separate form, is intended for the use of Students who wish to make
themselves acquainted with German Grammar chiefly for the purpose of being
able to read German books.</p>
<p>German Composition; Α Theoretical and Practical Guide to
fhe Art of Translating English Prose into German, 8vo. 4s. 6d.</p>
<p>Lessing's Laokoon. With Introduction, English Notes, etc.
By A Hamann, Phil. Doc, M.A. Extra fcap. 8vo. 4s. 6d.</p>
<p>Schillers Wilhelm Tell. Translated irito English Verse by
Ε. Massie, M.A. Extra fcap. 8vo. 5s.</p>
<p>Also, Edited by C. A. BUCHHEIM, Phil. Doc.</p>
<p>Goethe's Egmont. With a Life of Goethe, c. Third Edition.
Extra fcap. 8vo, 3s.</p>
<p>— Lphigenie auf Tanris. Α Drama. With a Critical Introduction
and Notes, Second Edition. Extra fcap. 8vo. 3s.</p>
<p>Lessing's Minna von Barnhelm. Α Comedy. With a Life
of Lessing, Critical Analysis, Complete Commentary, c. Fourth Edition.
Extra fcap. 8vo, 3s. 6d.</p>
<p>— Nathan der Weise. With Introduction, Notes, etc.
Extra fcap. 8vo. 4s. 6d.</p>
<p>Schillers Historische Skizzen; Egmonfs Leben und Tod, and
Bellagerung von Antwerfen. Second Edition. Extra fcap. 8vo, 2s. 6d.</p>
<p>— Wilhelm Tell. With a Life of Schiller; an his-
torical and critical Introduction, Arguments, and a complete Commentary.
Sixth Edition, Extra fcap. 8vo. 3s. 6d.</p>
<p>— Wilhelm Tell. School Edition. Extra fcap. 8vo. 2s. 6d.
Just Published.</p>
<p>Halifis Griseldis. In Preparation.</p>
<p>Modern German Reader. Α Graduated Collection of Prose
Extracts from Modern German writers :—</p>
<p>Part I, With English Notes, a Grammatical Appendix, and a complete
Vocabulary. Third Edition, Extra fcap. 8vo. 2s. 6d.</p>
<p>Parts II and III in Preparation.</p>

<pb n="27"/>
<p>VI. MATHEMATICS, PHySICAL SCIENCE, &amp;c.</p>
<p>By LEWIS HENSLET, M.A.</p>
<p>Figures made Easy: a first Arithmetic Book. (Introductory
to ‘ The Scholar's Arithmetic.') Crown 8vo. 6d.</p>
<p>Answers to the Examples in Figures made Easy, together
with two thousand additional Examples formed from the Tables in the same,
with Answers. Crown 8vo. 1s.</p>
<p>The Scholar's Arithmetic: with Answers to the Examples.
Crown 8vo. 4s. 6d.</p>
<p>The Scholar's Algebra. An Introductory work on Algebra.
Crown 8vo. 4s. 6d.</p>
<p>Baynes (R. E., M.A.). Lessons on Thermodynamics. 1878.
Crown 8vo. 7s. 6d.</p>
<p>Chambers (G. F., F.R.A.S.). A Handbook of Descriptive
Astronomy. Third Edition. 1877. Demy 8vo. 28s.</p>
<p>Clarke (Col. A. R., C.B., R.E.). Geodesy. 1880. 8vo. 12s. 6d.</p>
<p>Donkin (W. F., M.A., F.R.S.). Acoustics. 1870. Crown 8vo.
7s. 6d.</p>
<p>Galton (Douglas, C.B., F.R.S.). The Construction of Healthy
Dwellings; namely Houses, Hospitals, Barracks, Asylums, c. Demy
10s. 6d.</p>
<p>Hamilton (R. G. C.). and jf. Ball. Book-keeping. New and
enlarged Edition. Extra fcap. 8vo. limp cloth, 2s.</p>
<p>Harcourt (A. G. Vernon, M.A.), and H. G. Madan, M.A.
Exercises in Practical Chemistry. Vol. I. Elementary Exercises. Third
Edition. Crown 8vo. 9s.</p>
<p>Maclaren (Archibald). A System of Physical Education :
Theoretical and Practical. Extra fcap. 8vo. 7s. 6d.</p>
<p>Madan (H. G. M.A.). Tables of Qtialitative Analysis.
Large 4to. paper, 4s. 6d.</p>
<p>Maxinell (f. Clerk, M.A., F.R.S.). A Treatise on Electricity
and Alagmtism. Second Edition. 2 vols. Demy 8vo. 1l. 11s. 6d.</p>
<p>— An Elementary Treatise on Electricity. Edited by
William Gamett, M.A. Demy 8vo. 7s. 6d.</p>

<pb n="28"/>
<p>Minchin (G. M., M.A.). A Treatise on Statics. Second
Edition, Revised and Enlarged. 1879. 8vo. 14s.</p>
<p>— Uniplanar Kinematics of Solids and Fluids. Crown 8vo.
7s. 6d.</p>
<p>Rolleston (G., M.D., F.R.S.). Forms of Animal Life. Illustrated
by Descriptions and Drawings of Dissections. A New Edition in the
Press.</p>
<p>Smyth. A Cycle of Celestial Objects. Observed, Reduced,
and Discussed by Admiral W. H. Smyth, R.N. Revised, condensed, and
greatly enlarged by G. F. Chambers, F.R.A.S. 1881. 8vo. 21s.</p>
<p>Stewart (Balfour, LL.D., F.R.S.). A Treatse on Heat, with
numerous Woodcuts and Diagrams. Fourth Edition. 1881. Extra fcap. 8vo.
7s. 6d.</p>
<p>Story-Maskelyne (M. H. N., M.A.). Crystallography. In the
Press.</p>
<p>Vemon-Harcotirt (L. F., M.A.). A Treatise on Rivers and
Canals, relating to the Control and Improvement of Rivers, and the Design,
Construction, and Development of Canals. 2 vols. (Vol. I, Text. Vol. II,
Plates.) 8vo. 21s.</p>
<p>Watson (H. W., M.A.). A Treatise on the Kinetic Theory
of Gases. 1876. 8vo. 3s. 6d.</p>
<p>Watson (H. W., M.A.), and Burbury (S. H, M.A.). A Treatise
on the Application of Generalised Coordinates to the Kinetics of a Material
Systevi. 1879. 8vo. 6s.</p>
<p>Williamson (A. W., Phil. Doc, F.R.S.). Chemistry for
Stttdents. A new Edition, with Solutions. 1873. Extra fcap. 8vo. 8s. 6d.</p>
<p>VII. HISTORY.</p>
<p>Finlay (George, LL.D.). A History of Greece from its Conquest
by the Romans to the present time, B.C. 146 to B.C. 1864. A new
Edition, revised throughout, and in part re-written, with considerable additions,
by the Author, and edited by H. F. Tozer, M.A. 1877. 7 vols. 8vo. 3l. 10s.</p>
<p>Freeman (E.A., M.A.). A Short History of the Norman
Conquest of England. Second Edition. Extra fcap. 8vo. 2s. 6d.</p>
<p>— A History of Greece. In preparation.
George (H. B., M.A .). Genealogical Tables illustrative ofModern
History. Second Edition, Revised and Enlarged. Small 4to. 12s.</p>
<p>Hodgkin (T.). Italy and her Invaders, A.D. 376—476.
with Plates and Maps. 2 vols. 8vo. 1l. 12s.</p>

<pb n="29"/>
<p>Kitchin (G. W., M.A.) A History of France. With numerous
Maps, Plans, and Tables. In Three Volumes. 1873—77. Crown 8vo.
10s. 6d.</p>
<p>Vol. I. Second Edition. Down to the Year 1453.</p>
<p>Vol. 2. From 1453—1624.</p>
<p>Vol. 3. From 1624—1793.</p>
<p>Payne (E. f., M.A.). A History of the United States of
America. In the Press.</p>
<p>Ranke [L. von). A History of England, principally in the
Seventeenth Century. Translated by Resident Members of the University of
Oxford, under the snperintendence of G. W. Kitchin, M.A., and C. W. Boase,
M.A. 1875. 6 vols. 8vo. 3l. 3s.</p>
<p>Rawlinson (George, M.A.). A Mannal of Ancient History.
Second Edition. Demy 8vo. 14s.</p>
<p>Select Charters and other Illustrations of English Constitutional
History, from the Earliest Times to the Reign of Edward I. Arranged aud
edited by W. Stubbs, M.A. Fourth Edition. 1881. Crown 8vo. 8s. 6d.</p>
<p>Stuhhs (W., D.D.). The Constitutional History of England,
in its Origin and Development. Library Edition. 3 vols. demy 8vo. 2l. 8s.</p>
<p>Also in 3 vols. crown 8vo. price 12s. each.</p>
<p>Wellesley. A Selection froni the Despatches, Treaties, aiui
other Papers of the Marquess Wellesley, K.G., during his Govemment
oflndia. Edited by S. J. Owen, M.A. 1877. 8vo. 1l. 4s.</p>
<p>wellington. A Selection froin the Despatches, Treaties, and
other Papers relating to India of Field-Marshal the Duke ofWellington, K.G.
Edited by S. J. Owen, M.A. 1880. 8vo. 24s.</p>
<p>A History of British India. By S. J. Owen, M.A., Reader
in Indian History in the University of Oxford. In preparation.</p>
<p>Vm. LAW.</p>
<p>Alherici Gentilis, I.C.D., I.C. Professoris Regii, De lure Belli
Libri Tres. Edidit Thomas Erskine HoIIand, I.C.D. 1877. Small 4to.
half morocco, 21 s.</p>
<p>Anson (Sir William R., Bart., D.C.L.). Principles of the
English Law of Contract, and of Agency in its Relation to Contract. Second
Edition. Demy 8vo. 10s. 6d.</p>
<p>Bentham (feremy). An Introduction to the Principles of
Morals and Legislation. Crown 8vo. 6s. 6d.</p>

<pb n="30"/>
<p>Digby (Kenelm E., M.A.). An Introduction to the History of
the Law of Real Property, with original Authorities Second Edition. 1876.
Crown 8vo. 7s. 6d.</p>
<p>Gaii Institutionum Juris Civilis Conimentarii Quattuor; or,
Elements of Roman Law by Gaius. With a Translation and Commentary
by Edward Poste, M.A. Second Edition. 1875. 8vo. 18s.</p>
<p>Hall ( W. E., M.A.). Internatiotial Law. Second Edition.
Demy 8vo. 21s.</p>
<p>Holland (T. E., D.C.L.). The Elements of Jurisprudence.
Second Edition. Demy 8vo. ios. dd.</p>
<p>Imperatoris lustiniani histitutionum Libri Quattuor; with
Introductions, Commentary, Excursus and Translation. By J. B. Moyle, B.C.L.,
M.A. 2 vols. Demy 8vo. 21s.</p>
<p>fustinian, The Institutes of, edited as a recension of the
Institutes of Gaius, by Thomas Erskine HoUand, D.C.L. Second Edition,
1881. Extra fcap. 8vo. 5s.</p>
<p>fustinian, Select Titles from the Digest of. By T. E. Holland,
D.C.L., and C. L. Shadwell, B.C.L. 8vo. 14s.</p>
<p>Also sold in Parts, in paper covers, as follows :—</p>
<p>Part I. Introductory Titles. 2s. 6d. Part II. Family Law. 1s.</p>
<p>Part III. Property Law. 2s. 6d. Part IV. Law of Obligations (No. 1). 35. 6d.</p>
<p>Part IV. Law of Obligations (No. 2). 4s. 6d.</p>
<p>Markby (W., M.A.). Elements of Law considered with reference
to Principles of General Jurisprudence. Second Edition, with Supplement.
1874. Crown 8vo. 7s. 6d. Supplement separately, 2s.</p>
<p>Twiss (Sir Travers, D.C L.). The Law of Nations considered
as Independent Political Communities.</p>
<p>Part I. On the Rights and Duties of Nations in time of Peace. A new Edition,
Revised and Enlarged. 1884. Demy 8vo. 15s.</p>
<p>Part II. On the Rights and Duties of Nations in Time of War. Second Edition
Revised. 1875. Deniy 8vo. 21s.</p>
<p>IX. MENTAL AND MORAL PHILOSOPHY, c.</p>
<p>Bacon's Novum Organum. Edited, with EngHsh Notes, by
G. W. Kitchin, M.A. 1855. 8vo. 9s. 6d.</p>
<p>— Translated by G. W. Kitchin, M.A. 1855. 8vo. 8vo. 6d.</p>
<p>Berkeley. The Works of George Berkeley, D.D., formerly
Bishop of Cloyne; including many of his writings hitherto unpublished.
With Prefaces, Annotations, and an Account of his Life and Philosophy,
by Alexander Campbell Fraser, M.A. 4 vols. 1871. 8vo. 8vo. 18s.</p>
<p>The Life, Letters, c. 1 vol. 16s.</p>
<p>— Selections from. With an Introduction and Notes.
For the use of Students in the Universities, By Alexander Campbell Fraser,
LL.D. Secoiid Edition, Crown 8vo, 7s. 6d.</p>

<pb n="31"/>
<p>Fowler (T., M.A.). The Elemeitts of Deductive Logic, designed
mainly for the use of Junior Students in the Universities. Eighth Edition,
with a Collection of Examples. Extra fcap. 8vo. 3s. 6d.</p>
<p>— The Elements of Inductive Logic, designed mainly for
the use of Students in the Universities. Fourth Edition. Extra fcap. 8vo. 6s.</p>
<p>Edited by T. POWLEB, M.A.</p>
<p>Bacon. Novum Orgatmm. With Introduction, Notes, &amp;c.
1878. 8vo. 14s.</p>
<p>Locke's Cojtduct of the Understanding. Second Edition.
Extra Fcap. 8vo. 2s.</p>
<p>Green (T. H., M.A.). Prolegomefia to Ethics. Edited by
A. C. Bradley, M.A. Demy 8vo. 12s. 6d.</p>
<p>Hegel. The Logic of Hegel; translated from the Encyclopaedia
of the Philosophical Sciences. With Prolegomena by William
Wallace, M.A. 1874. 8vo. 14s.</p>
<p>Lotzes Logic, in Three Books; of Thought, of Investigation,
and οἱ Knowledge. English Translation; Edited by B. Bosanquet, M M.A.,
Fellow of University College, Oxford. 8vo. cloth, 12s. 6d.</p>
<p>— Metaphysic, in Three Books; Ontology, Cosmology,
and Psychology. English Translation; Edited by B. Bosanquet, M.A.,
Fellow of University College, Oxford. 8vo. cloth, 12s. 6d.</p>
<p>Rogers (f. E. Thorold, M.A.). A Manual of Political Economy,
for the use of Schools. Third Edition. ἃκ fcap. 8vo. 4s. 6d.</p>
<p>Smith's Wealth of Nations. A new Edition, with Notes, by
J. E. Thorold Rogers, M.A. 2 vols. 8vo. 1880. 21s.</p>
<p>X. ABT, c.</p>
<p>Htdlah (fohn). The Cuitivation of the Speaking Voice.
Second Edition. Extra fcap. 8vo. 2s. 6d.</p>
<p>Ouseley (Sir F. A. Gore, Bart.). A Treatise on Harmony.
Third Edition. 4to. 10s.</p>
<p>— A Treatise on Counterpoint, Canon, and Fugue, based
upon that of Cherubini. Second Edition. 4to. 16s</p>
<p>— A Treatise on Musical Form and General Composition.
4to. 10s.</p>
<p>Robinson (f. C., F.S.A.). A Critical Account of tJte Drawings
by Michel Angelo and Haffaello in the University Galleries, Oxford. 1870.
Crown 8vo. 4s.</p>

<pb n="32"/>
<p>Ruskin (fohn, M.A.). A Course of Lectures on Art, delivered
beiore the University of Oxford in Hilary Term, 1870. 8vo. 6s.</p>
<p>Troutbeck (f., M.A.) and R. F. Dale, M.A. A Music Primer
(for Schools). Second Edition. Crown 8vo. 1s. 6d.</p>
<p>Tyrwhitt (R. St. f., M.A.). A Handbook of Pictorial Art.
With coloured IUustrations, Photographs, and a chapter on Perspective by
A. Macdonald. Second Edition. 1875. 8vo. halfmorocco, 18s.</p>
<p>Vaux ( W. S. W., M.A., F.R.S.). Catalogue of the Castellani
Collection οἱ Antiquities in the University Galleries, Oxford. Crown 8vo.
stiff cover, is.</p>
<p>The Oxford Bible for Teachers, containing supplemenary
Helps to the Study of the Bible, including Summaries
of the several Books, with copious Explanatory Notes and Tables
illustrative of Scripture History and the characteristics of Bible
Lands, with a complete Index of Subjects, a Concordance, a Dictionary
of Proper Names, and a series of Maps. Prices in various sizes
and bindings from 3s. to 2l. 5s.</p>
<p>Helps to the Study of the Bible, taken from the
OXFORD BiBLE FOR Teachers, comprising Summaries of the
several Books, with copious Explanatory Notes and Tables illustrative
of Scripture History and the Gharacteristics of Bible Lands;
with a complete Index of Subjects, a Concordance, a Dictionary
of Proper Names, and a series of Maps. Pearl 16mo. cloth, 1s.</p>
<p>LONDON: HENRY FROWDE,
OxFORD University Press Warehouse, AMEN Corner.</p>
<p>OXFORD: CLARENDON PRESS. DEPOSITORY,
116 HIGH STREET.</p>
<p>The DELEGATES OF THE PRESS invite suggestions and advice frovt all persons
interested in education; and will be thankful for hints, ec. addressed to the
SECRETARY TO THE DELEGATES, Clarendon Press, Oxford.</p>

</div>
</div>
</body></text></TEI>
