<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:lang="lat">Geographiae Informatio</title>
                <author>Agathemerus</author>
                <editor>Aubrey Diller</editor>
                <funder>Harvard Library Arcadia Fund</funder>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="DDD">Digital Divide Data</persName>
                    <resp>Corrected and encoded the text</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName>Gregory Crane</persName>
                    <resp>Editor-in-Chief, Perseus Digital Library</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName>Matt Munson</persName>
                    <resp>Project Manager (University of Leipzig), 2016 - 2018</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName>Annette Gessner</persName>
                    <resp>Project Assistant (University of Leipzig), 2015 - 2017</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName>Thibault Clérice</persName>
                    <resp>Lead Developer (University of Leipzig), 2015 - 2017</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName>Bruce Robertson</persName>
                    <resp>Technical Advisor</resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Harvard College Library</authority>
                
                <idno type="filename">tlg0090.tlg001.opp-eng1.xml</idno>
                <availability>
                    <p>Available under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International
                        License</p>
                </availability>
                <date>2018</date>
                <publisher>Harvard College Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>United States</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>

                <listBibl>


                    <biblStruct>
                        <monogr>
                            <title>Agathemerus. "Sketch of Geography"</title>
                            <editor>
                                <persName>Aubrey Diller</persName>
                            </editor>
                            <author ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0090">Agathemerus</author>
                            
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope unit="issue">16</biblScope>
                                <biblScope unit="pp" from="59" to="76">59-76</biblScope>
                                <publisher>Duke University Libraries</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>Duke University</pubPlace>
                                <date>1975</date>
                            </imprint>

                        </monogr>
                        <ref target="http://grbs.library.duke.edu/article/view/8681">Greek Roman and Byzantine Studies n. 16</ref>



                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>

            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>

        
        
                <p>Text encoded in accordance with the latest EpiDoc standards</p>
                <p>The following text is encoded in accordance with EpiDoc standards and with the
                    CTS/CITE Architecture.</p>

            <refsDecl n="CTS">
                <cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(.+).(.+)"
                    replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:div[@n='$2'])">
                    <p>This pointer pattern extracts chapters and sections</p>
                </cRefPattern>
                <cRefPattern n="chapter" matchPattern="(.+)"
                    replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
                    <p>This pointer pattern extracts chapters</p>
                </cRefPattern>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>

        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
                <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
                <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>

        <revisionDesc>

  <change who="Chiara Palladino" when="2018-03-20">Created the XML file and made the file
                CTS compliant</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0090.tlg001.opp-eng1" xml:lang="eng">


<pb n="67"/>

                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="1">
                    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
                        <p> Anaximander of Miletus, disciple of Thales, ﬁrst attempted to draw the
                            earth on a map. After him Hecataeus of Miletus, a widely- traveled man,
                            improved the work marvelously. Hellanicus of Lesbos, a man of much
                            learning, gave his account without a map. Then Damastes of Citium wrote
                            a circumnavigation, drawing mostly on Hecataeus. Next Democritus and
                            Eudoxus and others wrote tours of the earth by land and sea. </p>
                    </div>


                    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
                        <p> The ancients drew the earth round, and regarded Hellas as the center and
                            Delphi as the center of Hellas, since it had the navel of the earth.
                            Democritus, a man of much experience, ﬁrst perceived that the earth was
                            oblong, with the length half again the breadth. Dicaearchus the
                            Peripatetic agreed with him. Eudoxus made the length double the breadth,
                            Eratosthenes more than double, Crates semicircular, Hipparchus
                            trapezoid, others . . . , Posidonius the Stoic sling-shaped and wide in
                            the middle from south to north, narrow to the east and west, wider,
                            however, to the southeast, toward India. </p>
                    </div>


                    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
                        <p> Boundaries of the continents: of Europe and Libya the Pillars of
                            Hercules; of Libya and Asia the Nile, but some say the isthmus between
                            Lake Serbonis and the Arabian gulf; of Asia and Europe the ancients said
                            the Phasis River and the isthmus to the Caspian, the later and more
                            recent ones say Lake Maeotis and the Tanais River. </p>
                    </div>

                    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
                        <p> The continents were called <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἤπειροι</foreign> as being 
                            boundless <foreign xml:lang="grc">(ἄπειροι)</foreign> , out of
                            ignorance. Asia was named for coming close
                            <foreign xml:lang="grc">(ἆσσον)</foreign> for those going over
                            from Europe both by land and by the islands lying in a row: Euboea
                            Andros Tenos Myconos Icaria Samos Mycale. Europe was named for its
                            breadth <foreign xml:lang="grc">(εὖρος)</foreign>. Libya was quite unknown to the Greeks,
                            but from a
                            signal nation †Phoenicians were named seafaring†. The ocean was named
                            for quickly encircling <foreign xml:lang="grc">(ὠκέως ἀνύειν)</foreign> the earth. </p>
                    </div>


                    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
                        <p> Dicaearchus bounds the earth not by waters but by a straight line from
                            the Pillars through Sardinia Sicily Peloponnesus Ionia Caria Lycia
                            Pamphylia Cilicia and Taurus on to Mt Imaus, and he calls the several
                            regions either northern or southern. </p>
                    </div>

                </div>

                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="2">
                    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
                        <p> The winds blow: from equinoctial sunrise <hi rend="italic">apeliotes</hi>, 
                            from equinoctial
                            sunset <hi rend="italic">zephyros</hi> from midday <hi rend="italic">notos</hi>, 
                            from the bear <hi rend="italic">aparctias</hi>, 
                            <pb n="68"/>
                            from summer
                            solstice (sunrise) <hi rend="italic">kaikias</hi>, and next, from equinoctial sunrise
                            <hi rend="italic">apeliotes</hi>, and from winter sunrise <hi rend="italic">euros</hi>,
                            and in the west, from winter
                            sunset <hi rend="italic">lips</hi>, 
                            and next again, from equinoctial sunset <hi rend="italic">zephyros</hi> 
                            from
                            summer sunset <hi rend="italic">argestes</hi> 
                            or <hi rend="italic">Olympias</hi> also called <hi rend="italic">Iapyx</hi>, 
                            then <hi rend="italic">notos</hi> and
                            <hi rend="italic">aparctias</hi> blowing opposite each other; so there are eight. </p>
                    </div>

                    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7">
                        <p> But Timosthenes, who wrote the circumnavigations, says there are twelve,
                            adding <hi rend="italic">boreas</hi> between <hi rend="italic">aparctias</hi> 
                            and <hi rend="italic">kaikias</hi>, <hi rend="italic">phoinix</hi> also called
                            <hi rend="italic">euronotos</hi> between <hi rend="italic">euros</hi> 
                            and <hi rend="italic">notos</hi>, <hi rend="italic">leuconotos</hi> 
                            or <hi rend="italic">libonotos</hi> between <hi rend="italic">notos</hi>
                            and <hi rend="italic">lips</hi>, <hi rend="italic">thrascias</hi> 
                            or <hi rend="italic">kirkios</hi> (as called by the local people) between
                            <hi rend="italic">aparctias</hi> and <hi rend="italic">argestes</hi>. 
                            He says nations dwell on the borders of the
                            earth, towards <hi rend="italic">apeliotes</hi> Bactrians, 
                            towards <hi rend="italic">euros</hi> Indians, towards
                            <hi rend="italic">phoinix</hi> the Red Sea and Aethiopia, towards 
                            <hi rend="italic">notos</hi> Aethiopia beyond Egypt,
                            towards <hi rend="italic">leuconotos</hi> Garamantes
                            beyond the Syrtes, towards <hi rend="italic">lips</hi> western
                            Aethiopians beyond Moors, towards <hi rend="italic">zephyos</hi> 
                            the Pillars and the beginnings
                            of Libya and Europe, towards <hi rend="italic">argestes</hi> 
                            Iberia, now Hispania, towards
                            <hi rend="italic">thrascias</hi> 
                            Celts and their neighbors, towards <hi rend="italic">aparctias</hi> 
                            Scythians beyond
                            Thrace, towards <hi rend="italic">borras</hi> 
                            Pontus Maeotis Sarmatians, towards <hi rend="italic">kaikias</hi> the
                            Caspian Sea and Sacae. </p>
                    </div>
                </div>


                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="3">
                    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8">
                        <p>The Great Syrtis is 5000 stades, the Little Syrtis 1600 stades. The mouth
                            of the Adriatic, which some call the Ionian Sea, has a passage of 700
                            stades from the tip of Iapygia to the Ceraunian mountains in Epirus.
                        </p>
                    </div>


                    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9">
                        <p> After the Aegean Sea comes the Hellespont ending at Abydus and Sestus,
                            then the Propontis ending at Chalcedon and Byzantium, where the narrows
                            are from which the Pontus begins, then Lake Maeotis. Again, from the
                            beginning of Europe and Libya the Iberian Sea from the Pillars to Mt
                            Pyrene, the Ligurian as far as the borders of Etruria, the Sardinian
                            beyond Sardinia bending down towards Libya, the Tuscan ending as far as
                            Sicily and beginning from the capes of Liguria, then the Libyan, then
                            the Cretan and Sicilian and Ionian and Adriatic and the one opening out
                            of the Sicilian sea, which they call the gulf of Corinth or Halcyon sea.
                            The Saronic sea enclosed by Sunium and Scyllaeum, then the Myrtoan and
                            Icarian, in which are the Cyclades, then the Carpathian and Pamphylian
                            and Egyptian. Beyond the Icarian spreads the Aegean. </p>
                    </div>

                    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10">
                        <p>The coast of Europe from the outlet of the Tanais River to the Pillars of
                            Hercules is 69709 stades, of Libya from Tingis to the Canobic mouth is
                            29252 stades, of Asia from Canobus to the Tanais River, with the gulfs,
                            is <pb n="69"/> 40111 stades; altogether, the coast of our earth, with the gulfs, is
                            139072 stades, including Lake Maeotis, of which the perimeter is 9000
                            stades and the mouth at the Cimmerian Bosporus is 
                            
                            <choice>
                                <corr resp="#AD" evidence="conjecture">20</corr>
                                <sic>70</sic>
                            </choice>
                        
                            
                            
                            stades. </p>
                    </div>

                    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11">
                        <p> The Pontus is 3350 stades, the narrows at the Thracian Bosporus, where
                            Dareius built the bridge against the Scythians, is six stades.</p>
                    </div>


                    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12">
                        <p>The Persian Sea, being round and narrowing to the mouth at the capes of
                            Carmania and Arabia, has a perimeter of 20000 stades; the mouth, between
                            Arabia and Carmania is 400 stades. </p>
                    </div>

                    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13">
                        <p> The Hyrcanian or Caspian Sea, being crescent-shaped, but some say
                            oblong, is 20000 stades and has a passage of 1000 stades at the
                            mouth.</p>
                    </div>

                    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14">
                        <p> The Arabian Gulf, being narrow and oblong, begins from the gulf of
                            Heroöpolis along Troglodytica to Ptolemais at the Hunts 9000 stades
                            long, where follows a voyage of 6500 stades, the narrows at Deire of 60
                            stades, along the Red Sea to the ocean 5000 stades, the rest is not
                            navigated. The side along Arabia from the gulf of Aelana is 14000
                            stades. Arabia itself extends to the Red Sea and lengthens to 12000
                            stades.</p>
                    </div>

                </div>

                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="4">
                    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15">
                        <p> The length of the earth from the Ganges to Gades is 68545 stades, thus:
                            from the Ganges River to Myriandrus in the gulf of Issus 41725 stades,
                            thus: from the Ganges to the outlet of the Indus River 16000 stades,
                            from the Indus to the Caspian Gates 15300 stades, to the Euphrates 10050
                            stades, to Myriandrus 375 stades. </p>
                    </div>



                    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16">
                        <p>From Myriandrus to Gades 26820 stades, thus: from Myriandrus to the Keys
                            of Cyprus 1400 stades, to Cape Acamas 1300 stades, to the Chelidoniae
                            through the Pamphylian sea 1900 stades, to Patara 800 stades, to Rhodes
                            700 stades, to Astypalaea through the Carpathian †140 stades, to
                            Taenarum 1950 stades, to Pachynum in Sicily 4000 stades, to Lilybaeum
                            through the Libyan sea 1520 stades, to Caralis in Sardinia through the
                            Tuscan sea 1800 stades, to Gades past the Gymnesiae islands 10000
                            stades, from Gades past the Sacred Cape and harbor of the Artabrians
                            7932. Altogether 76477 stades. </p>
                    </div>


                    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17">
                        <p>Another way: from the Ganges to the Euphrates River 41350, from the
                            Euphrates to Mazaca in Cappadocia 1950 stades, from Mazaca through
                            piedmont and great Phrygia and Caria to Ephesus 3990 stades, altogether
                            from the Ganges to Ephesus 47290 stades. From Ephesus to Delos through
                            the Aegean 1600 stades, to the Isthmus 1700 stades, from the Isthmus
                            through the Gulf of Corinth to Patrae 720 stades, to Leucas 700 stades, <pb n="70"/>
                            to Corcyra 700 stades, to the Acroceraunian mountains 660 stades, to
                            Brundisium 700 stades, from Brundisium by land to Rome 2880 stades, from
                            Rome to the Alps at the village Scingomagus beneath the Alps 4152
                            stades, then through Celtica to the town Illygyris beneath Pyrene 3744
                            stades, then through Iberia to Gades 6654 stades, and the passage to
                            Gades by way of the inns 60 stades. Altogether from the Ganges to Gades
                            71560 stades.</p>
                    </div>


                    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18">
                        <p>The breadth of the earth from the Aethiopian sea to Meroe 5000 stades,
                            from Meroe to Alexandria 10000 stades, from Alexandria to the Tanais
                            †11056, above the outlet of the Tanais to the north is unknown, thus:
                            from Alexandria to Lindus in Rhodes 4500 stades, to Thoantion passing
                            Rhodes on the right 400 stades, to Telos 160 stades, to Lacter in Cos
                            120 stades, to Drepanon in Cos 100 stades, to the island Arcitis 230
                            stades, to Corsiae 100, to Ampelus in Samos 30 stades, to Argennon
                            through the Aegean 500 stades, to Erythraean Corynaion 270 stades, to
                            Cape †Phlion in Chios 50 stades, to Cape Melaneus in Lesbos 450 stades,
                            to Sigrion in Lesbos 500 stades, to the island Tenedos 450 stades, to
                            Sigeum 100 stades, to the mouth of Pontus 2500 stades, to Carambis 2800
                            stades, to the mouth of Maeotis 2500 stades, to the Tanais 2200 stades.
                        </p>
                    </div>

                    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19">
                        <p>Another way, from city to city: from Alexandria to Rhodes 4670 stades, to
                            Cnidus 700 stades, to Cos 200 stades, to Samos 800 stades, to Chios 750
                            stades, to Mitylene 520 stades, to Tenedos 950, to Sigeum 100, to the
                            mouth of Pontus 2500, to Carambis 2800, to the mouth of Maeotis 2500, to
                            the Tanais River 2200; altogether from Alexandria to Tanais 18690
                            stades. </p>
                    </div>

                </div>

                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="5">
                    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20">
                        <p> Finally, we will give the perimeters of the islands of our earth taking
                            them from Artemidorus and Menippus and other trustworthy authors. Gades
                            is 120 stades long, 16 wide; the passage at the Pillars of Hercules is
                            80 stades at the narrowest; in the Iberian sea, of the Pityussae islands
                            the greater, inhabited, is 300 stades long, the lesser 100 stades; of
                            the Gymnasiae, which the Carthaginians call Baliariae (for slingers are
                            thus called Baliares) the greater is 1200 stades long, 400 stades wide,
                            the lesser 300 stades. The Stoechades so-called lie in a row in front of
                            the Massilian towns, three greater and two small near Massilia itself.
                            Sardinia has the shape of a footprint, hollow in the middle, 2200 long;
                            Corsica near Sardinia but much poorer is less than half as long as
                            Sardinia; the take-off for Sardinia and Corsica is Popu<pb n="71" break="no"/>
                            lonium in
                            Etruria, the passage 1200 stades. The perimeter of Sicily according to
                            Timosthenes is 4740 stades, the shape a scalene triangle, the passage
                            from Cape Pelorus to Italy 12 stades. The side of the island from
                            Pelorus to Pachynum is 1360 stades, from Pachynum to Lilybaeum 1600
                            stades, from Lilybaeum to Pelorias according to Timosthenes 1700 stades;
                            the passage from Lilybaeum to Aspis in Libya about 1500 stades. </p>
                    </div>

                    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="21">
                        <p> The island Cercina is 200 long, 70 stades wide, but 40 at the narrowest;
                            it lies off the town Theёne on the mainland at the beginning of the
                            lesser Syrtis; beside Cercina lies the island Carcinitis, joined by a
                            bridge, 40 stades long, 25 stades wide. </p>
                    </div>


                    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="22">
                        <p>From Cercina to the island Meninx Lotophagitis the passage is 600 stades,
                            as is said to be the mouth of the lesser Syrtis; Meninx is 600 stades
                            long, 180 stades wide, and there are great currents around it. </p>
                    </div>

                    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="23">
                        <p>The island Cephallenia, of four towns, is 400 stades long. There are also
                            in the Adriatic islands along Illyria, especially Issa and Black Corcyra
                            and Pharos and Melite, of which I do not know the perimeters. </p>
                    </div>


                    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="24">
                        <p>The circumnavigation of the Peloponnesus counting the gulfs is 5627
                            stades, without entering the gulfs 4000 stades; the length from Malea to
                            Aegium is 1400 stades; the shape like a plane leaf, cut up by great
                            gulfs; it narrows in the Gulf of Corinth to the Isthmus 40 stades wide
                            between the Corinthian and Saronic gulfs.
                            
                            <gap resp="#AD" extent="unknown" reason="omitted"/>
                            
                            to Cape Scyllaeum with
                            the island Calauria to the left sacred to Poseidon, then the gulf of
                            Hermione, next the gulf of Argos as far as Cape Malea, which juts far
                            into the sea, next after Malea the gulf of Laconia as far as Taenarum on
                            the right, which bounds the gulf of Messenia on the left with Cape
                            Acritas on the right, then Cape Ichthys, off which is Zacynthus, and
                            Cape Chelonatas, and ﬁnally Cape Araxus facing Acarnania, after which
                            opens up the Gulf of Corinth narrowing to a mouth of 7 stades at Rhion
                            in the Peloponnesus and Antirhion in Locris. From Taenarum to Phycus in
                            Libya the passage is 3000 stades. </p>
                    </div>


                    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="25">
                        <p>The island Aegina 160 stades long lies against Attica; Salamis 70 stades
                            long, Ceia 120. Of the Cyclades the greatest is Naxos, hence called
                            Little Sicily; to the right are the Sporades. Euboea is joined to
                            Boeotia by a bridge; it extends along Boeotia Phocis Locris, and on the
                            other end even a little along Attica, for it is long, hence called
                            Macris, the length 1700 stades. </p>
                    </div>

                    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="26">
                        <p> Crete is near the Peloponnesus off Malea, 4100 stades around, 2300 long,
                            for it is much lengthened; Cythera is between Crete and Laconia. Cyprus
                            has the shape of a hide, perimeter 3420 stades, length 1300; from Paphos
                            to Alexandria the passage is from <pb n="71"/> 
                            the north, 3800 stades. The perimeter
                            of Rhodes is 1300 stades, of Cos 540 stades, of Samos 630 stades. Icaria
                            is long and rugged, the length 300 stades. The perimeter of Chios is 660
                            stades, of Lesbos 1100 stades. </p>
                    </div>
                </div>


            </div>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
